<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<messages>
  <message id="error-missing-data">

    <div>The data file "{1}" could not be found. Check your deployment.</div>
    
  </message>
  <message id="introduction">

<h2><span>Introduction</span></h2>

<p class="p">
  This example demonstrates some of the capabilities of
  the <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/namespaceWt_1_1Chart.html"
  target="_new">Wt charting widgets</a>. These widgets are implemented
  using
  the <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WPaintedWidget.html"
  target="_new">Wt painting API</a>, which provides cross-browser
  native painting, using VML, SVG, or the Html 5 canvas tag.
</p>

<p class="p">
  The two main chart widgets
  are <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1Chart_1_1WCartesianChart.html"
  target="_new">WCartesianChart</a>, which provides category charts
  and scatter plots,
  and <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1Chart_1_1WPieChart.html" target="_new">WPieChart</a>
  which provides pie charts. These widgets are based on the MVC
  mechanism, and retrieve their data from
  a <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WAbstractItemModel.html" target="_new">WAbstractItemModel</a>.
</p>

<p class="p">
  Many aspects of the charts may be customized. By default, style
  information for rendering data series are taken from a
  <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1Chart_1_1WChartPalette.html" target="_new">WChartPalette</a>. It
  is straight forward to specialize this class to provide different
  styles from the standard styles provided by <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1Chart_1_1WStandardPalette.html" target="_new">WStandardPalette</a>.
</p>

<p class="p">
  Btw, would you expect this example to work when Ajax/JavaScript are
  not available or disabled?
</p>

  </message>
  <message id="category chart">

<h2><span>Category Chart</span></h2>

<p class="p">
  A category chart uses categories on the X axis, and displays one or
  more data series on the Y axes. The values corresponding to each
  category are plotted consecutively (this is the main difference with
  a ScatterPlot). Each data series corresponds to a column from the
  model.
</p>

<p class="p">
  A cartesian chart provides automatic configuration of the axes, and
  support for a second Y axis. In addition, you may use a simple
  built-in legend, or extend the class to provide a specialized
  legend. <!-- In the example below, we use a manual Y axis configuration,
  with a break as would be commonly used when your data has a few
  outliers.-->
</p>

<p class="p">
  The table view allows editing of the model, which is automatically
  reflected in the chart.
</p>

  </message>
  <message id="scatter plot">

<h2><span>Scatter Plot (time series)</span></h2>

<p class="p">
  A scatter plot is very much like a category chart, but uses
  numerical data on the X axis. By default, these numerical data are
  mapped linearly on the X axis, but may also be log transformed (as
  can be configured for the Y axes). In addition, there is special
  support for displaying date series, by means of smart heuristics for
  chosing the labels on the X axis.
</p>

<p class="p">
  Below is an extract from historical financial market data.
</p>

  </message>
  <message id="scatter plot 2">

<h2><span>Scatter Plot (sine function)</span></h2>

<p class="p">
  Below we plot a single sine curves. We use 'curve' data series,
  which creates a smooth spline curve that interpolates the data
  points. As is typical when showing mathematical functions, we let
  the axes cross each other at the origin (0, 0).
</p>

  </message>
  <message id="pie chart">

<h2><span>Pie chart</span></h2>

<p class="p">
  The pie chart is provided by the WPieChart widget. A pie chart can
  only display data from one data series. The class supports both
  plain 2D pies, as well as a 3D effect (as used below). As shown
  below for the first segment, these may be separated from the pie to
  show emphasis.
</p>

  </message>
</messages>
