<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<messages xmlns:if="Wt.WTemplate.conditions">

<!--LAYOUT message blocks-->
  <message id="layout-intro">
    <p class="lead">Layout &#8212; building blocks for organizing your
    application as a tree of widgets</p>
  </message>

  <message id="layout-Containers">
    <h2 id="containers">Containers</h2>
    <p>
      The primary method for combining a number of widgets in a composite
      widget is a ${doc-link WContainerWidget}. This widget corresponds to an
      HTML <tt>&lt;span&gt;</tt> or <tt>&lt;div&gt;</tt> element (depending on
      whether it is inline or not). It can contain any number of children, and
      these children may be added or removed dynamically.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Container}
      ${src Container}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      Alternative to consider are a <a
      href="#/layout/html-templates">WTemplate</a>, which puts widgets
      inside an HTML fragment using placeholder substitution, or a <a
      href="#/trees-tables/table">WTable</a> for organizing children
      in a table (without using a layout manager).
    </p>
    ${<if:cpp>}
    <p>
      The container takes ownership of its children: when the parent
      is deleted, the children will be deleted as well. This does not
      stop you from deleting a child widget, as this also automatically
      removes it from the parent.
    </p>
    ${</if:cpp>}
    <p>
      As a fundamental building block of Wt, a container widget itself
      usually does not have any visual aspect (although it can very
      well be styled to give it for example margin and borders). The
      widgets that are contained can be positioned using <a
      href="#/layout/CSS">Cascading StyleSheets (CSS)</a> or a <a
      href="#/layout/layout-managers">Layout Manager</a>. CSS, which
      to most C++ developers will be a new technology, is worthwile
      learning as it will allow you to push many layout and style
      aspects of your application into a declarative text file. It
      also works irrespective of JavaScript, which is a clear benefit
      over layout managers. The latter are however the superior (and
      only) choice in case vertical fitting or stretching of children
      to the height of the container is needed.
    </p>
    <p>
      There are several specialized container classes that have
      additional markup or behaviour:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="#/layout/grouping-widgets">WGroupBox</a> adds a title and
          a frame
        </li>
        <li><a href="#/layout/grouping-widgets#panel">WPanel</a> adds
        a title and a collapsible frame</li>
        <li><a href="#/navigation/anchor">WAnchor</a> links to a URL
        </li>
        <li><a href="#/navigation/stacked-widget">WStackedWidget</a> displays
          only one of its children at a time</li>
      </ul>
    </p>

  </message>

  <message id="layout-Text">
    <h2 id="text">Text</h2>
    <p>
      Text provides a primary means for displaying information in the user
      interface. The ${doc-link WText} class provides a simple way to add plain
      or markup text to the user interface.
    </p>
    <p>
      The <tt>WText</tt> widget displays text using an HTML <tt>&lt;span&gt;
      </tt> or <tt>&lt;div&gt;</tt> element (depending on whether it is inline
      or not). It can display either XHTML formatted text or plain text.
    </p>
    <p>
      The text contents is contained in a ${doc-link WString}. This string
      class provides at the same time support for localization and
      internationalization:
      <ul>
        <li>It is a unicode string (internally store as UTF-8) with an
        API to interact with plain C++ strings.
        </li>
        <li>It supports localization, when created using <a href=
        "${doc-url}classWt_1_1WString.html#0afc7dc0f9897456d71b569a86ca26c1"
        target="_blank">WString::tr()</a>. The actual value
        corresponding to a key is retrieved from a ${doc-link
        WLocalizedStrings} instance, taking into account the current
        locale. The default implementation of this interface class
        uses XML files, which are convenient for specifying XHTML
        snippets.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      In its most simple form, the <tt>WText</tt> widget displays plain text
      (escaping special characters as needed).
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${TextPlain}
      ${src TextPlain}
    </fieldset>
    
    <p>
      Of course, a <tt>WText</tt> widget may also display XHTML formatted text.
    </p>
    
    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${TextXHTML}
      ${src TextXHTML}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      XHTML text that is not read from a localized strings interface (which is
      considered inherently safe), is protected against unwanted side effects
      from Cross-Site Scripting (XSS) attacks. The text of an XHTML-formatted
      <tt>WText</tt> is filtered using an XML parser and all malicious tags are
      removed (unless this feature is explicitly by-passed by using the
      <tt>XHTMLUnsafeText</tt> text format).
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${TextXSS}
      ${src TextXSS}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      If you want to display a text label associated with a form field then a
      ${doc-link WLabel} is more suitable as it can be linked to the input
      field, relaying focus to it when clicked.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you want to display an HTML fragment which contains widgets or other
      bound contents, then a <a href="#/layout/html-templates">WTemplate</a>
      widget is probably what you are looking for.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#text">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Events</h3>
    <p>
      The functionality of <tt>WText</tt> is very basic. As this widget derives
      - like many widgets - from ${doc-link WInteractWidget} it may respond to
      to mouse events and also keyboard events if it can be given keyboard
      focus. A few mouse events are demonstrated below.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${TextEvents}
      ${src TextEvents}
    </fieldset>

    <h3>ToolTip</h3>
    <p>
      You may add a tooltip or deferred tooltip to <tt>WText</tt> 
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Tooltip example</legend>
      ${TextToolTip}
      ${src TextToolTip}
    </fieldset>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Deferred tooltip example</legend>
      ${TextDeferredToolTip}
      ${src TextDeferredToolTip}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#text">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="layout-Template">
    <h2 id="templates">HTML Templates</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WTemplate} can be used to format a number of widgets within
      an XHTML fragment. This is especially useful as an alternative to a
      container widget if you want to use CSS for style and layout, and when
      the contents is relatively static: for each placeholder you must bind a
      widget or a string (which can be empty).
    </p>
    <p>
      In a template text, a <tt>$${<i>var</i>}</tt> indicates a place holder
      named <strong>var</strong> which is substituted with a widget or string
      that is bound to that variable. Other syntactical constructs are:
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>arguments</dt>
        <dd><tt>$${<i>var arg1 arg2</i>}</tt></dd>
        <dt>conditions</dt>
        <dd><tt>$${&lt;<i>condition</i>&gt;} ...
        $${&lt;/<i>condition</i>&gt;}</tt>
        </dd>
        <dt>functions</dt>
        <dd><tt>$${<i>fun:arg1 arg2</i>}</tt></dd>
      </dl>
    </p>
    <p>
      The template text can be provided by a <tt>WString</tt> and is thus
      easily localized and internalitionalized using a message resource bundle.
    </p>
    <p>
      Below is an example of a template text, illustrating the use of place
      holders for a line edit and two buttons.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="src">
      <legend>source</legend>
      <pre>${template-text}</pre>
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      This template text, made available as a string in a resource bundle with
      the id "WTemplate-example", is used by the following example:
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Template}
      ${src Template}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      If you want to simply display an HTML fragment without binding
      any widgets within it, then the <a href="#/layout/text">WText</a>
      widget is probably what you are looking for.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#templates">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="WTemplate-example">
    <div class="form">
      <p>
        <label>Please enter your name: ${name-edit}</label>
      </p>
      <p>
        ${save-button} ${cancel-button}
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="layout-Grouping">
    <h2 id="grouping">Group box</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WGroupBox} corresponds to an HTML
      <tt>&lt;fieldset&gt;</tt> element, and provides a frame and
      title around a group of widgets.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${GroupBox}
      ${src GroupBox}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      It is usually styled using the CSS stylesheet which provides many
      options for layout of the legend (title) and the box contents.
    </p>

    <h2 id="panel">Panel</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WPanel} is similar to a group box, but provides
      optional functionality to collapse or expand its contents, and a
      theme-based style.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PanelNoTitle}
      ${src PanelNoTitle}
    </fieldset>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Panel}
      ${src Panel}
    </fieldset>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PanelCollapsible}
      ${src PanelCollapsible}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#grouping">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="layout-Managers">
    <h2 id="managers">Layout Managers</h2>
    <p>
      Usually, CSS is a sufficient and convenient way to indicate how to
      layout widgets within a container widget, and we recommend to get
      accustomed with CSS for basic layout and styling.
    </p>
    <p>
      There are however several situations when CSS is not effective
      to create a layout, especially for complex web applications. In
      particular, when placing contents within a dialog it is often
      necessary to adjust its contents to available vertical space,
      and it is often desirable to distribute excess space to a
      particular widget while keeping other widgets to their preferred
      size. It is for these reasons that Wt has a comprehensive set of
      layout managers that use JavaScript to compute and apply layout
      managent to children of a <a
      href="#/layout/containers">WContainerWidget</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Wt provides the typical box, grid or border layout management
      options and layout managers and CSS can safely be intermixed.
    </p>

    <h3 id="layout-box">Box Layout</h3>
    <p>
      ${doc-link WVBoxLayout} and ${doc-link WHBoxLayout} provide
      respectively vertical and horizontal layout of widgets inside a
      <a href="#/layout/containers"><tt>WContainerWidget</tt></a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      In a horizontal box layout, widgets are given an appropriate
      width based on available space in the container and layout
      rules, while all widgets get the same height. Similarly, in a
      vertical box layout, widgets are given appropriate heights based
      on available space in the container and layout rules, while all
      widgets get the same width.
    </p>
    <p>
      In the example below, a <tt>WHBoxLayout</tt> with default
      padding (9 pixels) and spacing (6 pixels) is used to manage two
      child widgets. If no stretch factors have been specified, space
      is evenly distributed to all widgets.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${HBoxLayout}
      ${src HBoxLayout}
      <p>
	The coloring for this and the following examples are provided
	by a stylesheet that you need to load using
	<tt>WApplication::useStyleSheet()</tt>:
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
	<legend>CSS</legend>
	${tr:src-layout}
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      By giving <strong>Item 1</strong> a non-zero stretch factor value of 1,
      <strong>Item 2</strong> will only use its preferred width, and
      <i>Item 1</i> consumes all excess space, as illustrated below.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${HBoxLayoutStretch}
      ${src HBoxLayoutStretch}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      The preferred width of a widget is either based on its contents
      (which for text is the in some cases inpractical assumption of
      putting all text on a single line), but can be further
      controlled using <tt>widget->setWidth()</tt> or CSS
      <tt>width</tt> settings.
    </p>
    <p>
      The <tt>WVBoxLayout</tt> works in exactly the same way, but
      stacks children vertically.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${VBoxLayout}
      ${src VBoxLayout}
    </fieldset>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${VBoxLayoutStretch}
      ${src VBoxLayoutStretch}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      Layout managers may be arbitrarily nested, either directly, or
      indirectly through widget composition, to create complex
      layouts. Layout managers fully cooperate with CSS, honoring the
      CSS margins and paddings of children, but also those of
      intermediate widgets in complex layouts.
    </p>
    <p>
      In the example below we nest a <tt>WHBoxLayout</tt> containing
      two items in a <tt>WVBoxLayout</tt> containing one other item.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${NestedLayout}
      ${src NestedLayout}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#managers">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="layout-grid">Grid Layout</h3>
    <p>
      This layout manager organizes the contents of a <a
      href="#/basics/wcontainerwidget"><tt>WContainerWidget</tt></a>
      in a grid.
    </p>
    <p>
      Like <a
      href="#/style-and-layout/wboxlayout"><tt>WBoxLayout</tt></a>, a
      stretch factor defined for rows or columns is used to distribute
      excess space. In the example below, row 1 and columns 1 and 2
      are given a non-zero stretch factor.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${GridLayout}
      ${src GridLayout}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#managers">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="layout-border">Border Layout</h3>
    <p>
      This is a layout manager that organizes the container space in up to 5
      regions, with a central region consuming any excess space.
    </p>
    <p>
      Any of the regions can be omitted.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${BorderLayout}
      ${src BorderLayout}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#managers">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="borderlayout-item">
    <div>
      {1} item
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="layout-Dialogs">
    <h2 id="dialogs">Dialogs</h2>
    <p>
      A dialog is a window used to communicate information to the user
      and/or prompt the user for a response. Use the class ${doc-link
      WDialog} to show a dialog. A specialized dialog is also
      available to alert the user with a message then use the simple
      <a href="#message-box">WMessageBox</a> dialog.
    </p>
    <p>
      By default, a <tt>WDialog</tt> is modal. A modal window blocks
      the user interface, and does not allow the user to interact with
      any other part of the user interface until the dialog is
      closed. With a modeless dialog the window can be left open while
      the user continues in another window of the application. Use
      <tt>setModal(false)</tt> to create a non-modal dialog.  In the
      <a href="#message-box">Message box</a> section below you can
      find an example of a modeless window.
    </p>
    <p>
      Unlike other widgets, a dialog does not need to be added to a parent
      widget, and it is hidden by default. You must use the method
      <tt>show()</tt> or <tt>setHidden(false)</tt> to show the dialog. The
      dialog may be closed by calling <tt>accept()</tt>, <tt>reject()</tt> or
      <tt>done()</tt> (or connecting a signal to one of these methods). This
      will hide the dialog and emit the <tt>finished()</tt> signal, which you
      then can listen for to process the dialog result${<if:cpp>} and delete
      the dialog${</if:cpp>}.
      Typically, an OK button will be connected to <tt>accept()</tt>, and in
      some cases a Cancel button to <tt>reject()</tt>.
      You can add content to the dialog by adding the content to its container.
      You can get the container with the <tt>contents()</tt> method.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Dialog}
      ${src Dialog}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      A modal dialog can be instantiated in two ways &#8212;
      synchronously or asynchronously &#8212; while a non-modal dialog
      can only be instantiated asynchronously. By preference
      instantiate a dialog asynchronously. The synchronous use of a
      dialog is what is commonly done in desktop applications to show
      a modal dialog, and involves a call to <tt>exec()</tt> that
      starts a local event loop, and returns only when the dialog is
      closed. The draw-back of synchronous use is that the application
      is not scalable to many concurrent sessions, since it blocks a
      thread. This means it is only suitable for applications with
      restricted access or applications that are deployed on an
      intranet or extranet. When using a dialog asynchronously, there
      is no API call that waits for the dialog to be closed. In this
      case, the usage is similar to instantiating any other
      widget.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#dialogs">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="message-box">Message box</h3>
    <p>
      A message box is a simple dialog to alert the user with a message. It may
      require an acknowledgment that the message has been read (usually by
      clicking an "OK" button), or a decision as to whether or not an action
      should proceed (by clicking an "OK" or "Cancel" button).
    </p>
    <p>
      The usage is similar to instantiating a <tt>WDialog</tt> (or any other
      widget). You need to connect to the <tt>buttonClicked</tt> signal with a
      method that interpretes the result${<if:cpp>} and deletes the message
      box${</if:cpp>}.
      You can get the resulting standard button with <tt>buttonResult()</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      The buttons of a ${doc-link WMessageBox} may be standard or customized
      type of buttons. Customized buttons should be dealt with using
      the <tt>result()</tt> method from the parent <tt>WDialog</tt>.
      The strings used in standard buttons can be translated by overriding the
      default values of localization keys.
    </p>
<!--    <p>
      You can include an icon in a <tt>WMessageBox</tt>. You can choose from
      the following types:
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>Information</dt>
        <dd>An information icon</dd>
        <dt>Warning</dt>
        <dd>A warning icon</dd>
        <dt>Critical</dt>
        <dd>An critical icon</dd>
        <dt>Question</dt>
        <dd>An question icon</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>-->

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${MessageBox}
      ${src MessageBox}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      The following example is much more compact but it has a big disadvantage
      because the messagebox is instantiated synchronously. The <tt>show()</tt>
      method is used statically; this involves the static use of the
      <tt>exec()</tt> method which blocks the current thread until the user has
      clicked a button and the result of the messagebox is processed.
      It is highly recommended to use a messagebox asynchronously because there
      is no API call that waits for the messagebox to be processed in that
      case.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${MessageBoxSync}
      ${src MessageBoxSync}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      A <tt>WMessageBox</tt> can be styled using the <tt>Wt-dialog</tt> and
      <tt>Wt-outset</tt> style classes from it's superclass <tt>WDialog</tt>.
      Its buttons can be styled using the <tt>Wt-msgbox-buttons</tt> style
      class.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#dialogs">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="layout-Images">
    <h2 id="images">Images</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WImage} is a widget that displays an image. The image may be
      specified either as a URL, or may be dynamically generated by a
      <a href="#/media/resources">WResource</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can set an alternate text using the method
      <tt>setAlternateText()</tt>. The alternate text should provide a
      fallback for browsers that do not display an image, and are also
      important for accessibility. If no sensible fallback text can be
      provided, an empty text is preferred over nonsense.
    </p>
    <p>
      You may listen to events by attaching event listeners to signals such as
      <tt>clicked()</tt>. Since mouse events pass the coordinates through a
      A ${doc-link WMouseEvent} object, it is possible to react to clicks in
      specific parts of the image.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Image}
      ${src Image}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      Image also supports a more structural approach to listening for
      events depending on the image location. One can define
      interactive areas on the image using <tt>addArea()</tt>, which
      also allows to define a custom tool tip (using
      <tt>WAbstractArea::setToolTip()</tt>) or a different cursor
      image (using <tt>WAbstractArea::setCursor</tt>) for a certain
      image area.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ImageArea}
      ${src ImageArea}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      In contrast to the image, which displays typically a static
      image resource, Wt are also includes several options for
      dynamically <a href="#/graphics-charts">painted graphics</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <tt>WImage</tt> is an inline widget. The widget corresponds to the HTML
      <tt>&lt;img&gt;</tt> tag and doesn't provide styling. It can be styled
      using inline or external CSS as appropriate.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#images">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="layout-CSS">
    <h2 id="CSS">Styling (and Layout) with CSS</h2>
    <p>
      There are different techniques and technologies available to
      determine the size (width and height) of a rendered widget.
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>CSS</dt>
        <dd>The browser uses CSS (Cascading Style Sheets) as a
        technology for defining visual aspects, such as fonts, colors,
        border styles, but also for geometry.</dd>
        <dt>Layout Managers</dt>
        <dd>Whereas CSS (and browsers) were originally designed for
        the markup of documents, the requirements for web applications
        are in many ways different. <a
        href="#/layout/layout-managers">Layout Managers</a> are a
        common technique in desktop applications to layout a UI, and
        this is also available in Wt.</dd>
        <dt>CSS Grids</dt>
        <dd>A practical alternative to plain CSS, and to overcome some
        of its deficiencies which, are CSS frameworks which allow one
        to place widgets using a generic tag system. These typically
        divide the page in a virtual grid. When using Wt with the Bootstrap
        theme, such a CSS grid framework is included.</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

    <h3>Introduction to CSS</h3>
    <p>
      Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) group rules that specify both
      markup and layout properties of widgets. These rules are linked
      to certain widgets (or more correctly, DOM nodes in the browser
      that render these widgets) using selectors. Selectors may match
      widgets based on the style class or widget id of the widget or
      one of its ancestors, or even more advanced combinations.
    </p>

    <p>
      Primer + reference here.
    </p>

    <p>
      Three ways to use CSS in Wt.
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>Inline CSS</dt>
        <dd>A single widget's style properties can be modified directly using
        C++ API</dd>

        <dt>Internal StyleSheet</dt>
        <dd>The internal stylesheet allows to use a C++ API to create,
        modify and remove CSS style rules that typically impact
        multiple widgets.</dd>

        <dt>External StyleSheets</dt>
        <dd>By far the most practical approach is to use external CSS
        stylesheets that define styling rules, and apply them to Wt widgets
        using style classes.</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

    <h3>API for inline CSS style</h3>
    <p>
      A subset of CSS properties are available in the Wt API, and thus
      allow to influence the layout or visual appearance of a widget
      directly, from C++. This is useful if you want programmatic
      control over these properties; for other situations we recommend
      to use a n external CSS stylesheet.
    </p>

    <p>
      CSS properties that impact layout aspects are made available directly
      in the <tt>WWidget</tt> API, whereas decorative aspects are available
      from <tt>WWidget::cssDecorationStyle()</tt>, which returns a reference
      to a <tt>WCssDecorationStyle</tt> class.
    </p>

    <p>
      The following table gives an overview of properties that can be
      directly modified from C++.

      <table class="table table-bordered table-striped">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Class</th>
            <th>Property</th>
            <th>Description</th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setPositionScheme()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>position</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setOffsets()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>top, right, bottom, left</tt> properties.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>resize()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>width, height</tt> properties.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setMinimumSize()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>min-width, min-height</tt> properties.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setMaximumSize()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>max-width, max-height</tt> properties.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setLineHeight()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>line-height</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setFloatSide()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>float</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setClearSides()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>clear</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setMargin()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>margin</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setVerticalAlignment()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>vertical-align</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setInline(), setHidden()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>display</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WCssDecorationStyle}</td>
            <td><tt>setCursor()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>cursor</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WCssDecorationStyle}</td>
            <td><tt>setBackgroundColor(), setBackgroundImage()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>background</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WCssDecorationStyle}</td>
            <td><tt>setForegroundColor()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>color</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WCssDecorationStyle}</td>
            <td><tt>setBorder()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>border</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WCssDecorationStyle}</td>
            <td><tt>setFont()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>font</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WCssDecorationStyle}</td>
            <td><tt>setTextDecoration()</tt></td>
            <td>CSS <tt>text-decoration</tt> property.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </p>

    <h3>The Internal Style Sheet</h3>

    <p>
      The method <tt>WApplication::styleSheet()</tt> returns a
      reference to the embedded stylesheet (an instance of
      <tt>WCssStyleSheet</tt>), which can be manipulated dynamically
      to add, modify or removing rules. This is used primarily in some
      advanced composite widgets within Wt (such as <a
      href="#/trees-tables/mvc-table-views">WTableView</a>,
      <a href="#//trees-tables/mvc-tree-views">WTreeView</a>)
      since it allows to modify certain properties of a group of
      widgets using a minimum of DOM manipulations.
    </p>

    <h3>Using External Style Sheets</h3>

    <p>
      Widgets may allow configuration of their look and feel through style
      classes. These may be defined in an embedded stylesheet or in external
      style sheets. Preferably use external stylesheets because of the strict
      separation between style and widget. It provides the broadest application
      of style as it allows you to manage the presentational aspects of all
      widgets from a handful of style sheets.
    </p>

    <p>
      These are API classes and methods for working with CSS external
      stylesheets:
      <table class="table table-bordered table-striped">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Class</th>
            <th>Method</th>
            <th>Description</th>
         </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WApplication}</td>
            <td><tt>useStyleSheet()</tt></td>
            <td>Adds an external style sheet</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>setStyleClass()</tt></td>
            <td>Sets (one or more) CSS style classes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>styleClass()</tt></td>
            <td>Returns the CSS style class</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>addStyleClass()</tt></td>
            <td>Adds a CSS style class</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>removeStyleClass</tt></td>
            <td>Removes a CSS style class</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${doc-link WWidget}</td>
            <td><tt>toggleStyleClass</tt></td>
            <td>Toggles a CSS style class</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </p>

    <p>
      The following example shows how to refer to add an external style sheet
      to the application and how to add/remove classes to a widget like
      ${doc-link WTable}.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${CSS}
      ${src CSS}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding style sheet (CSSexample.css).
      </p>
      ${src CSSexample}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#CSS">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="layout-Themes">
    <h2 id="theme">Styling with a theme</h2>
    <p>
      A theme provides the look and feel of several built-in widgets, using CSS
      style rules. The rules for each CSS theme are defined in the folder
      <tt>resources/themes/</tt>. There each theme is organized in a subfolder.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can choose from three themes:
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>default</dt>
        <dd>You don't have to do anything to use this theme from the
          ${doc-link WCssTheme} class as it is the default theme.
        </dd>
        <dt>polished</dt>
        <dd>This theme is also implemented by the ${doc-link WCssTheme} class.
          You can change to this CSS theme with <tt>setCssTheme("polished")</tt>
          in your ${doc-link WApplication}.
        </dd>
        <dt>bootstrap</dt>
        <dd>
	  <p>
	    This theme is implemented by the ${doc-link WBootstrapTheme}
	    class, and relies on <a
	    href="http://getbootstrap.com/">Twitter's Bootstrap CSS
	    framework</a>. Use <tt>setTheme(new WBootstrapTheme())</tt>
	    to use this theme.
	  </p>
	  <p>
	    As of version 3.3.2, Bootstrap 2 and Bootstrap 3 versions
	    are supported. The widget gallery has been restyled to use
	    Bootstrap 3. While the theme makes sure that Wt's widgets
	    are rendered with the markup expected by bootstrap, there
	    are many features that are particular to the layout system
	    of bootstrap (and chaned from version 2 to version
	    3). Thus you need to know how bootstrap expects you to
	    layout widgets in order to effectivily use this theme, for
	    which we refer to the <a
	    href="http://getbootstrap.com/">Bootstrap
	    documentation</a>.
	  </p>
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${src theme}
    </fieldset>

    <h3>Remark</h3>
    <p>
      Setting an empty theme (with parameter "") will result in a stub CSS theme
      that does not load any stylesheets.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#theme">Top</a></p>

  </message>

<!--FORMS message blocks-->

  <message id="formwidgets-intro">
    <p class="lead">Forms &#8212; widgets and support classes for capturing user information</p>
  </message>

  <message id="forms-introduction">
    <h2 id="forms">Introduction</h2>
    <p>
      There are two ways in which you can compose a form:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="#form-simple">using a simple form</a></li>
        <li><a href="#form-model">using a Model-View concept</a></li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <h3 id="form-simple">Simple form</h3>
    <p>
      You can create a simple form by using one or more input widgets like
      ${doc-link WLineEdit} in addition to a ${doc-link WPushButton} to
      process the input.
      You can add <tt>Validation</tt> to filter the user's input (See also the
      menu <a href="#/forms/validation">Validation</a>).
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${SimpleForm}
      ${src SimpleForm}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding XML template (with
        <tt>message id="simpleForm-template"</tt>) using style classes from the
        <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/base-css.html"
        target="blank">Bootstrap theme</a>.
        In order to apply validation style to any widget with invalid input,
        you should group the widgets in a div or span section and apply the
        style <tt>form-group </tt> to it.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
        <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${simpleForm-template}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#forms">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="form-model">Model/view concept</h3>
    <p>
      It is more convenient to create a form using a model/view concept. The
      model is a specialisation of ${doc-link WFormModel} while the
      complementary template-based view class is a specialisation of
      ${doc-link WTemplateFormView}. The main advantage is that forms based on
      this concept are structured in a uniform way.
    </p>
    <p>
      The form model implements field data and validation handling for (simple)
      form-based views. It provides a standard way for views to perform field
      validation, and react to validation results.
      Each field has a string literal assigned to it. The string literal
      uniquely identifies the field. For each field, its value, the visibility,
      whether the field is read-only, and its current validation status is
      managed by the model.
      In addition, you will typically specialize the class to customize the
      validation and application logic. Although it can be setup to use <tt>
      WValidator</tt> objects for individual fields, you could also create a
      validator to simultaneously validate interdependent fields.
    </p>
    <p>
      A model is typically used by a view (<tt>WTemplateFormView</tt>) which
      renders the fields configured in the model, updates the model values,
      invokes and reflects the validation status. For each model field, the
      view uses a number of conventional variable names to represent the
      label, editor, and validation messages in the template:
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>field</dt>
        <dd>
          This variable name refers to the <strong>form widget</strong> which
          contains the value. It is used by <tt>createFormWidget()</tt> at the
          moment that the form is created.
        </dd>
        <dt>field-label</dt>
        <dd>
          This variable name refers to the <strong>label</strong>. It is used
          by <tt>label()</tt>.
        </dd>
        <dt>field-info</dt>
        <dd>
          This variable name refers to <strong>details</strong> on the field. This
          could be input advice (e.g. the format or the range) or a validation
          message. It is used by <tt>addField()</tt> and <tt>validate()</tt>.
        </dd>
        <dt>if:field</dt>
        <dd>
          This variable name refers to a condition for the
          <strong>visibility</strong> of the field. It is used by
          <tt>isVisible()</tt>.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </p>
    <p>
      For a field with the name 'field', a typical template contains a block in
      the following format:
      <fieldset class="src">
        <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${form-field}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </p>
    <p>
      The view can update the form using several methods. The <tt>updateView()
      </tt> method updates the view based on a model (e.g. to propagate changed
      values or validation), while the <tt>updateModel()</tt> method updates a
      model with values entered in the view.
      The view doesn't have to render all fields of a model. You can call
      <tt>updateViewField()</tt> and <tt>updateModelField()</tt> to update
      individual model fields.
    </p>
    <p>
      The view is passive. It will not perform any updates by itself if either
      the view or model has changed. To update the form, each view method uses
      a service method from the model; either <tt>setValue()</tt> to update the
      model or <tt>value()</tt> to update the view. You will typically bind a
      method to a button in order to process the form (i.e. update and validate
      the model).
    </p>
    <p>
      <img src="/pics/model-view.png" alt="model-view picture"></img>
    </p>
    <p>
      The view may render fields of more than one model. Note that there are
      still other models like ${doc-link WStandardItemModel} which can be used
      to represent tables, trees and tree tables.
    </p>
    <p>
      The form below is composed of input fields which are implemented with
      different controls like a line edit, a combo box, a date picker, a spin
      box, a text area. The push button at the end is used to start the
      validation of the values in the input fields.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${FormModel}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      This menu continues with controls (widgets) which you can use to assemble
      a form. At the end the above form is explained in detail with the source
      code.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#forms">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="simpleForm-template">
    <div class="form-inline">
      <div class="form-group">
          ${name}
      </div>
      <div class="form-group">
          ${button}
      </div>
      <div class="form-group">
           ${out}
      </div>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="form-field">
    <div class="form-group">
      <label class="control-label col-sm-2" for="${id:{2}}"> ${1} </label>
      <div class="col-sm-5"> ${2} </div>
      <div class="help-block col-sm-5"> ${3} </div>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="userForm-template">
    <legend>${title}</legend>
    <div class="form-horizontal">
      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-2"  for="${id:first-name}">
          First name
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-5">
          ${first-name}
        </div>
        <div class="help-block col-sm-5">
          ${first-name-info}
        </div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-2"  for="${id:first-name}">
          Last name
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-5">
          ${last-name}
        </div>
        <div class="help-block col-sm-5">
          ${last-name-info}
        </div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-2"  for="${id:first-name}">
          Country
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-5">
          ${country}
        </div>
        <div class="help-block col-sm-5">
          ${country-info}
        </div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-2"  for="${id:first-name}">
          City
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-5">
          ${city}
        </div>
        <div class="help-block col-sm-5">
          ${city-info}
        </div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-2"  for="${id:first-name}">
          Birth date
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-5">
          ${birth}
        </div>
        <div class="help-block col-sm-5">
          ${birth-info}
        </div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-2"  for="${id:first-name}">
          Children
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-5">
          ${children}
        </div>
        <div class="help-block col-sm-5">
          ${children-info}
        </div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-2"  for="${id:first-name}">
          Remarks
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-5">
          ${remarks}
        </div>
        <div class="help-block col-sm-5">
          ${remarks-info}
        </div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <div class="col-sm-offset-2 col-sm-10">
          ${submit-button} <span class="help-inline">${submit-info}</span>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="form-field">
    ${<if:field>}
      <label class="control-label col-sm-2"  for="${id:field}">${field-label}</label>
      ${field} ${field-info}
    ${</if:field>}
  </message>

  <message id="forms-textEditors">
    <h2 id="text-editors">Text editors</h2>
    <p>
      Wt provides different kinds of text entry widgets:
      <a href="#line-edit"><tt>WLineEdit</tt></a>,
      <a href="#text-area"><tt>WTextArea</tt></a>,
      <a href="#text-edit"><tt>WTextEdit</tt></a> and
      <a href="#spin-box"><tt>WSpinBox</tt></a>.
    </p>

    <h3 id="line-edit">Line edit</h3>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WLineEdit} class is an inline widget that provides a
      single line edit.
    </p>
    <p>
      A <tt>&lt;WLineEdit&gt;</tt> corresponds to an HTML
      <tt>&lt;input type="text"&gt;</tt> element.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can restrict its input using a validator providing immediate
      client-side feedback. In the example below characters that aren't
      numbers are not accepted. If you enter a number out of the
      predefined range (0..130) then the widget colour is changed.
      See <a href="#/forms/validation">Forms > Validation</a> for more details.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${LineEdit}
      ${src LineEdit}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding XML template (with
        <tt>message id="lineEdit-template"</tt>) using style classes from the
        <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/base-css.html"
        target="blank">Bootstrap theme</a>.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
      <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${lineEdit-template}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      The line edit below reacts on every 'key pressed' event. It also shows
      how you can embed the label within the control (when empty).
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${LineEditEvent}
      ${src LineEditEvent}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#text-editors">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="text-area">Text area</h3>
    <p>
      ${doc-link WTextArea} is an inline widget that provides a multi-line edit.
    </p>
    <p>
      A <tt>WTextArea</tt> corresponds to an HTML <tt>&lt;textarea&gt;</tt> element.
    </p>
    <p>
      Form validators can be used to validate the user's input with immediate
      client-side feedback.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${TextArea}
      ${src TextArea}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#text-editors">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="text-edit">Text edit</h3>
    <p>
      ${doc-link WTextEdit} is a full-featured editor for rich text editing. It
      is based on the TinyMCE editor, which must be downloaded separately from
      its author's website. The TinyMCE toolbar layout and plugins can be
      configured through Wt's interface. The default layout - as shown below -
      covers only a small portion of TinyMCE's capabilities.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      <div class="text-edit-example">
        ${TextEdit}
      </div>
      ${src TextEdit}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      You could also render the XHTML text to pdf using the
      ${doc-link Render-WPdfRenderer} class.
      See <a href="#/media/pdf-output">Media > Pdf output</a> for more details.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#text-editors">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="spin-box">Spin box</h3>
    <p>
      A spin box is an inline widget to enter a number; ${doc-link WSpinBox} is
      an input control for integer numbers, while ${doc-link WDoubleSpinBox} is
      an input control for fixed point numbers. A spin box consists of a line
      edit, and buttons which allow to increase or decrease the value.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${SpinBox}
      ${src SpinBox}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#text-editors">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="spin-box">Input masks</h3>
    <p>
      A user may be steered to providing correct input by providing an
      input mask. The input mask indicates the expected format and
      constrains the user to provide data only in the expected format.
    </p>
    <p>
      In the example below we use an input mask to ask the user to
      enter an IP address.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${InputMask}
      ${src InputMask}
    </fieldset>

    <h3 id="edit-options">Prepended and appended inputs</h3>
    <p>
      Adding on top of the standard input controls, the
      <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/base-css.html"
      target="blank">Bootstrap theme</a> includes other useful form components
      like prepended/appended inputs. You can add text or buttons before and/or
      after any text-based input using the <tt>.input-prepend</tt> and
      <tt>.input-prepend</tt> classes respectively. Note that select elements
      are not supported.
    </p>

    <h4>Adding text</h4>
    <p>
      Wrap an <tt>.add-on</tt> and an input control with one of two classes to
      prepend or append text to an input. You could also use both classes and
      two instances of <tt>.add-on</tt> to prepend and append an input at once.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${TextSide}
      ${src TextSide}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding XML template (with
        <tt>message id="editSide-template"</tt>) using style classes from
        the <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/base-css.html"
        target="blank">Bootstrap theme</a>.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
      <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${editSide-template}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <h4>Adding drop down buttons</h4>

    <p>
      See <a href="#/forms/push-button#dropdown">Push buttons</a>.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#text-editors">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="dateEdit-template">
    <p>When do you want to take your holiday?</p>

    <div class="form-horizontal">
      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-3" for="${id:from}">From</label>
        <div class="col-sm-4">${from}</div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-3" for="${id:to}">
          To (format dd MM yyyy)
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-4">${to}</div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <div class="col-sm-offset-3 col-sm-4">
          ${save}
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>

    ${out class="help-block"}

  </message>
  
  <message id="timeEdit-template">
    <p>When do you want your package to be delivered?</p>

    <div class="form-horizontal">
      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-3" for="${id:from}">From (format ${from-format})</label>
        <div class="col-sm-4">${from}</div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-3" for="${id:to}">
          To (format ${to-format})
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-4">${to}</div>
      </div>

      <div class="form-group">
        <div class="col-sm-offset-3 col-sm-4">
          ${save}
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>

    ${out class="help-block"}

  </message>

  <message id="lineEdit-template">
    <div class="form-inline">
      <div class="form-group">
        <label for="${id:edit}">${label}</label>
        ${edit}
      </div>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="editSide-template">
    <div class="form-group">
      <div class="input-group">
        <span class="input-group-addon">@</span>
        ${name}
      </div>
    </div>      
    <div class="form-group">
      <div class="input-group">
        ${amount1}
        <span class="input-group-addon">.00</span>
      </div>
    </div>      
    <div class="form-group">
      <div class="input-group">
        <span class="input-group-addon">$</span>
        ${amount2}
        <span class="input-group-addon">.00</span>
        </div>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="forms-checkBox">
    <h2 id="check-boxes">Check boxes</h2>
    <p>
      Wt provides different kinds of button widgets. The ${doc-link WCheckBox}
      class provides independent on/off options in contrast to
      ${doc-link WRadioButton}s which are usually mutually exclusive.
    </p>
    <p>
      An instance of <tt>WCheckBox</tt> corresponds to an HTML
      <tt>&lt;input type="checkbox"&gt;</tt> element.
    </p>
    <p>
      Next to being checked or unchecked, a checkbox can be configured
      to allow a third state, <tt>Wt::PartiallyChecked</tt>, which can
      be used to indicate that it isn't <i>entirely</i> checked,
      e.g. if only some of the files in a folder are selected, then
      the checkbox for that folder would be partially checked. In the
      example below, the third checkbox demonstrates this tristate
      behaviour.
    </p>

    <h3>Inline check boxes</h3>
    <p>
      By default, check boxes will appear on the same line.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${CheckBoxInline}
      ${src CheckBoxInline}
    </fieldset>

    <h3>Stacked check boxes</h3>
    <p>
      Since by default, check boxes are inline, you will need to use
      <tt>setInline(false)</tt> to let them stack vertically.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${CheckBoxStack}
      ${src CheckBoxStack}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#check-boxes">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="forms-radioButton">
    <h2 id="radio-buttons">Radio buttons</h2>
    <p>
      Wt provides different kinds of button widgets. The
      ${doc-link WRadioButton} class provides options which are usually
      mutually exclusive in contrast to ${doc-link WCheckBox}s which provide
      independent on/off options.
    </p>
    <p>
      An instance of <tt>WRadioButton</tt> corresponds to an HTML
      <tt>&lt;input type="radio"&gt;</tt> element.
    </p>
    <p>
      Use a <a href="#radio-group">WButtonGroup</a> to group together radio
      buttons that reflect options that are mutually exclusive.
      With <a href="#radio-events">event handling</a> you can follow up any
      change in the selection.
    </p>
    <p>
      By default, radio buttons are inline. You will need to use
      <tt>setInline(false)</tt> to let them stack vertically.
    </p>

    <h3 id="radio-loose">Loose buttons</h3>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${RadioButtonsLoose}
      ${src RadioButtonsLoose}
    </fieldset>

    <h3 id="radio-group">Button group</h3>
    <p>
      Usually, you'll group a set of radio buttons together in a
      ${doc-link WButtonGroup}, so that only one can be selected at a time.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${RadioButtonGroup}
      ${src RadioButtonGroup}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#radio-buttons">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="radio-stack">Stacked buttons</h3>
    <p>
      Since by default, radio buttons are inline, you will need to use
      <tt>setInline(false)</tt> to let them stack vertically.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${RadioButtonStack}
      ${src RadioButtonStack}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#radio-buttons">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="radio-events">Events</h3>
    <p>
      You can process a new selection with a signal/slot mechanism. In the
      example below the signal <tt>checkedChanged()</tt> of the
      <tt>WButtonGroup</tt> is passed to an inner function passing a
      ${doc-link WPushButton}.
      You can see that there are two ways to get the id assigned to a button,
      namely <tt>group->id(selection)</tt> and <tt>group->checkedId()</tt>.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${RadioButtonsActivated}
      ${src RadioButtonsActivated}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      <a href="#/events" target="blank">More details on events</a>
    </p>

    <p><a href="#radio-buttons">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="forms-comboBox">
    <h2 id="combo-boxes">Combo box</h2>
    <p>
      A combo box is a drop-down list allowing you to choose one option from a
      list of options.
    </p>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WComboBox} corresponds to an HTML <tt>&lt;select&gt;</tt>
      element.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ComboBox}
      ${src ComboBox}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      <tt>WComboBox</tt> is a View widget (see also
      <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/mvc-widgets/" target="_blank">
      Model-View-Controller</a>) which instantiates its own
      <tt>WStringListModel</tt> by default. You can use this widget also in
      conjunction with another model.
    </p>

    <h3>Events</h3>
    <p>
      You can capture the selected item and deal with it using a signal/slot
      mechanism.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ComboBoxActivated}
      ${src ComboBoxActivated}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#combo-boxes">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="model">Model</h3>
    <p>
      WComboBox is a MVC class (model-view-controller). By default a
      ${doc-link WStringListModel} is used. With this model you can associate a
      single column of data to the displayed items. The member methods
      <tt>addItem()</tt>, <tt>insertItem()</tt> and <tt>removeItem()</tt>
      manipulate the model. You can set the model with <tt>setModel()</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Item models support different roles like
      <tt>Wt::ItemDataRole::DisplayRole </tt> and
      <tt>Wt::ItemDataRole::UserRole</tt>. The text for an item in the
      drop-down box is associated with a
      <tt>Wt::ItemDataRole::DisplayRole</tt>. Typically, you will associate the
      underlying "value" with a <tt>Wt::ItemDataRole::UserRole</tt>). In this
      way, you can also add additional user roles.
    </p>
    <p>
      Note that there are still other models like ${doc-link WFormModel} which
      and can be used to represent fields in a form.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ComboBoxModel}
      ${src ComboBoxModel}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#combo-boxes">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="forms-selectionBox">
    <h2 id="selection-boxes">Selection box</h2>
    <p>
      A selection box shows an immediately visible list allowing you to choose
      one (by default) or <a href="#selection-multiple">more</a> options.
    </p>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WSelectionBox} corresponds to an HTML <tt>&lt;select&gt;</tt>
      element.
    </p>
    <p>
      <tt>WSelectionBox</tt> is a View widget (see also
      <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/mvc-widgets/" target="_blank">
      Model-View-Controller</a>). By default a ${doc-link
      WStringListModel} is used. With this model you can associate a
      single column of data to the displayed items. The member
      methods <tt>addItem()</tt>, <tt>insertItem()</tt> and <tt>
      removeItem()</tt> manipulate the model. You can set the model
      with <tt>setModel()</tt>. See the Combo box section for an <a
      href="#/forms/combo-boxes">example</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      A model supports different roles like
      <tt>Wt::ItemDataRole::DisplayRole </tt> and
      <tt>Wt::ItemDataRole::UserRole</tt>.  The suggestion text for an
      item in the drop-down box is associated with a
      <tt>Wt::ItemDataRole::DisplayRole</tt>. The value, which will be
      inserted in the line-edit, corresponding with a suggestion, is
      stored as <tt> Wt::ItemDataRole::UserRole</tt>) data. If no
      UserRole data is available, the behaviour defaults to inserting
      the suggestion text iteself.
    </p>
    <p>
      If you want to associate multiple data columns with an item from the
      combo box then you should assign another model to this control like
      ${doc-link WStandardItemModel} or an implemention of
      ${doc-link WAbstractTableModel}.
    </p>
    <p>
      Note that there are still other models like ${doc-link WFormModel} which
      and can be used to represent fields in a form.
    </p>

    <h3>Single option selection box</h3>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${SelectionBoxSimple}
      ${src SelectionBoxSimple}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#selection-boxes">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="selection-multiple">Multiple option selection box</h3>
    <p>Use shift and/or ctrl-click to select your pizza toppings...</p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${SelectionBoxExtended}
      ${src SelectionBoxExtended}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#selection-boxes">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="forms-autoComplete">
    <h2 id="auto-complete">Auto complete</h2>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WSuggestionPopup} class is a widget which pops up to
      assist in editing a text area or line edit through auto completion.
      This widget may be associated with one or more ${doc-link WFormWidgets}
      (typically a ${doc-link WLineEdit} or a ${doc-link WTextArea}).    </p>
    <p>
      The popup provides the user with suggestions to enter input. The popup
      can be used by one or more text editors, using <tt>forEdit()</tt>. The
      popup will show when the user starts editing the edit field, or when the
      user opens the suggestions explicitly using a drop down icon or with the
      down key. In the example below, the popup positions itself on top of the
      edit field.
    </p>
    <p>
      The class is initialized with an <tt>Options</tt> struct which configures
      how suggestion filtering and result editing is done. Alternatively, you
      can provide two <a href="#auto-complete-javascript">JavaScript functions
      </a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      To style the suggestions, you should style the &lt;span&gt; element
      inside this widget, and the &lt;span&gt;."sel" element to style the
      current selection.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can also limit the maximum height of the popup by using <tt>
      setMaximumSize()</tt>. In this case, scrolling is supported (similar to a
      combo-box).
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${AutoComplete}
        ${src AutoComplete}
    </fieldset>

    <h3>Model</h3>
    <p>
      WSuggestionPopup is a MVC class (model-view-controller). By
      default a ${doc-link WStringListModel} is used. The member
      methods <tt>clearSuggestions()</tt> and <tt>addSuggestion()</tt>
      manipulate this model. You can set another model with
      <tt>setModel()</tt>. See the Combo box section for an <a
      href="#/forms/combo-boxes">example</a>.
    </p>

    <h3>Server-side filtering</h3>
    <p>
      By default, the popup implements all filtering client-side. To support
      large datasets, you may enable server-side filtering of suggestions based
      on the input. The server-side filtering may provide a coarse filtering
      using a fixed size prefix of the entered text, and complement the
      client-side filtering. To enable server-side filtering, use <tt>
      setFilterLength()</tt> and listen to filter notification using the <tt>
      modelFilter()</tt> signal. Whenever a filter event is generated you can
      adjust the model's content according to the filter (e.g. using a
      ${doc-link WSortFilterProxyModel}).
    </p>

    <h3 id="auto-complete-javascript">Initializing Options with JavaScript
      functions</h3>
    <p>
      Usually, the popup class is initialized with an <tt>Options</tt> struct
      which configures how suggestion filtering and result editing is done.
      Alternatively, you can provide two JavaScript functions, one for
      filtering the suggestions (<tt>generateMatcherJS()</tt>), and one for
      editing the value of the textarea when a suggestion is selected (<tt>
      generateReplacerJS()</tt>).
      The matcher function must have the following JavaScript signature:
      ${src matcher}
    </p>
    <p>
      The replacerJS function that edits the value has the following JavaScript
      signature.
      ${src replacer}
    </p>

    <h3>Remark</h3>
    <p>
      You can find several more advanced examples in the Wt distribution
      directory <tt>examples/feature/suggestionpopup/</tt>. In the <tt>
      SuggestionPopup.C</tt> class you can explore different functions.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#auto-complete">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="forms-dateEntry">
    <h2 id="date-entry">Date entry</h2>
    <p>
      Wt provides to kinds of widgets to enter a date, namely
      <a href="#date-calendar">WCalendar</a> and <a href="#date-picker">
      WDatePicker</a>.
    </p>

    <h3 id="date-calendar">Date entry using a calendar</h3>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WCalendar} widget provides navigation by month and year,
      and indicates the current day.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${CalendarSimple}
        ${src CalendarSimple}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      You can select multiple dates after passing the flag <tt>
      ExtendedSelection</tt> to the method <tt>setSelectionMode()</tt>.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${CalendarExtended}
        ${src CalendarExtended}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#date-entry">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="date-picker">Date entry using a date edit</h3>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WDateEdit} widget is a line edit with support for
      date entry, using a <tt>WCalendar</tt> in a popup for editing
      the date. In the future, it is foreseen that this widget can evolve to
      use browser support for easy date entry.
    </p>
    <p>
      By default the selected date is shown in the format "dd/MM/yyyy" as in
      the first example. In the second example the format is set to
      "dd MM yyyy".
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${DateEdit}
        ${src DateEdit}
    </fieldset>
    <p><a href="#date-entry">Top</a></p>
    
    <h3 id="time-picker">Time entry using a time edit</h3>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WTimeEdit} widget is a line edit with support for
      time entry.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${TimeEdit}
        ${src TimeEdit}
    </fieldset>
    <p><a href="#date-entry">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="date-edit">Date entry using a date picker</h3>
    <p>
      The date picker offers about the same functionality as the newer
      <tt>WDateEdit</tt>, but with a slightly different API. Most
      importantly, the date editor is a form widget, and integrates
      better with other parts in Wt. It is in general more convenient
      to use the newer WDateEdit class instead.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${DatePicker}
        ${src DatePicker}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#date-entry">Top</a></p>
  </message>

  <message id="forms-inPlaceEdit">
    <h2 id="in-place-edit">In place edit</h2>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WInPlaceEdit} widget provides in-place-editable text. The
      text that may be edited in place by clicking on it.
    </p>

    <h3>In place edit with buttons</h3>
    <p>
      By default, the Save and Cancel buttons are shown. To prevent losing the
      widget, always use <tt>setEmptyText()</tt> in addition to <tt>setText()
      </tt> or initially setting the text by the constructor.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${InPlaceEditButtons}
        ${src InPlaceEditButtons}
    </fieldset>

    <h3>In place edit without buttons</h3>
    <p>
      To show the line edit only, call <tt>setButtonsEnabled()</tt> with
      parameter <tt>enabled</tt> set to false; this hides the buttons. In this
      mode, any event that causes focus to be lost saves the value while the
      escape key cancels the editing.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${InPlaceEdit}
        ${src InPlaceEdit}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#in-place-edit">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="forms-slider">
    <h2 id="slider">Slider</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WSlider} is a horizontal or vertical linear control with
      which you can set an integer value by moving an indicator within a
      particular range. You can also click on a point on the slider to change
      the value.
    </p>
    <p>
      The default size is 150 x 50 pixels for a horizontal slider, and 50 x 150
      pixels for a vertical slider. The slider size cannot be set explicitly by
      a CSS style sheet. You should use <tt>resize()</tt> or a layout manager
      for that purpose.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${Slider}
        ${src Slider}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#slider">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Vertical slider</h3>
    <p>
      You can create a vertical slider using <tt>setOrientation()</tt> with the
      parameter <tt>orientation</tt> set to Vertical on a default horizontal
      slider like in the above example or using a more specialized constructor.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${SliderVertical}
        ${src SliderVertical}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#slider">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="forms-progressBar">
    <h2 id="progress-bar">Progress bar</h2>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WProgressBar} can be used to indicate the progress of a
      certain operation. The text displayed in the progress bar can be
      customized by specializing <tt>text()</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      To use the progress bar widget, you need to give it a range (either by
      <tt>setRange()</tt> or by using <tt>setMinimum()</tt> and
      <tt>setMaximum()</tt>), and update the progress using <tt>setValue()</tt>.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${ProgressBar}
        ${src ProgressBar}
    </fieldset>

    <h3>Remark</h3>
    <p>
      With the advent of HTML5, this widget will be implemented using the
      native HTML5 control when available.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#progress-bar">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="forms-fileUpload">
    <h2 id="file-upload">File upload</h2>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WFileUpload} widget allows you to upload a local file to
      the server.
    </p>

    <h3>Signals</h3>
    <p>
      To properly use this widget you need to handle the <tt>uploaded()</tt>
      or <tt>fileTooLarge()</tt> signals; even when <tt>upload()</tt> was not
      called.
    </p>
    <p>
      An oversized file will result in a <tt>fileTooLarge()</tt> signal. The
      default threshold value (128) for this signal is defined in the general
      application settings file <tt>wt_config.xml</tt> by the parameter <tt>
      max-request-size</tt> (Kb). See the <a href=
      "http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/overview.html#config_general"
      target="blank">Library overview</a> for more details.
    </p>
    <p>
      Also check using <tt>canUpload()</tt> if <tt>upload()</tt> will schedule
      a new upload.
      <ul>
        <li>
          If (!canUpload()) then <tt>upload()</tt> will not have any effect.
        </li>
        <li>
          If (canUpload()), then <tt>upload()</tt> will start a new file
          upload.
          <br />
          If the upload completes succesfully then an <tt>uploaded()
          </tt>signal will be emitted. Otherwise a <tt>fileTooLarge()</tt>
          signal will be emitted.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${FileUpload}
        ${src FileUpload}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#file-upload">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="forms-pushButton">
    <h2 id="push-button">Push buttons</h2>
    <p>
      Wt provides different kinds of button widgets. With a
      ${doc-link WPushButton} a user can execute a command by a click action,
      e.g. an OK button is generally used for confirming actions and closing
      the window while a Cancel button is used for canceling actions and
      closing the window.
    </p>
    <p>
      A <tt>WPushButton</tt> corresponds to an HTML <tt>&lt;button&gt;</tt>
      element.
    </p>
    <p>
      A push button typically responds to <tt>clicked()</tt> events.
    </p>
    <p>
      You may decorate a push button with a background image to create a
      clickable image. As a descendant of class ${doc-link WFormWidget}, push
      buttons can be disabled or enabled.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PushButton}
      ${src PushButton}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#push-button">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="one-time">One-time hit button</h3>
    <p>
      A push button can be designated to be pushed only once and as a result
      execute a command only once.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PushButtonOnce}
      ${src PushButtonOnce}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#push-button">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="navigation">Navigation button</h3>
    <p>
      You can also associate navigation with a button using
      <tt>WPushButton::setLink()</tt>. With this method you can change the
      internal path of the application. As a result the button behaves as an
      <a href="#/navigation/anchor">anchor</a>. This is similar to how a
      ${doc-link WMenuWidget} or a ${doc-link WTabWidget} works. See the menu
      <a href="#/navigation">Navigation</a> for more details.
    </p>
    <p>
      With a push button you can execute an action while navigating to a
      hyperlink target at the same time using <tt>WPushButton::setLink()</tt>.
      This method accepts a ${doc-link WLink} as parameter.
    </p>
    <p>
      In the example below, the internal path is changed from
      <tt>/forms/button</tt> (the path associated with the current web page) to
      <tt>/navigation/anchor</tt>.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PushButtonLink}
      ${src PushButtonLink}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#push-button">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="dropdown">Drop down button</h3>
    <p>
      A drop down button is a button with a drop down menu. It could be used to
      extend a line edit with possible actions on the input. Usually the menu
      items are links.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PushButtonDropdownAppended}
      ${src PushButtonDropdownAppended}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding XML template (with
        <tt>message id= "appendedDropdownButton-template"</tt>) using style
        classes from the
        <a href= "http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/base-css.html"
        target="blank">Bootstrap theme</a>.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
        <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${appendedDropdownButton-template}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#push-button">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="style">Button style</h3>
    <p>
      You can add different styles to buttons to change the color, the size,
      the positioning, etc. using style classes from the
      <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/base-css.html"
      target="blank">Bootstrap theme</a>.
      Button styles can be applied to anything with the <tt>.btn</tt> class
      applied. However, for the best rendering, apply these to hyperlinks
      (<tt>&lt;a&gt;</tt>) and button controls (<tt>&lt;button&gt;</tt>) only.
    </p>

    <h4 id="color">Button color</h4>
    <p>
      The following table provides an overview of the standard color classes
      and visualizes the effect on a button. The <tt>.btn</tt> class is applied
      to a button control by default; you only have to set additional classes.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PushButtonColor}
      <p>
        Here is the underlying program showing how to assign the appropriate
        color style class to a button.
      </p>
      ${src PushButtonColor}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding XML template
        (with <tt>message id="pushButtonColor-template"</tt>). Note that there
        is no style applied to the buttons here; this is dealt with in the
        program. As a result it's easy to change the style on-the-fly.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
        <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${pushButtonColor-template}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#push-button">Top</a></p>

    <h4 id="size">Button size</h4>
    <p>
      Instead of using the default size, you can apply a larger or smaller size
      to a button. Add the style class <tt>.btn-large</tt>,
      <tt>.btn-small</tt>,or <tt>.btn-mini</tt> to change the size.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PushButtonSize}
      <p>
        Here is the underlying program showing how to assign the appropriate
        size style class to a button.
      </p>
      ${src PushButtonSize}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding XML template
        (with <tt>message id="pushButtonSize-template"</tt>). Note that there
        is no style applied to the buttons here; this is dealt with in the
        program.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
        <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${pushButtonSize-template}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#push-button">Top</a></p>

    <h4 id="primary">Primary button</h4>
    <p>
      You can create a primary button - one that is more striking - by adding
      the <tt>.btn-primary</tt> style to it.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PushButtonPrimary}
      ${src PushButtonPrimary}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#push-buttonn">Top</a></p>

    <h4 id="action">Buttons in a form</h4>
    <p>
      Usually, a form ends with a group of actions (buttons). You can make the
      action section more striking compared to the upper input field section by
      adding the style class <tt>.form-actions</tt>. When placed within a
      <tt>.form-horizontal</tt>, the buttons will automatically indent to line
      up with the form controls (See the example at
      <a href="#/forms/forms">Forms &gt; Form model</a>).
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PushButtonAction}
      ${src PushButtonAction}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding XML template
        (with <tt>message id="pushButtonAction-template"</tt>) showing how to
        assign the appropriate style class to the action section.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
        <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${pushButtonAction-template}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#push-button">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="appendedDropdownButton-template">
  <div class="form-inline">
    <div class="form-group">
      ${input}
    </div>
    <div class="form-group">
        ${appendedButton}
    </div>
  </div>
  </message>

  <message id="pushButtonColor-template">
      <table class="table table-bordered table-striped">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Button</th>
            <th>Class</th>
            <th>Description</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>${button-default}</td>
            <td><tt></tt></td>
            <td>Default style configured by the library (gray, with gradient)</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${button-primary}</td>
            <td><tt>btn-primary</tt></td>
            <td>Provides extra visual weight and identifies the primary action
                in a set of buttons</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${button-info}</td>
            <td><tt>btn-info</tt></td>
            <td>Used as an alternative to the default styles</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${button-success}</td>
            <td><tt>btn-success</tt></td>
            <td>Indicates a successful or positive action</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${button-warning}</td>
            <td><tt>btn-warning</tt></td>
            <td>Indicates caution should be taken with this action</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${button-danger}</td>
            <td><tt>btn-danger</tt></td>
            <td>Indicates a dangerous or potentially negative action</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${button-inverse}</td>
            <td><tt>btn-inverse</tt></td>
            <td>Alternate dark gray button, not tied to a semantic action or
                use</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>${button-link}</td>
            <td><tt>btn-link</tt></td>
            <td>Deemphasize a button by making it look like a link while
                maintaining button behavior</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
  </message>

  <message id="pushButtonSize-template">
    <div>
      ${button-large}
      <p>${button-default}</p>
      <p>${button-small}</p>
      ${button-mini}
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="pushButtonAction-template">
    <div class="form-actions">
      ${button-save} ${button-cancel}
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="forms-validation">
    <h2 id="validation">Validation</h2>
    <p>
      A validator is used to validate user input according to pre-defined rules.
    </p>
    <p>
      A validator may have a split implementation to provide both validation at
      the client-side (which gives instant feed-back to the user while
      editing), and server-side validation (to be sure that the client was not
      tampered with). The feed-back given by (client-side and server-side)
      validation is reflected in the style class of the form field: a style
      class of <tt>Wt-invalid</tt> is set for a field that is invalid.
    </p>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WValidator} only checks that mandatory fields are not
      empty. Validated input can have one of the following states:
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Valid</strong>, if the input data is valid.</li>
        <li><strong>Invalid</strong>, if the input data is invalid.</li>
        <li><strong>InvalidEmpty</strong>, if the input field is empty while it
            is configured as mandatory.</li>
      </ul>
      This class is reimplemented in ${doc-link WDateValidator},
      ${doc-link WIntValidator}, ${doc-link WDoubleValidator},
      ${doc-link WLengthValidator} and ${doc-link WRegExpValidator}. All these
      validators provide both client-side and server-side validation.
    </p>
    <p>
      If these validators are not suitable, you can inherit from this class,
      and provide a suitable implementation to <tt>validate()</tt> which does
      the server-side validation. If you want to provide client-side validation
      for your own validator, you may also reimplement <tt>javaScriptValidate()
      </tt>.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Validation}
      ${src Validation}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding XML template (with
        <tt>message id= "validation-template"</tt>) using style classes from
        the <a href= "http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/base-css.html"
        target="blank">Bootstrap theme</a>.
        In order to apply validation style if the input is not valid, you
        should surround the input widget in a div or span section and apply the
        style <tt>form-group </tt> to it.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
        <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${validation-template}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#validation">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Date validation</h3>
    <p>
      In entirely the same way, a date validator can be used to
      validate date input with a <tt>WDateEdit</tt> or
      <tt>WDatePicker</tt>. You can limit the date range of the
      calendar using <tt> setBottom()</tt> and <tt>setTop()</tt>.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
        <legend>Example</legend>
        ${ValidationDate}
        ${src ValidationDate}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#validation">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Server-side validation using a form model</h3>
    <p>
      A more convenient way to perform validation is to implement a form model
      (a specialisation of ${doc-link WFormModel}) and a complementary
      template-based view (a specialisation of ${doc-link WTemplateFormView}).
      In this way you can validate the values entered at the server-side.
    </p>
    <p>
      The form model implements field data and validation handling for (simple)
      form-based views. It provides a standard way for views to perform field
      validation, and react to validation results.
      Each field has a string literal assigned to it. The string literal
      uniquely identifies the field. For each field, its value, the visibility,
      whether the field is read-only, and its current validation status is
      managed by the model.
      In addition, you will typically specialize the class to customize the
      validation and application logic. Although it can be setup to use <tt>
      WValidator</tt> objects for individual fields, you could also create a
      validator to simultaneously validate interdependent fields.
    </p>
    <p>
      A model is typically used by a view which renders the fields configured
      in the model, updates the model values, invokes and reflects the
      validation status. See <a href="#/forms/forms">Forms</a> for more details
      on implementing forms.
    </p>
    <p>
      Here is an example with the same behavior as the previous example. It
      also uses the same XML template. The contents of the variable name
      'age-info' in the template depends on the outcome of the method
      <tt>validate()</tt> of the model.
      <ul>
        <li>It holds a confirmation that the value is saved if the input is
          valid.
        </li>
        <li>It holds a validation message if the input is not valid.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ValidationModel}
      ${src ValidationModel}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#validation">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="validation-template">
    <div class="form-horizontal">
      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-3" for="${id:age}">
          Please enter your age:
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-2">${age}</div>
      </div>
      <div class="form-group">
        <div class="col-sm-offset-3 col-sm-7">
          ${button}
        </div>
      </div>
      ${age-info}
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="date-template">
    <div class="form-horizontal">
      <div class="form-group">
        <label class="control-label col-sm-3" for="${id:birth-date}">
          Enter your birth-date:
        </label>
        <div class="col-sm-2">${birth-date}</div>
      </div>
      <div class="form-group">
        <div class="col-sm-offset-3 col-sm-7">
          ${button}
        </div>
      </div>
      ${info}
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="forms-integration-example">
    <h2 id="forms-integration">Integration example</h2>
    <p>
      There are two ways in which you can compose a form:
      <ul>
        <li>using a simple form</li>
        <li>using a Model-View concept</li>
      </ul>
      In the introduction you can find an example using a simple form. Here you
      can find a detailed example using a model/view concept.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${FormModel}
      <p>
        The underlying XML template (with
        <tt>message id="userForm-template"</tt>) uses style classes from the
        <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/base-css.html"
        target="blank">Bootstrap theme</a>.
        In order to apply validation style to any widget with invalid input,
        you should group the widgets in a div or span section and apply the
        style <tt>form-group </tt> to it.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
        <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${userForm-template}</pre>
      </fieldset>
      <p>
        Here is the implementation of <tt>WFormModel</tt> and <tt>
        WTemplateFormView</tt>.
      </p>
      <p>
        There are created validators for several fields. See the section
        <a href="#/forms/validation">Validation</a> for more details on
        validators, especially a more elaborated example on a
        <tt>WDateValidator</tt> for a <tt>WDatePicker</tt>.
      </p>
      ${src FormModel}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#forms-integration">Top</a></p>

  </message>

<!--NAVIGATION message blocks-->

  <message id="navigation-intro">
    <p class="lead">Navigation &#8212; interacting with a browser's navigation model</p>
  </message>

  <message id="navigation-internalPaths">
    <h2>Internal paths</h2>

    <p>
      Out of the box a Wt application is a <i>single page</i>
      application: regardless of what the user does, the URL displayed
      in the location bar does not change. Single page applications
      are typically implemented in JavaScript and use Ajax to pull
      data from the server, while multi-page applications typically
      require full page refreshes.
    </p>

    <p>Single page appliations have a number of draw-backs:

      <dl>
        <dt>Usability</dt>
        <dd><p>The usability of your web application may suffer because
        users lose the ability to use browser history to navigate
        through the application, and bookmarks to bookmark particular
        content (or application state). Whether this is an actual
        usability problem will depend on the type of application: only
        when a user's intuition is deceived in trying to use browser
        navigation buttons to navigate through the pages in your
        application, you should be concerned.</p>

        <p>
          For example, an interactive web application that mimicks a
          desktop application with a single window whose content is
          manipulated might be conceptually considered a single page for
          the user.
        </p>

        <p>
          On the other hand, applications such as web shops, CMS systems, or
          online email readers, all have a need for the user to be able to
          bookmark certain content pages.
        </p>
        </dd>

        <dt>Deep linking</dt>
        <dd>
          <p>There is no possibility for deep linking to content within
          your application from other websites. This is to some extent
          related to the previous point. For example a web shop will
          want its products pages to be linked to from product review
          websites. But for other applications which have no public
          information such as email applications, this might not be a
          motivation for internal paths.</p>
        </dd>

        <dt>Search engine indexing</dt>
        <dd>
          <p>Content in your web application cannot be indexed properly
          by search engines. A related problem, which might be more
          serious for certain types of applications, is how search
          engines will perceive your web application. Web robots index
          the web by retrieving pages and following anchors to other
          pages. When your application is presented as only a single
          page, only the content on your initial page is accessible to
          these search engines.
          </p>
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

    <p>
      Wt allows the application to define internal paths and handle
      changes of internal paths. Because a Wt application is not
      composed of pages, a URL does not define to particular page, but
      rather a particular application state. An internal path is a
      link to a page in a web application.
    </p>

    <p>
      The widget gallery makes extensive use of internal paths: the
      top-level menu provides the first level, and the menu to the
      left a second level.
    </p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>
        With the help of HTML5's History API, Wt provides a perfect
        illusion of a multi-page application, but within a single page!
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p>
      The recommended method to integrate internal path support in
      your application is to use internal path links (defined by
      ${doc-link WLink}) in anchors or menu items, for people to
      navigate to a different 'page' in the application, and respond
      to internal path change events, to show the new page in
      response. thus instead of directly listening to a click event,
      the click results in an internal path change.
    </p>

    <p>
      The main benefit of this approach is that internal path changes
      may also originate from a user navigating using the brower's
      back and forward buttons, may follow such a link in a new window
      (and thus a new session) or may arrive at the internal path
      following a deep link from elsewhere, and this approach
      decouples the origin of the event from the handling of the
      event.
    </p>

    <p>
      As a corner stone feature in Wt, internal paths are entirely
      supported both in Ajax and plain HTML sessions. For browsers
      without support for the HTML5 History API, Ajax sesion will fall
      back to <i>named anchors</i>. This effectively makes internal
      paths the perfect tool for search engine accessibility of your
      application.
    </p>

    <h3>Creating Internal Path Links</h3>

    <p>
      For the following widgets you can associate an internal path
      with the method <tt>setLink()</tt>:
      <ul>
        <li>an <a href="#/navigation/anchor">anchor</a> (${doc-link WAnchor})
        or a pushbutton (${doc-link WPushButton}), or</li>
        <li>a menu item (${doc-link WMenuItem}) from within menus or
        popup menus,</li>
        <li>any ${doc-link WAbstractArea} implementation (like a rectangle,
          circle or polygon) which define interactive areas on images.</li>
      </ul>
      In addition, standard item views such as ${doc-link WTableView}
      will render links for <tt>LinkRole</tt> data.
    </p>

    <p>
      In the example below, the push button is configured to navigate
      to the internal path <tt>/navigation/anchor</tt>; the next item
      in the menu bar. The button behaves as an <a
      href="#/navigation/anchor">anchor</a>. This is similar to how a
      ${doc-link WMenuWidget} or a ${doc-link WTabWidget} works.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Path}
      ${src Path}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      In this example, the <a href="#/navigation/menu">menu</a> reacts
      to the internal path event and selects the corresponding menu
      item. One can also catch the navigation event directly.
    </p>

    <h3>Reacting to internal path changes</h3>

    <p>
      Whereas in traditional page-based frameworks, a
      <i>controller</i> or <i>request router</i> is a central
      component that decides what page content needs to be rendered in
      response to a particular request, Wt employs a quite different
      model. Instead, you can react to internal path changes, by
      listening to the <tt>WApplication::internalPathChanged()</tt>
      signal, as you would react to any other event. At any time,
      including when the application is started, the current internal
      path is available through <tt>WApplication::internalPath()</tt>.
    </p>

    <p>
      The following example shows the basic mechanism to react to an
      internal path event.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PathChange}
      ${src PathChange}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      Notice how the same function is used to react to an actual event
      but also to the initial state. This will be a common pattern in
      widgets that support internal path navigation, as they also need
      to initialize to the initial internal path.
    </p>

  </message>

  <message id="navigation-anchor">
    <h2 id="anchor">Anchor</h2>
    <p>
      An ${doc-link WAnchor} is a widget that represents an HTML
      <tt>&lt;a&gt;</tt> element, and provides a link to an URL. So, you can
      use an anchor to provide link to another web page, document, internal
      application path or a resource. The anchor may contain a label text, an
      image, or any other widget (as it inherits from
      ${doc-link WContainerWidget}).
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Anchor}
      ${src Anchor}
    </fieldset>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${AnchorImage}
      ${src AnchorImage}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      When an anchor is activated, by default the browser will replace the Wt
      application with the targeted document or external url. This could
      terminate the application. This may be changed to suggest the browser to
      follow the link in a new window, using the <tt>setTarget()</tt> method
      with parameter <tt>Wt::TargetNewWindow</tt>.
      Even for non-HTML documents, this may be important since pending Ajax
      requests are cancelled if documents are not served within the browser
      window in certain browsers.
    </p>
    <p>
      <tt>WAnchor</tt> plays an important role for navigation within your
      application, using Wt's internal paths, since they provide support for
      bookmarks, the browser back/forward buttons, and following links in new
      windows. For example, the <a href="#/navigation/menu">WMenu</a> widget
      (used here to navigate Wt widgets) uses anchors for its items by default.
    </p>
    <p>
      You may specify the anchor's target URL directly, but anchors can also
      refer to a <a href="#/media/resources">WResource</a>. A resource
      specifies application-dependent content that may be generated by your
      application on demand. This allows you to serve auxiliary files related
      to a particular application session, and perhaps dynamically generate the
      content. Wt includes ${doc-link WFileResource} to stream a file and
      ${doc-link WMemoryResource} to stream a data vector. When linking to a
      resource, the anchor does not assume ownership of the resource. As a
      result, you may share the same resources for several anchors.
    </p>
    <p>
      Note that if you set a text or image using one of the API methods like
      <tt>setText()</tt> or <tt>setImage()</tt> or a constructor, you should
      not attempt to remove all contents (using <tt>clear()</tt>, or provide a
      layout (using <tt>setLayout()</tt>), as this will result in undefined
      behaviour. The text or image are simply inserted as widgets into the
      container.
    </p>
    <p>
      The widget corresponds to the HTML <tt>&lt;a&gt;</tt> tag and does not
      provide styling. It can be styled using inline or external CSS as
      appropriate.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#anchor">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="navigation-stackedWidget">
    <h2 id="stacked-widget">Stacked widget</h2>
    <p>
      A stacked widget is a container widget that stacks its child widgets on
      top of each other and displays a single child at any time.
    </p>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WStackedWidget} accomplishes this using
      <tt>setHidden(bool)</tt> on the children. Using <tt>currentIndex()</tt>
      and <tt>setCurrentIndex(int index)</tt> you can retrieve or set the
      visible widget.
    </p>
    <p>
      Like its parent ${doc-link WContainerWidget}, <tt>WStackedWidget</tt> is
      by default not inline. The widget is rendered using an HTML
      <tt>&lt;div&gt;</tt> tag and does not provide styling. It can be styled
      using inline or external CSS as appropriate.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Stack}
      ${src Stack}
    </fieldset>

  </message>

  <message id="navigation-menu">
    <h2 id="navigation-menu">Menu</h2>
    <p>
      A menu widget provides a list of items which are associated with some
      contents. At any time one item is selected from the list.
    </p>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WMenu} works in conjunction with a
      <a href="#/navigation/stacked-widget">WStackedWidget</a>,
      which manages the contents.
    </p>
    <p>
      The panel at the left is implemented using a <tt>WMenu</tt>.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Menu}
      ${src Menu}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      You can create items with submenus by using the <tt>WSubMenuItem</tt>
      rather than the default <tt>WMenuItem</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      A menu has full support for bookmarks and the back button, by rendering
      its items using <a href="#/navigation/anchor">WAnchor</a> and making use
      of internal paths.
    </p>
    <p>
      By default, the menu does not provide any styling. It can be rendered
      using HTML <tt>&lt;ul&gt;</tt> and <tt>&lt;li&gt;</tt> elements. It
      should be styled using CSS. The look and behaviour of menu
      items can be customized by just reimplementing the styling. For example,
      the <a href="#/navigation/tab-widget">WTabWidget</a> is merely a
      specialized menu. By default the <tt>nav</tt> class from the
      <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/components.html#navs"
      target="blank">Bootstrap theme</a> is applied.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#navigation-menu">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="navigation-tabWidget">
    <h2 id="navigation-tab">Tab widget</h2>
    <p>
      A tab widget is a widget that organizes contents in tab panes.
    </p>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WTabWidget} combines a horizontal
      <a href="#/navigation/menu">WMenu</a> with a
      <a href="#/navigation/stacked-widget">WStackedWidget</a> in a tab-like look.
      A tab widget will place the tab bar on top of the contents, and fit the
      contents below it. It is similar to a
      <a href="#/navigation/navigation-bar">WNavigationBar</a> but with less
      options like a title or multiple menus.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Tab}
      ${src Tab}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      The tab widget is styled by the current CSS theme. The look (of the
      header) can be overridden using the <tt>Wt-tabs</tt> CSS class and
      addition to selectors like <tt>ul</tt>, <tt>li</tt> and <tt>span</tt>.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#navigation-tab">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="navigation-navigationBar">
    <h2 id="navigation-bar">Navigation bar</h2>
    <p>
      A navigation bar is a widget that organizes contents in window- or
      application-specific drop down menus which are grouped in a parent menu.
      Usually, it is anchored to the top of the screen or a window.
    </p>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WNavigationBar} consists of one ore more
      <a href="#/navigation/menu">WMenu</a> controls - each working in
      conjunction with a <a href="#/navigation/stacked-widget">WStackedWidget</a> to
      manage its contents.
      You can still add other kind of widgets to the navigation bar with
      <tt>addWidget()</tt>.
      It is similar to <a href="#/navigation/tab-widget">WTabWidget</a> but
      it has more features like a title and multiple menus in addition to
      a more extensive style class.
    </p>
    <p>
      In the example below, the title and an optional link is set with the
      method <tt>setTitle()</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Especially for mobile applications, you can make the navigation bar
      responsive to the available screen size with <tt>setResponsive()</tt>.
      You can see the effect by resizing the window size of your browser.
    </p>
    <p>
      Use <tt>addMenu()</tt> to add a menu to the navigation bar, e.g. a menu
      for contents at the left side of the navigation bar and a right menu for
      help. You could also add a search widget with <tt>addSearch()</tt>. Note
      that if you add several widgets to the right then they are placed from
      right to left.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${NavigationBar}
      ${src NavigationBar}
    </fieldset>

    <h3>Remark</h3>
    <p>
      In some cases, you may want to add a form field to the navigation bar
      (e.g. for a compact login option) with <tt>addFormField()</tt>.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#navigation-bar">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="navigation-popupMenu">
    <h2 id="popup-menu">Popup menu</h2>
    <p>
      A popup menu is a menu presented in a popup window. The menu implements a
      typical context menu, with support for submenu's.
    </p>
    <p>
      ${doc-link WPopupMenu} is not to be confused with
      <a href="#/navigation/menu">WMenu</a> which implements an always-visible
      navigation menu for a web application.
    </p>
    <p>
      When initially created, the menu is invisible, until <tt>popup()</tt> or
      <tt>exec()</tt> is called. Then, the menu will remain visible until an
      item is selected, or the user cancels the menu (by pressing the Escape
      key or clicking elsewhere).
    </p>
    <p>
      The implementation assumes availability of JavaScript to position the
      menu at the current mouse position and provide feed-back of the currently
      selected item.
    </p>
    <p>
      <tt>WPopupMenu</tt> is similar in use to
      <a href="#/layout/dialogs">WDialog</a>. So there are two ways of using
      the menu. The simplest way is to use one of the <tt>exec()</tt> methods,
      apply a reentrant event loop and wait until the user selected an item or
      cancelled the popup menu (by pressing Escape or clicking elsewhere).
    </p>
    <p>
      Preferably, use one of the <tt>popup()</tt> methods to show the menu and
      listen to the <tt>aboutToHide</tt> signal where you read the
      <tt>result()</tt> (the last triggered menu item). If you listen to the
      <tt>aboutToHide</tt> signal of a parent popup it will also be triggered
      by its child popups.
    </p>
    <p>
      You have several options to react to the selection of an item:
      <ul>
        <li>
          You can use the ${doc-link WMenuItem} itself to identify the action,
          perhaps by specialization or by simply by binding custom data using
          <tt>WMenuItem::setData()</tt>.
        </li>
        <li>
          You can use a lambda function to connect to each of the listeners.
          In C++, you can use boost::bind() to bind parameters that identify the
          selected item.
        </li>
        <li>
          You can bind a separate method to each item's
          <tt>WMenuItem::triggered</tt> signal.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Popup}
      ${src Popup}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#popup-menu">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="navigation-splitButton">
    <h2 id="split-button">Split button</h2>
    <p>
      A split button is a widget composed of an action button in addition to
      a drop down button which are shown beside each other.
    </p>
    <p>
      The action button of a ${doc-link WSplitButton} is implemented as a
      ${doc-link WPushButton} while the drop down button is implemented as a
      push button with a <a href="#/navigation/popup">WPopupMenu</a>.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${SplitButton}
      ${src SplitButton}
    </fieldset>

  </message>

  <message id="navigation-toolBar">
    <h2 id="toolbar">Toolbar</h2>
    <p>
      A toolbar is a widget composed of child widgets which are shown beside
      each other.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ToolBar}
      ${src ToolBar}
    </fieldset>

  </message>

<!--TREES & TABLES message blocks-->

  <message id="mvc-intro">
    <p class="lead">Trees &amp; Tables &#8212; widgets for tabular and
    tree-like data</p>
  </message>

  <message id="treestables-Tables">
    <h2 id="tables">Tables</h2>
    <p>
      The most direct way to organize widgets in a tabular grid is
      using ${doc-link WTable}. This widget renders as an HTML
      <tt>&lt;table&gt;</tt> element.
    </p>

    <p>
      Each table cell is a <a href="#/layout/">Container</a> to which
      ontents can be added. The table will grow as necessary while you
      add data to it.
    </p>

    <p>
      Our first example shows a plain table, with default browser
      styling.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PlainTable}
      ${src PlainTable}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      If you only need to display a <strong>static</strong> table
      (with a fixed number of rows and columns), then you might just
      as well consider using a <a
      href="#/layout/html-templates">WTemplate</a> containing the HTML
      markup for a table, and providing the contents (widgets or
      strings) by substituting place holders.
    </p>

    <p>
      In contrast, the <tt>WTable</tt> class is suitable when the
      table is to be constructed dynamically, based on information
      that may be variable in size.
    </p>

    <p>
      Finally, you may want to consider using a <a
      href="#/trees-tables/mvc-table-views">WTableView</a> if you
      would like to display large amounts of data (more than could fit
      in memory!), or if you would like the user to be able to resort
      the data or resize columns.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#tables">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Bootstrap styling</h3>

    <p>
      The bootstrap theme provides optional markup for the
      table. These styles are enabled by adding the <tt>"table"</tt>
      style class, and other optional style classes. The other styling
      options are enabled by adding one of the following classes:
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>table-bordered</dt>
        <dd>Adds borders</dd>
        <dt>table-hover</dt>
        <dd>Enables a row hover effect</dd>
        <dt>table-condensed</dt>
        <dd>Makes the table more compact</dd>
        <dt>table-striped</dt>
        <dd>Adds alternating row colors</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${StyledTable}
      ${src StyledTable}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#tables">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="treestables-Trees">
    <h2 id="tree">Trees</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WTree} displays a tree widget.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Tree}
      ${src Tree}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#tree">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="treestables-TreeTables">
    <h2 id="treetable">Trees</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WTreeTable} displays a tree widget.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${TreeTable}
      ${src TreeTable}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#treetable">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="treestables-TableViews">
    <h2 id="mvc-table-view">MVC Table Views</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WTableView} displays tabular data. The data is
      provided by a separate ${doc-link WAbstractItemModel}. This is a
      variation of the classical MVC strategy, where the
      <strong>View</strong> displays data provided by a
      <strong>Model</strong>. The View delegates the rendering of each
      individual item (i.e. table cell) to an <strong>Item
      Delegate</strong> (${doc-link WItemDelegate} to render an item
      as a widget, allowing this aspect to be customized without
      needing to deal with the rest of the complexity of the view.
    </p>
    <p>
      A more direct approach to showing a table of data is to use a
      ${doc-link WTable} which allows you to directly specify a widget
      that renders each cell. Compared to this, a <tt>WTableView</tt>
      support virtual scrolling (for both rows and columns !), column
      sorting and resize handles, and the ability to define row
      headers which allow you to scroll through many columns of
      additional data while keeping the first header column(s) within
      view. Its main restriction is that every item must have the same
      height.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${SmallTableView}
      ${src SmallTableView}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#mvc-table-view">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Virtual scrolling</h3>
    <p>
      A tableview has the capbility todisplay large datasets, by
      implementing virtual scrolling both horizontally and vertically.
    </p>

    <p>
      The example below shows how one can scroll through data in a
      virtual model with 10000 rows and 50 columns.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${LargeTableView}
      <p>
      ${src LargeTableView}
      </p>
      <span class="label label-info">Note</span>
      The implementation of <tt>VirtualModel</tt> is shown
      <a href="#/trees-tables/mvc-item-models">in the section on item
      models</a>
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#mvc-table-view">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Customizing cell rendering</h3>

    <p>
      The rendering of each cell is handled by a ${doc-link
      WAbstractItemDelegate}. An item delegate will typically query
      various properties of an item, which are provided by the model for
      different <a
      href="${doc-url}group__modelview.html#ga0ae864e12320f9f89172735e075ed068"
      target="_blank">data roles</a> (which one can consider pretty
      much like a 3rd dimension for what otherwise corresponds to
      two-dimensional model organized in rows and columns). The default
      implementation (${doc-link WItemDelegate}) will
      <ul>
        <li>render <strong>text</strong>,
            using the data role<tt>DisplayRole</tt>,</li>
        <li>render <strong>icons</strong>,
            using the data role <tt>DecorationRole</tt>,</li>
        <li>render <strong>check boxes</strong>,
            using the data role <tt>CheckStateRole</tt>,</li>
        <li>render <strong>links</strong>,
            using the data role <tt>LinkRole</tt>,</li>
        <li>render <strong>tool tips</strong>,
            using the data role <tt>ToolTipRole</tt>,</li>
        <li>render <strong>style classes</strong>,
            using the data role <tt>StyleClassRole</tt>.</li>
      </ul>
      If the default item delegate doesn't satisfy, you can reimplement it to
      tailor the rendering, and you can extend models with data for additional
      data roles.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#mvc-table-view">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Editing + Combo box editor example</h3>
    <p>
      MVC Views will automatically react to changes to the underlying
      model, be it in the form of data updates, or the insertion of
      new rows or columns.
    </p>
    <p>
      But an MVC View may also actively participate in editing the
      data. You can define editing triggers (such as a double click)
      and the model can indicate to the view which data can be
      edited. The default item delegate (<tt>WItemDelegate</tt>) will
      use a line edit for editing, but this can be customized by
      providing your own item delegate implementation.
    </p>
    <p>
      The example below illustrates how to override the editing behaviour of 
      ${doc-link WItemDelegate}. It uses a combo box to allow the user to edit 
      the cell values.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ComboDelegateTable}
      <p>
      ${src ComboDelegateTable}
      </p>
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#mvc-table-view">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Row headers</h3>
    <p>
      Especially when displaying datasets with many columns, it may be
      convenient to define a number of columns as row headers (using
      <tt>WAbstractItemView::setRowHeaderCount()</tt>), which are kept
      in view while scrolling to the columns.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#mvc-table-view">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="treestables-TreeViews">
    <h2 id="mvc-tree-view">MVC Tree Views</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WTreeView} displays tree data (with additional
      properties available in extra columns). The archetypical
      application is a file system browser: the filesystem tree is
      displayed in the first column, and additional columns annotate
      properties of files.
    </p>
    <p>
      As with other MVC item views, the actual data is provided by a
      ${doc-link WAbstractItemModel}. This is a variation of the
      classical MVC strategy, where the <strong>View</strong> displays
      data provided by a <strong>Model</strong>. The View delegates
      the rendering of each individual item (i.e. table cell) to an
      <strong>Item Delegate</strong> to render (as a widget) the
      individual items, allowing this to be easily customized.
    </p>
    <p>
      A more direct approach to showing a tree is to use the <a
      href="#/trees-tables/trees">WTree</a> or <a
      href="#/trees-tables/tree-tables">WTreeTable</a> widgets which
      do not enforce this Model/View separation and allow you to directly
      specify the widgets that renders each cell. Compared to this, a
      <tt>WTreeView</tt> supports virtual scrolling (have you ever
      seen that for a tree ?), column sorting and resize handles, and
      row headers which allow you to scroll through many columns of
      additional data while keeping the first column within view. Its
      main restriction is that each row must have the same height.
    </p>

    <p>
      The example below shows a treeview that is seeded with a custom
      hierarhical model which displays a revision in a git repository.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${TreeView}
      <p>
      ${src TreeView}
      </p>
      <span class="label label-info">Note</span> The implementation of
      <tt>GitModel</tt> is discussed in <a
      href="#/trees-tables/mvc-item-models">Item Models</a>
    </fieldset>

    <h3>Other Features</h3>
    <p>
      The tree view shares a great deal of functionality with its
      sibling table view (which both reimplement
      ${doc-link WAbstractItemView}), such as customizing cell rendering,
      editing and row headers. See <a href="#/trees-tables/mvc-table-views">
      MVC Table Views</a>.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#mvc-tree-view">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="treestables-ItemModels">
    <h2 id="mvc-item-models">MVC Item Models</h2>

    <p>A common data model involves lists, tables and trees of more or
    less uniform items. Several standard widgets provided by the
    library use such a model. The abstract #{doc-link
    WAbstractItemModel} base class provides the interface which is
    used by these view classes.</p>

    <p>Not only <a href="#/trees-tables/mvc-table-views">Table
    Views</a> and <a href="#/trees-tables/mvc-tree-views">Tree
    Views</a> display (and interact with) data from an item model, but
    so do also the list-oriented widgets such as <a
    href="#/forms/combo-box">Combo box</a>, <a
    href="#/forms/selection-box">Selection box</a>, <a
    href="#/forms/autocomplete">Auto complete</a>, and charting
    widgets such as <a
    href="#/graphics-charts/category-chart">Cartesian Chart, Scatter
    Plot</a> and <a
    href="#/graphics-charts/pie-chart">Pie Chart</a>.
    </p>

    <div>
      <img src="/pics/modelview.png"
           style="max-width: none; margin: 5px auto; display: block"/>
    </div>

    <h3>The model</h3>

    <blockquote>
      <p>An item model is essentially a table of items, where each
      item can be a parent to a nested table of items.</p>
    </blockquote>

    <p>Since recursive statements like the one above can confuse even
    a seasoned programmer, let's start from a simple model, and extend
    it to more complex instances.</p>

    <h4>Lists</h4>

    <img src="/pics/list-models.png" style="max-width: none; float: right; margin: 30px"/>

    <p>In its most simple and perhaps most common form, an item model
    simply stores a list of items. Such a model has only one column.
    </p>

    <p>
      Each item may holds different facets of the data, stored as
      different <strong>Item Data Roles</strong>. If a table has two
      dimensions (rows an columns), then data roles could be considered
      as a third dimension.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      The common use-case for item data roles is that for a single
      item, there may be a textual representation, but also an icon, a
      customized style class, a link, etc... 
    </p>

    <p>
      The built-in views will thus interpret
      subsets of this data to render a single item. In particular, the
      following data roles are commonly supported:
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>DisplayRole</dt>
        <dd>Rendered as text</dd>
        <dt>DecorationRole</dt>
        <dd>Rendered as icons</dd>
        <dt>CheckStateRole</dt>
        <dd>Rendered as check box state</dd>
        <dt>LinkRole</dt>
        <dd>Rendered as links</dd>
        <dt>ToolTipRole</dt>
        <dd>Rendered as tool tips</dd>
        <dt>StyleClassRole</dt>
        <dd>Rendered as style classes</dd>
      </dl>

      See the <a
      href="${doc-url}group__modelview.html#ga0ae864e12320f9f89172735e075ed068"
      target="_blank">WItemDataRole</a> enumeration for a more complete
      list of standard roles, whose use may depend on the View.
    </p>

    <h4 style="clear: both">Tables</h4>

    <img src="/pics/table-models.png" style="max-width: none; float: right; margin: 30px"/>

    As a straight forward generalization to lists, tables may include
    more than one more column, and each item can be identified by a
    <i>(row, column)</i> pair.
      
    <h4 style="clear: both">Trees</h4>

    <img src="/pics/tree-models.png" style="max-width: none; float: right; margin: 30px"/>

    <p>
      A tree model is - like a list - a model with a single column. In addition
      each item may be parent to another list.
    </p>

    <p>
      At this point it becomes necessary to introduce the concept of
      a ${doc-link WModelIndex} to uniquely identify an item. A model
      index is a data structucre containing:

      <dl class="dl-horizontal no-clear">
        <dt>row</dt>
        <dd>The row number</dd>
        <dt>column</dt>
        <dd>The column number</dd>
        <dt>parent</dt>
        <dd>The parent model index</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

    <p>
      The recursion is thus achieved by associating a parent index
      with each item index. By convention, top-level items have an
      <strong>Invalid</strong> index (which is a default constructed
      <tt>WModelIndex</tt>). To make the recursive definition
      consistent, one can also imagine an invisible root item
      (corresponding to the "invalid" index) which is the parent of
      the top-level items.
    </p>

    <h4>Tree Tables</h4>

    <p>
      Finally, a tree table extends the list model by allow additional
      columns of data to be associated with each item row.
    </p>

    <p>
      None of the standard Views render hierarchical data that is not
      present in the first column ! While such data structures can
      indeed be defined by item models, this will effectively be
      ignored by the standard View classes.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#mvc-item-models">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Standard model implementations</h3>

    <p>
      To get you going, and more than sufficient for simple needs, the
      library provides a number of standard and generic models, which
      store the data in memory.
      <ul>
        <li>${doc-link WStandardItemModel} can implement any kind of
        item model, being composed of a table of ${doc-link
        WStandardItem}'s, which each can contain itself a nested table
        of <tt>WStandardItem</tt> items.</li>
        <li>${doc-link WStringListModel} only supports lists with a
        single column, and is thus optimized for list-oriented widgets
        (combo-boxes and the like).</li>
      </ul>

      One particarly useful standard model is the ${doc-link
      Dbo-QueryModel} which is a tabular model backed by database
      data.
    </p>

    <h3>Custom models</h3>

    <p>
      Separating models from views would be not very useful, if it were
      not of the ablity to implement customized models. These could be
      models that compute some or all data on the fly, or fetch this
      information from a underlying database or file system, or simply
      display information from an existing data structure in a
      tabular/tree-like way.
    </p>

    <h4>Table models</h4>

    <p>
      As a minimum, a custom table model should reimplement the
      following methods from ${doc-link WAbstractTableModel}:
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>int rowCount()</dt>
        <dd>Returns the table row count (only for the invalid parent!)</dd>
        <dt>int columnCount()</dt>
        <dd>Returns the table column count (only for the invalid parent!)</dd>
        <dt>boost::any data()</dt>
        <dd>Returns the data for an item, and a particular role</dd>
        <dt>boost::any headerData()</dt>
        <dd>Returns the header data for a column</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

    <p>
      As an example of a custom table model, consider the following
      (non-sensical) model that simply displays row/column information
      for each item.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${LargeTableView}
      <p>
      ${src VirtualModel}
      </p>
      <span class="label label-info">Note</span> The instantiation of
      this model with a Table View is discussed in <a
      href="#/trees-tables/mvc-table-views">MVC Table Views</a>.
    </fieldset>

    <h4>Tree models</h4>

    <p>
      A custom tree model involves considerably more work. Each
      internal item (in the first column) which has children, needs to
      be identified by a unique 64-bit value (which may thus be a
      <tt>long long</tt> or a <tt>void *</tt> pointer). Depending on
      the source data, a suitable choice must be made for this data.
    </p>

    <p>
      The following methods must be implemented for a minimally
      compliant hierarchical model:
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>int rowCount()</dt>
        <dd>Returns the item children count</dd>
        <dt>int columnCount()</dt>
        <dd>Returns the column count (which is usually the same for
          each item in the first column)</dd>
        <dt>boost::any data()</dt>
        <dd>Returns the data for an item, and a particular role</dd>
        <dt>boost::any headerData()</dt>
        <dd>Returns the header data for a column</dd>
        <dt>WModelIndex child()</dt>
        <dd>Creates a child index</dd>
        <dt>WModelIndex parent()</dt>
        <dd>Creates a parent index</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

    <p>
      As an example of a tree table model, consider the following
      model that loads information from a git repository (in this
      case, Wt's git). Only a minimum of information is kept in
      memory: we allocate a data structure only for folders that are
      being expanded, for use as internal pointer data in model
      indexes.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${TreeView}
      <p>
      ${src GitModel}
      </p>
      <span class="label label-info">Note</span> The instantiation of
      this model with a Tree View is discussed in <a
      href="#/trees-tables/mvc-tree-views">MVC Tree Views</a>.
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#mvc-item-models">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Sorting</h3>

    <p>
      A model may support sorting by one of its columns. This sorting
      can be implemented within the model itself.
    </p>

    <dl class="dl-horizontal">
      <dt>void sort()</dt>
      <dd>Sorts the model according to one of its columns.</dd>
    </dl>
    
    <p>
      Sorting may be bolted onto a source model using the <a
      href="#/trees-tables/proxy-models">WSortFilterProxyModel</a>,
      which is one of the standard proxy models.
    </p>

    <h3>Model Changes</h3>

    <p>
      A model does not necessarily need to be a static data source, but
      its data can also change, and data (rows/columns) can be added or
      removed. A model needs to generate events to inform Views of these
      modifications (for the events to which a View is subscribed). When
      implementing a custom model which is dynamic in nature, it is
      therefore important to emit these signals when making the
      modifications.
    </p>

    <!-- TODO List the relevant events here, in a table ? -->

    <h3>Editing</h3>

    <p>
      The model API also provides a standard interface to perform
      editing of the data, and some Views (such as the Tree View and
      Table Views) can be configured to allow editing of the data.
    </p>

    <p>
      If a custom wants to support this editing API, it needs to reimplement the
      following methods from ${doc-link WAbstractTableModel}:
      <dl class="dl-horizontal">
        <dt>bool setData()</dt>
        <dd>Updates data. Views typically use the <tt>EditRole</tt>
        for the data used in editing</dd>
        <dt>bool insertColumns()</dt>
        <dd>Inserts one or more columns</dd>
        <dt>bool insertRows()</dt>
        <dd>Inserts one or more rows</dd>
        <dt>bool removeColumns()</dt>
        <dd>Removes one or more columns</dd>
        <dt>bool removeRows()</dt>
        <dd>Removes one or more rows</dd>
      </dl>
    </p>

    <p><a href="#mvc-item-models">Top</a></p>

  </message>

<!--GRAPHICS & CHARTS message blocks-->

  <message id="graphics-intro">
    <p class="lead">Graphics &amp; Charts &#8212; generic and specialized painting
    infrastructure</p>
  </message>

  <message id="graphics-Painting2D">
    <h2 id="painting2D">2D Painting</h2>
    <h3>The painting system</h3>
    <p>
      Wt provides a vector graphics painting system, which depending on the
      browser support, uses inline SVG, inline VML, HTML5 &lt;canvas&gt; or a
      raster image to paint the graphics.
    </p>
    <p>
      The Wt API provides different classes that provide support for vector
      graphics painting. To use the paint system, you need to specialize
      ${doc-link WPaintedWidget} and use a ${doc-link WPainter} to paint the
      contents of the widget inside its <tt>WPaintedWidget::paintEvent()</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      In addition, a PDF backend is included in the library, which can be used
      <ul>
        <li>to <strong>make a PDF version</strong> of a painting, or</li>
        <li>to <strong>embed a painting</strong> in a PDF document.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      To use inline SVG, you need to enable XHTML support in your configuration
      file (<tt>wt_config.xml</tt>) by enabling send-xhtml-mimetype .
    </p>

    <h3>Vector graphics painting class</h3>
    <p>
      The painter class ${doc-link WPainter} provides a vector graphics
      interface for painting. It has to be used in conjunction with a
      ${doc-link WPaintDevice}, onto which it paints:
      <ul>
        <li>Use ${doc-link WSvgImage} to render with SVG (Scalable Vector
            Graphics).</li>
        <li>Use ${doc-link WVmlImage} to render with the VML pseudo-standard.
            </li>
        <li>Use ${doc-link WCanvasPaintDevice} to render with HTML5 &lt;canvas&gt;
            element.</li>
        <li>Use ${doc-link WRasterImage} to render to a raster image.</li>
        <li>Use ${doc-link WPdfImage} to render to PDF.</li>
      </ul>
      WSvgImage and WVmlImage are paint devices for rendering using native
      vector graphics. The benefit of vector graphics is a lower bandwidth
      usage compared to raster images; indepedent of the image size.
      To start painting on a device, either pass the device through the
      constructor, or use <tt>begin()</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      A typical use is to instantiate a <tt>WPainter</tt> from within a
      specialized <tt>WPaintedWidget::paintEvent()</tt> implementation, to
      paint on the given paint device, but you can also use a painter to paint
      directly to a particular paint device of choice, for example to create
      SVG, PDF or PNG images (as resources). A painted widget can dynamically
      be updated as shown in the following example.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PaintingEvent}
      ${src PaintingEvent}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#painting2D">Top</a></p>

    <p>
      The painter maintains the state such a...
      <ul>
        <li>the current <strong>pen</strong>, which you can define with
            <tt>setPen()</tt>,</li>
        <li>the current <strong>brush</strong>, which you can define with
            <tt>setBrush()</tt>,
        </li>
        <li>the current <strong>font</strong>, which you can define with
            <tt>setFont()</tt>,
        </li>
        <li>the current <strong>world transformation matrix</strong>, which you
            can get with <tt>worldTransform()</tt>,</li>
        <li>the <strong>clipping settings</strong> (See <tt>setClipping()</tt>
            and <tt>setClipPath()</tt>).</li>
      </ul>
      A particular state can be saved using <tt>save()</tt> and later restored
      using <tt>restore()</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      The painting system distinguishes between different coordinate types:
      <ul>
        <li>device coordinates,</li>
        <li>logical coordinates, and</li>
        <li>local coordinates.</li>
      </ul>
      Each coordinate type corresponds to a coordinate system:
      <dl>
        <dt>The device coordinate system</dt>
        <dd>ranges from (0, 0) in the top left corner of the device, to
        <tt>device->width().toPixels(), device->height().toPixels()</tt> for
            the bottom right corner.</dd>
        <dt>The logical coordinate system</dt>
        <dd>defines a coordinate system that may be chosen independent of the
            geometry of the device, which is convenient to make abstraction of
            the actual device size. </dd>
        <dt>The local coordinate system</dt>
        <dd>may be different from the logical coordinate system because of a
            transformation (which you can set with <tt>translate()</tt>,
            <tt>rotate()</tt>, and <tt>scale()</tt>).</dd>
      </dl>
      Initially, the local coordinate system coincides with the logical
      coordinate system, which coincides with the device coordinate system.
    </p>
    <p>
      The device coordinates are defined in terms of pixels. Even though most
      underlying devices are actual vector graphics formats, when used in
      conjunction with a <tt>WPaintedWidget</tt>, these vector graphics are
      rendered by the browser onto a pixel-based canvas (like the rest of the
      user-interface). The coordinates are defined such that integer values
      correspond to an imaginary raster which separates the individual pixels,
      as in the figure below.
    </p>
    <p class="centered">
      <img alt="The device coordinate system for a 6x5 pixel device"
           src="/pics/WPainter.png"></img> <br/>
      <strong>The device coordinate system for a 6x5 pixel device</strong>
    </p>
    <p>
      As a consequence, to avoid anti-aliasing effects when drawing straight
      lines of width one pixel, you will need to use vertices that indicate the
      middle of a pixel to get a crisp one-pixel wide line, as shown in the
      above picture.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can map logical coordinates onto device coordinates by setting a
      <tt>viewPort()</tt> and a <tt>window()</tt>; this defines a viewPort
      transformation.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can define how the current local coordinates map onto
      logical coordinates by changing the world transformation using
      <tt>translate()</tt>, <tt>rotate()</tt>, <tt>scale()</tt> and
      <tt>setWorldTransform()</tt> operations.
    </p>
    <p>
      The painter provides support for clipping using an arbitrary
      ${doc-link WPainterPath}. Please note that the ${doc-link WVmlImage}
      paint device only has limited support for clipping.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PaintingShapes}
      ${src PaintingShapes}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#painting2D">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Transformations</h3>

    <h4>Introduction</h4>
    <p>
      Besides the different transformation methods which you can apply to a
      drawing (i.e. translate, rotate, and scale), there are also two other
      methods which are indispensable once you start generating more complex
      drawings:
      <ul>
        <li>
          <tt>WPainter::save()</tt> to save the current painter state on a
          stack, and
        </li>
        <li>
          <tt>WPainter::restore()</tt> to restore a painter state from the
          stack.
        </li>
      </ul>
      The <strong>painter state</strong> that is saved is the current pen,
      brush, font, shadow, transformation and clipping settings (See
      <tt>WPainter::setClipping()</tt> and
      <tt>WPainter::setClipPath()</tt>).
    </p>

    <h4>Translate the origin</h4>
    <p>
      The method <tt>WPainter::translate()</tt> translates the origin of the
      logical coordinate system to a new location relative to the current
      logical coordinate system. It's a good practice to save the painter
      state before doing any transformations because usually, it's easier to
      call <tt>restore()</tt> compared to a reverse translation to return to
      the oiginal state. In addition, if you're translating in a loop you might
      end up missing a part of your drawing because it was drawn outside the
      the paint device's edge.
    </p>

    <h4>Rotate to the paint device</h4>
    <p>
      The method <tt>WPainter::rotate()</tt> rotates the logical coordinate
      system around its origin by an angle. The angle is specified in degrees,
      and positive values are clockwise. Use this method to rotate an object
      around its origin before it is drawn on the paint device.
    </p>

    <h4>Scale to the paint device</h4>
    <p>
      The method <tt>WPainter::scale()</tt> scales the logical coordinate
      system around its origin, by a factor in the X and Y directions.
      Use this method to scale what you draw on the paint device.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PaintingTransformations}
      ${src PaintingTransformations}
    </fieldset>

    <h4>Reset the transformations</h4>
    <p>
      Use the method <tt>WPainter::resetTransform()</tt> to reset the current
      transformation to the identity transformation matrix, so that the logical
      coordinate system coincides with the device coordinate system.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#painting2D">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Clipping paths</h3>
    <p>
      A clipping path is like a normal ${doc-link WPainterPath} but it acts as
      mask to hide unwanted parts of shapes. The path is specified in local
      coordinates.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can set a clipping path with the method <tt>setClipPath()</tt>.
      To apply clipping you still have to enable clipping using
      <tt>setClipping(true)</tt>.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PaintingClipping}
      ${src PaintingClipping}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#painting2D">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Style</h3>
    <p>
      Until now we used a limited number of line and fill styles. Now we will
      explore other options to make a drawing more attractive by examples.
      <ul>
        <li>
          the difference between <strong>filling</strong> with a brush and
          <strong>stroking</strong> with a pen
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>transparency</strong> - drawing semi-transparent shapes using
          a color with lower opacity
        </li>
        <li>
          painting with a <strong>gradient brush</strong>
        </li>
        <li>
          rendering <strong>line ends</strong> with the line style
          <tt>PenCapStyle</tt> (flat, square or round)
        </li>
        <li>
          rendering <strong>line joins</strong> using the style
          <tt>PenJoinStyle</tt> (miter, bevel or round)
        </li>
        <li>
          drawing thicker lines using <tt>strokePath()</tt>
        </li>
        <li>
          drawing crisp lines - even if the line thickness is an odd integer
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PaintingStyle}
      ${src PaintingStyle}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#painting2D">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Images</h3>
    <p>
      One of the more fun features of ${doc-link WPainter} is that you can
      render one or more images on a painting using the method
      <tt>drawImage()</tt>. Images can be used for dynamic photo compositing or
      as a background for a drawing (e.g. with shapes, graphs, etc.).
      An image is specified in terms of a URL, and the width and height.
    </p>
    <p>
      An image can be drawn in different ways:
      <ul>
        <li>Draw an image at a starting point.</li>
        <li>Draw a part of an image at a starting point.</li>
        <li>
          Draw an image in a rectangle and scale it to the width and heigth of
          it.
        </li>
        <li>
          Draw a part of an image in a rectangle and scale it to the width and
          heigth of it.
        </li>
      </ul>
      Please note that the image can become blurry when scaling up or grainy
      when scaling down too much.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PaintingImages}
      ${src PaintingImages}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#painting2D">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Client side interaction and repainting</h3>
    <p>
      In order to avoid server roundtrips, it's possible to change some of the
      properties of a ${doc-link WPaintedWidget} and redraw it entirely on the client side.
      The interactive features of ${doc-link WCartesianChart} use this
      functionality, for example.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PaintingInteractive}
      ${src PaintingInteractive}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#painting2D">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="graphics-Paintbrush">
    <h2 id="paintbrush">Paintbrush</h2>
    <p>
      Here is an example showing a more dynamic use of Wt's vector
      graphics API.
    </p>
    <p>
      Wt's ${doc-link WPaintedWidget} renders as SVG, VML or HTML5
      graphics depending on the capabilities of the browser. The
      backend decides how to render the graphics, the application
      programmer has to draw his graphics using the available methods
      in the ${doc-link WPainter} API. The drawing primitives include
      points, lines, arcs, cubic splines, text, etc.
    </p>
    <p>
      The <tt>update()</tt> method of <tt>WPaintedWidget</tt> is called with
      the <tt>PaintUpdate</tt> rendering flag to update the canvas without
      clearing the previously painted contents (which is the default behavior).
    </p>
    <p>
      Every mouse drag operation on the simple painting device is sent to the
      server, which in turn updates the canvas. You could imagine more
      interesting use cases, such as a multi-user white board, or interactive
      visualizations.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can use a custom cursor image (pencil) by providing a cursor image to
      ${doc-link WCssDecorationStyle}.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Paintbrush}
      ${src Paintbrush}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="graphics-CategoryChart">
    <h2 id="category-chart">Category chart</h2>
    <h3>The Charting library</h3>
    <p>
      The examples in this menu and the other charting menus
      <a href="#/graphics/scatter-plot">Scatter plot</a> and
      <a href="#/graphics/pie-chart">Pie chart</a> demonstrate some of the
      capabilities of the
      <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/namespaceWt_1_1Chart.html"
      target="_new">Wt charting widgets</a>. These widgets are implemented using
      the Wt painting API ${doc-link WPaintedWidget} which provides
      cross-browser native painting, using VML, SVG, or the HTML5 canvas tag.
    </p>
    <p>
      The two main chart widgets are
      <ul>
        <li>
          ${doc-link WCartesianChart}, which provides charts with a X and a Y
          axis to show data, and
        </li>
        <li>
          ${doc-link WPieChart} which provides pie charts.
        </li>
      </ul>
      These widgets are based on the MVC mechanism, and retrieve their data
      from a ${doc-link WAbstractItemModel}.
    </p>
    <p>
      A cartesian chart is either a CategoryChart or a ScatterPlot.
      <ul>
        <li>
          A <strong>CategoryChart</strong> shows data in categories.
        </li>
        <li>
          A <strong>ScatterPlot</strong> shows the data according to a
          numerical X scale.
        </li>
      </ul>
      It can display one or multiple data series which may be rendered
      individually using bars, lines, areas, or points.
      To use a cartesian chart, the minimum you need to do is to set a model
      using <tt>setModel()</tt>, set the model column that holds the X data
      using <tt>setXSeriesColumn(int modelColumn)</tt>, and add one or more
      series using <tt>addSeries(const WDataSeries&amp;)</tt>. Each series
      corresponds to one data column that holds Y data.
    </p>
    <p>
      Many aspects of the charts may be customized. By default, style
      information for rendering data series are taken from a
      ${doc-link WChartPalette}. It is straightforward to specialize this class
      to provide different styles from the standard styles provided by
      ${doc-link WStandardPalette}.
    </p>
    <p>
      The cartesian chart has support for dual Y axes. Each data series may be
      bound to one of the two Y axes. By default, only the first Y axis is
      displayed. To show the second Y axis you will need to call
      <tt>chart->axis(Y2Axis).setVisible(true)</tt>
      By default a chart has a horizontal X axis and a vertical Y axis, which
      corresponds to a <tt>Vertical</tt> orientation. The orientation may be
      changed to <tt>Horizontal</tt> using <tt>setOrientation()</tt>.
      The styling of the data series are defined by a palette which may be set
      using <tt>setPalette(WChartPalette *)</tt>, but may be overridden by
      settings in each data series.
    </p>

    <h3>What is a category chart?</h3>
    <p>
      A category chart has different categories on the X axis, and displays
      values of one or more data series on the Y axes as a series of bars. The
      values corresponding to each category are plotted consecutively in model
      row order. Each data series corresponds to a column from the model and
      may be rendered differently (This is configured in the data series - See
      ${doc-link WDataSeries} for more information).
    </p>
    <p>
      As a cartesian chart it provides automatic configuration of the axes, and
      support for a second Y axis. In addition, you may use a simple built-in
      legend, or extend the class to provide a specialized legend. In the
      example below, we use a manual Y axis configuration, with a break as
      would be commonly used when your data has a few outliers.
    </p>
    <p>
      The table view allows editing of the model, which is automatically
      reflected in the chart.
    </p>
    <p>
      By the way, would you expect this example to work when Ajax/JavaScript
      are not available or disabled?
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${CategoryChart}
      ${src CategoryChart}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#category-chart">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="graphics-ScatterPlot">
    <h2 id="scatter-plot">Scatter Plot</h2>
    <h3>The Charting library</h3>
    <p>
      See <a href="#graphics/category-chart">Category chart</a> for an
      introduction to the charting library.
    </p>

    <h3>What is a scatter plot?</h3>
    <p>
      A scatter plot is very much like a category chart, but uses numerical
      data on the X axis. By default, these numerical data are mapped linearly
      on the X axis, but may also be log transformed (This can also be
      configured for the Y axes). In addition, there is special support for
      displaying date series, by means of smart heuristics for chosing the
      labels on the X axis.
    </p>
    <p>
      In a ScatterPlot, the X series data are interpreted as numbers on a
      linear scale. The scale for the X axis defaults to a
      <strong>LinearScale</strong>, but this may be changed to a
      <strong>DateScale</strong> when the X series contains dates (of type
      <tt>WDate</tt>) to create a time series chart, or to a
      <strong>LogScale</strong>. A ScatterPlot supports the same types of data
      series as a CategoryChart, but does not support stacking. In a scatter
      plot, the X series do not need to be ordered in increasing values, and it
      may be set differently for each dataseries using
      <tt>WDataSeries::setXSeriesColumn(int modelColumn)</tt>.
    </p>

    <h3>Scatter plot of a time series</h3>
    <p>
      The table below shows an extract from historical financial market data.
      The scatter plot shows the second and the third column as line series.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ScatterPlotData}
      ${src ScatterPlotData}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#scatter-plot">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Scatter plot of a function</h3>
    <p>
      Below we plot a single sine curve. We use 'curve' data series, which
      creates a smooth spline curve that interpolates the data points. As is
      typical when showing mathematical functions, we let the axes cross each
      other at the origin (0, 0).
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ScatterPlotCurve}
      ${src ScatterPlotCurve}
    </fieldset>

    <h3>Remark</h3>
    <p>
      Missing data in a model series Y values is interpreted as a break. For
      curve-like series, this breaks the curve (or line).
    </p>

    <p><a href="#scatter-plot">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Interactive features</h3>
    <p>
      WCartesianChart supports some forms of interaction that do not require a server roundtrip.
      You can zoom in on the chart below using ctrl+scroll, or with a pinch movement, and pan it
      with the scrollwheel, click and drag, or touch and drag.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ScatterPlotInteractive}
      ${src ScatterPlotInteractive}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#scatter-plot">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="graphics-AxisSliderWidget">
    <h2 id="axis-slider-widget">Axis slider widget</h2>
    <p>
      If you have a chart with a long range of X values,
      and want to easily focus on a particular range, you can use a ${doc-link 'Chart::WAxisSliderWidget'}. You can change
      the size of the focused region by dragging the blue handles, and change the position by dragging
      the selected area. When using touch, the size of this area can also be changed using a pinch movement.
    </p>
    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${AxisSliderWidget}
      ${src AxisSliderWidget}
    </fieldset>
    <h3>Using an alternative WDataSeries</h3>
    <p>
      If a series is assigned to a ${doc-link 'Chart::WAxisSliderWidget'}, but is hidden on the chart,
      then it will still be drawn on the WAxisSliderWidget. Combined with the
      zoomRangeChanged method of ${doc-link 'Chart::WAxis'}, this can be used to have a
      rough version of the data to present in the WAxisSliderWidget, and as the
      user zooms in, present a more detailed version of the data.
    </p>
    <p>
      The example below shows a rough version of the data in the slider, and as
      you zoom in, a more fine version will be loaded on demand of the zoomed in
      area.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${AxisSliderWidgetDifferentDataSeries}
      ${src AxisSliderWidgetDifferentDataSeries}
    </fieldset>
  </message>

  <message id="graphics-PieChart">
    <h2 id="pie-chart">Pie Chart</h2>
    <h3>The Charting library</h3>
    <p>
      See <a href="#graphics/category-chart">Category chart</a> for an
      introduction to the charting library.
    </p>

    <h3>What is a pie chart?</h3>
    <p>
      A pie chart is a circular visualization of a single data series. The pie
      chart is provided by the ${doc-link WPieChart} widget. The class supports
      both plain 2D pies, as well as a 3D effect (as used below). In the
      example the first segment is separated from the pie for emphasis.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PieChart}
      ${src PieChart}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#pie-chart">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="graphics-GoogleMap">
    <h2 id="google-map">Google Maps</h2>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WGoogleMap} widget displays a google map. It implements a
      Wt wrapper around the Google Maps functionality.
    </p>
    <p>
      This widget uses the online Google Maps server to display a map. It
      exposes a part of the google maps API; both version 2 and version 3 are
      supported. The version 2 API is used by default, to enable the version 3
      API, use the constructor's version argument.
    </p>
    <p>
      To use the map on a public server you will need to obtain a key. The
      widget will look for this key as the configuration property
      <tt>google_api_key</tt>. If this configuration property has not been
      set, it will use a key that is suitable for localhost.
    </p>
    <p>
      The ${doc-link WGoogleMap} widget displays a google map. It implements a
      Wt wrapper around the Google Maps functionality. The following example
      demonstrates multiple controls and shows a polyline representing a road
      description from the Emweb office to the old market of Leuven. We also
      added a marker to Koen's favourite bar!
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${GoogleMap}
      ${src GoogleMap}
      <p>
        Here is the corresponding XML template (with
        <tt>message id="media-GoogleMap-controls"</tt>) for the controls.
      </p>
      <fieldset class="src">
        <legend>source</legend>
        <pre>${GoogleMap-controls}</pre>
      </fieldset>
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#google-map">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="graphics-GoogleMap-controls">
    <table class="googlemaps-controls">
      <tr>
        <td>Zoom:</td>
        <td>
          ${zoom-in} ${zoom-out}
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Pan to:</td>
        <td>
          ${Brussels} ${Lisbon} ${Paris} ${emweb}
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Control menu type: </td>
        <td>
          ${control-menu-combo}
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td colspan="2">${dragging-cb}</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td colspan="2">${double-click-zoom-cb}</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td colspan="2">${scroll-wheel-zoom-cb}</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td colspan="2">${save-position} ${return-to-saved-position}</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </message>

  <message id="graphics-Painting3D">
    <h2 id="painting3D">3D Graphics</h2>
    <h3>WebGL</h3>
    <p>
      Wt uses WebGL to render 3D graphics in the browser. The class ${doc-link WGLWidget} provides an interface for a 3D widget. Most of the functions provided by this class are a simple one-to-one map of the WebGL functions available in the browser.
    </p>
    <p>
      The rendering process consists of four major parts, which should be implemented by overriding four virtual functions:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li><tt>initializeGL()</tt>: This function is executed only once, when the widget is created.</li>
      <li><tt>resizeGL()</tt>: This function is called whenever the widget is resized</li>
      <li><tt>updateGL()</tt>: This function allows you to make state changes (e.g. to VBO's, shaders ...).</li>
      <li><tt>paintGL()</tt>: This function contains all necessary calls to do the actual painting. The effect of <tt>paintGL()</tt> is recorded on the server, but the generated JavaScript is repeatedly executed on the client without requiring client/server requests. This is for example used to rerender a scene client-side after changing the camera position</li>
    </ul>

    <h3>Server-side Fallback</h3>
    <p>
      When a browser does not support WebGL (e.g. IE10 or less, mobile browsers ...), ${doc-link WGLWidget} provides a server-side fall-back. The image will then be rendered in the server an sent to the browser as an PNG. Interaction is still possible, but the performance will be determined by the network latency. Also note that for practical scenarios this requires a server with hardware 3D acceleration.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="graphics-NumCharts3D">
    <h2>3D Numerical Chart</h2>
    <h3>The chart</h3>
    <p>
      The 3D charting API is built on top of Wt's 3D painting API. A chart is represented by a ${doc-link Chart-WCartesian3DChart}, which derives from ${doc-link WGLWidget}.
    </p>
    <p>
      Based on the sort of data that will be shown, a chart is one of two types (the same as for 2D charts):
      <ul>
        <li>a <strong>CategoryChart</strong> for categorized data</li>
        <li>a <strong>ScatterPlot</strong> for numerical data</li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <h3>Types of data</h3>
    <p>
      All data that can be shown in a 3D chart, has to derive from ${doc-link Chart-WAbstractDataSeries3D}. Instances of this class include a model containing the actual data and all logic to draw themselves on the chart. This means all graphical features of the data (color, pointsize ...) are also part of this class.
    </p>
    <p>
      Wt provides three built-in classes representing data:
      <ul>
        <li><strong>WGridData</strong>: data lying on a grid specified by an x- and y-axis</li>
        <li><strong>WEquidistantGridData</strong>: data lying on a grid with an equidistant x- and y-axis</li>
        <li><strong>WScatterData</strong>: data containing a collection of unconstrained points</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      Each instance of these dataseries has a ${doc-link WAbstractItemModel} backing them. The model for all these dataseries has to be provided as a table. <br />
      In ${doc-link Chart-WGridData}, the table must contain one column representing the x-axis values and one row representing the y-axis values. All other values then specify the z-axis value belonging to the corresponding (x, y) pair. <br />
      The backing model for ${doc-link Chart-WEquidistantGridData} is similar, with the difference that no x- and y-axis values are required. These can be specified directly to the class instance using <tt>setXAbscis(double XMinimum, double deltaX)</tt> and <tt>setYAbscis(double YMinimum, double deltaY)</tt>. <br />
      The model for ${doc-link Chart-WScatterData} must have three columns containing (x, y, z) values for every point.
    </p>
    <p>
      All grid-based data has the additional feature that the visualization of the data is determined by its <tt>Series3DType</tt>, which can be either of three values:
      <ul>
        <li>PointSeries3D</li>
        <li>SurfaceSeries3D</li>
        <li>BarSeries3D</li>
      </ul>
      Note that PointSeries3D and SurfaceSeries3D only apply to a chart of type ScatterPlot and BarSeries3D only applies to a CategoryChart.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      ${NumericalCharts3D}
      ${src NumericalCharts3D}
    </fieldset>
  </message>

  <message id="graphics-CatCharts3D">
    <h2>3D Category Chart</h2>
    <p>
      General info on how to use the 3D Charting API can be found under '3D numerical chart'.
    </p>
    <h3>The data</h3>
    <p>
      A categorical representation is only possible for grid-based data. In terms of the API this means any class deriving ${doc-link WAbstractGridData}. Wt already provides two implementations: ${doc-link WGridData} and ${doc-link WEquidistantGridData}. To create a categorical chart, the chart must be configured as such (by setting the type to <tt>CategoryChart</tt>) and the data which is added to this chart must be of the type <tt>BarSeries3D</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      A categorical chart also allows multiple dataseries to be shown if the dimensions are the same. The different bar-series are then stacked on top of each other.
    </p>
    <fieldset class="example">
      ${CategoryCharts3D}
      ${src CategoryCharts3D}
    </fieldset>
  </message>

  <message id="dataconfig.x-axisMin">Minimum X:</message>
  <message id="dataconfig.x-axisMax">Maximum X:</message>
  <message id="dataconfig.y-axisMin">Minimum Y:</message>
  <message id="dataconfig.y-axisMax">Maximum Y:</message>
  <message id="dataconfig.nbXPoints">Datapoints in X-axis:</message>
  <message id="dataconfig.nbYPoints">Datapoints in Y-axis:</message>
  <message id="dataconfig.meshEnabled">Enable mesh:</message>
  <message id="dataconfig.hiddenEnabled">Hide data:</message>
  <message id="dataconfig.typeSelection">Chart type:</message>

  <message id="bs-controlgroup">
    <div class="form-group">
      <label class="control-label" for="${id:{1}}">${tr:dataconfig.{1}}</label>
      <div class="controls">
        ${{1}}
      </div>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="chartconfig-template">
    <table class="table table-bordered">
      <tr><td>X-axis range (${xAuto} auto):</td><td>${xAxisMin}</td><td>${xAxisMax}</td></tr>
      <tr><td>Y-axis range (${yAuto} auto):</td><td>${yAxisMin}</td><td>${yAxisMax}</td></tr>
      <tr><td>Z-axis range (${zAuto} auto):</td><td>${zAxisMin}</td><td>${zAxisMax}</td></tr>
    </table>
  </message>

  <message id="dataconfig-template">
    <table class="table table-bordered">
      <tr><td>X range min/max</td><td>${x-axisMin}</td><td>${x-axisMax}</td></tr>
      <tr><td>Y range min/max</td><td>${y-axisMin}</td><td>${y-axisMax}</td></tr>
      <tr><td>number of points X/Y</td><td>
      <div class="form-group"><div class="controls">${nbXPoints}</div></div>
      </td><td>
      <div class="form-group"><div class="controls">${nbYPoints}</div></div>
      </td></tr>
      <tr><td>pointsize</td><td>${pointSize}</td><td></td></tr>
    </table>
    <form class="form-horizontal">
      ${block:bs-controlgroup typeSelection}
      ${block:bs-controlgroup meshEnabled}
      ${block:bs-controlgroup hiddenEnabled}
    </form>
  </message>

  <message id="scatterdata-config">
    <table class="table">
      <tr><td>Scatterdata:</td></tr>
      <tr><td>pointsize</td><td>${pointSize}</td></tr>
      <tr><td>Enable droplines</td><td>${enableDroplines}</td></tr>
      <tr><td>Hide data</td><td>${hide}</td></tr>
    </table>
  </message>

  <message id="categorydata-config">
    <table class="table">
      <tr><td>Categoric dataset 1:</td></tr>
      <tr><td>Bar width X/Y</td><td>${barWidthX}</td><td>${barWidthY}</td></tr>
      <tr><td>Hide data</td><td>${hide}</td></tr>
    </table>
  </message>

<!--EVENTS message blocks-->

  <message id="events-intro">
    <p class="lead">Events &#8212; making your application dynamic with the signal/slot concept</p>
  </message>

  <message id="events-Introduction">
    <h2 id="events">Introduction</h2>
    <h3></h3>
    <p>

    </p>

    <h3></h3>
    <p>

    </p>

    <p><a href="#events">Top</a></p>

  </message>


<!--MEDIA message blocks-->

  <message id="specialpurposewidgets-intro">
    <p class="lead">Media &#8212; video, audio, PDF and other resources</p>
  </message>

  <message id="media-MediaPlayer">
    <h2 id="media-player">Media Player</h2>
    <p>
      This widget implements a media player with a customizable user-interface,
      suitable to play video or audio.
    </p>
    <p>
      This widget relies on a third-party JavaScript component
      <a href="http://www.jplayer.org" target="blank">jPlayer</a>, which is
      distributed together with Wt.
    </p>
    <p>
      To support cross-browser playing of video or audio content, you may need
      to provide appropriately encoded contents. For audio, at least an MP3 or
      MP4 audio (M4A) encoding should be supplied, while for video the M4V
      encoding should be provided. Additional encodings are beneficial since
      they increase the chance that native HTML <tt>&lt;video&gt;</tt> or
      <tt>&lt;audio</tt>&gt; elements can be used (which may be hardware
      accelerated), instead of the flash player. See <a href=
      "http://www.jplayer.org/latest/developer-guide/#reference-html5-media"
      target="blank">HTML5 browser media support</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      You need to specify the encoding types you are going to use when
      instantiating the media player, since based on the chosen encodings, a
      particular suitable implementation will be used. Thus, you need to call
      <tt>addSource()</tt> immediately, but you may pass empty URLs if you do
      not yet want to load media.
    </p>
    <p>
      The player provides a user-interface to control the playback which may be
      freely customized, and which is independent of the underlying media
      technology (HTML video or Flash player). The controls user-interface may
      be implemented as a Wt widget, where the controls (buttons, progress bars,
      and text widgets) are bound directly to the video player component
      (client-side).
    </p>
    <p>
      The default user-interface can be themed using jPlayer themes. The theme
      is global (it applies to all media player instances), and is configured
      by loading a CSS stylesheet, e.g. <tt>Wt::WApplication::instance()->
      useStyleSheet(WApplication::resourcesUrl() +
      "jPlayer/skin/jplayer.blue.monday.css"</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      The following examples show a video and audio player using the default
      controls.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${MediaPlayerVideo}
      ${src MediaPlayerVideo}
    </fieldset>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${MediaPlayerAudio}
      ${src MediaPlayerAudio}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      Alternatively, a custom widget may be set which implements the controls,
      using <tt>setControlsWidget()</tt>. In this case, you should add to this
      widget the buttons, text place holders, and progress bars and bind them
      to the media player using the <tt>setButton()</tt>, <tt>setText()</tt>
      and <tt>setProgressBar()</tt> methods. The controls widget is integrated
      in the media player, and this has as unique benefit (for a video player)
      that they may also be shown when the video player is maximized.
    </p>
    <p>
      Finally, you may want to control the media player only through widgets
      external to the media player. This may be configured by setting 0 as
      controlsWidget. In this case however, full screen mode should not be used
      since there is no way to restore the original size.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#media-player">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="media-Sound">
    <h2>Sound</h2>
    <p>
      ${doc-link WSound} is a value class to play a sound effect. It provides a
      way to play an MP3 sound asynchonously (if the browser supports this). It
      is intended as a simple way to play event sounds (not quite a media
      center).
    </p>
    <p>
      The <tt>WSound</tt> class uses a
      <a href="#/media/wmediaplayer">WMediaPlayer</a> to play the sound (using
      HTML <tt>&lt;audio&gt;</tt> or a flash player).
    </p>

    <p>
      The following example creates a beep sound that will be repeated 3 times.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Sound}
      ${src Sound}
    </fieldset>

  </message>

  <message id="media-Audio">
    <h2 id="audio">Audio</h2>
    <p>
      ${doc-link WAudio} is a widget to play audio. It is a low-level widget,
      mapping directly onto a <tt>&lt;audio&gt;</tt> element available in HTML5
      compliant browsers.
    </p>
    <p>
      In almost every situation you should use
      <ul>
        <li>
          the <a href="#/media/wmediaplayer">WMediaPlayer</a> widget if you
          want the user to be able to interact with the audio, or
        </li>
        <li>
          the <a href="#/media/wsound">WSound</a> widget for simple sound
          feedback.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      Usage of the audio element consists of adding one or more audio sources
      and setting some options.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Audio}
      ${src Audio}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      Use the method <tt>setAlternativeContent()</tt> to show alternative
      content if the audio cannot be played. The alternative content can be any
      widget; you can set it to an alternative media player (QuickTime, Flash,
      ...), show a Flash movie, an animated gif, a text, a poster image, ... .
      There are two reasons why the a browser may use the alternative content:
      <ul>
        <li>
          either because the browser does not support the HTML5 audio tag
          (alternative content is displayed even when JavaScript is not
          available), or
      </li>
      <li>
        because none of the specified sources contain an audio format that is
        understood by the browser (requires JavaScript to display the
        alternative content).
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p>
      The <tt>addSource()</tt> and <tt>setAlternativeContent()</tt> may not be
      called after the widget is rendered.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#audio">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="media-Video">
    <h2 id="video">Video</h2>
    <p>
      Although the <a href="#/media/wmediaplayer">WMediaPlayer</a> widget
      implements a cross-browser video player, in some cases, you may need
      direct access to a native HTML <tt>&lt;video&gt;</tt> element. This is
      provided by the ${doc-link WVideo} widget.
    </p>
    <p>
      The trailer used in the examples below is
      <a href="http://durian.blender.org/" target="blank">Sintel</a>, &#169;
      copyright Blender Foundation | durian.blender.org
    </p>

    <h3>Native video</h3>
    <p>
      In the example below the <tt>WVideo</tt> class is used with a
      ${doc-link WImage} (a static JPEG image) as fallback. The video will play
      on browsers (like Firefox, Chrome and Safari) that support MP4 or OGV
      video streams natively (using HTML <tt>&lt;video&gt;</tt>), but the video
      control will show the image on other browsers (Internet Explorer, Opera,
      ...).
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Video}
      ${src Video}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#video">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Native video with fallback</h3>
    <p>
      For browsers that support HTML <tt>&lt;video&gt;</tt>, the video below
      looks exactly like the one above. On other browsers, the player below
      falls back to a Flash player to play the video. If flash is not supported
      on your system, a static image is shown.
    </p>
    <p>
      Any Flash-based video player can do the job. In the example below the FLV
      Player is used as fallback for HTML5 video.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${VideoFallback}
      ${src VideoFallback}
    </fieldset>

    <h3>Flash</h3>
    <p>
      You may also choose to simply rely on Flash to play the video. In the
      menu item <a href="#/media/wflashobject">WFlashObject</a> you can find an
      example.
    </p>

    <p><a href="#video">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="media-FlashObject">
    <h2>Flash object</h2>
    <p>
      Although a media player like
      <a href="#/media/wmediaplayer">WMediaPlayer</a> is usually used to play
      video, you may also choose a ${doc-link WFlashObject} to play video. In the
      example below the YouTube flash player is used. If flash is not supported
      on your system, a static image is shown.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${Flash}
      ${src Flash}
    </fieldset>

  </message>

  <message id="media-Resources">
    <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>
    <p>
      A ${doc-link WResource} is a target for a HTTP request. It specifies
      application-dependent content that may be generated by your
      application on demand. This allows you to serve auxiliary objects
      related to a particular application or application session, and perhaps
      dynamically generate the content. There are different type of resources
      which can serve a HTTP request:
      <ul>
        <li><strong>a file</strong>, using ${doc-link WFileResource},</li>
        <li>other <strong>streaming data</strong>, using ${doc-link WStreamResource},</li>
        <li><strong>a memory map</strong>, using ${doc-link WMemoryResource},</li>
        <li><strong>a web service</strong> (e.g. REST), by specializing
            ${doc-link WResource}</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      You can deploy a resource depending on the scope:
      <ul>
        <li>
          Deploy a <strong>private resource</strong> if access should be limited
          to a session (single user access).
        </li>
        <li>
          Deploy a <strong>global resource</strong> if access should always be
          possible (e.g. a web service).
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      By default, a resource is private to an application; access to it is
      protected by same secret session Id that protects any other access to the
      application.
    </p>
    <p>
      You can help the browser to start a suitable helper application to handle
      the downloaded resource, or suggest to the user a suitable filename for
      saving the resource, by setting an appropriate file name using
      <tt>suggestFileName()</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      To serve resources that you create on the fly, you need to specialize
      the <tt>WResource</tt> class and implement <tt>handleRequest()</tt>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Because of the nature of the web, a resource may be requested one time or
      multiple times at the discretion of the browser, and therefore your
      resource should in general not have any side-effects except for what is
      needed to render its own contents. Unlike event notifications to a Wt
      application, resource requests are not serialized, but are
      <strong>handled concurrently</strong>. You need to grab the application
      lock if you want to access or modify other widget state from within the
      resource.
    </p>
    ${<if:cpp>}
    <p>
      When deleting a resource, any pending request is cancelled
      first. For this mechanism to work you need to specialize the destructor
      and call <tt>beingDeleted()</tt>. This method may safely be called
      multiple times (i.e. from within each destructor in the hierachy).
    </p>
    ${</if:cpp>}

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ResourceCustom}
      ${src ResourceCustom}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#resources">Top</a></p>

    <h3>Static resources</h3>
    <p>
      Static resources are global which means that they are available as long
      as the application is running. A web service (e.g. REST, SOAP, WSDL) is a
      typical example of a resource that should always be available. This could
      be needed for machine-to-machine communication, etc.
    </p>
    <p>
      Use <tt>WServer::addResource()</tt> to deploy static resources.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${ResourceStatic}
      ${src ResourceStatic}
    </fieldset>

    <p>
      Classes such as <tt>WAnchor</tt> or <tt>WImage</tt> can use a resource
      instead of a URL to provide their contents. So, in any widget where you
      pass a WLink, you can refer to a resource. You can find several examples
      in the widget gallery:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="#/media/wmediaplayer">WMediaPlayer</a></li>
        <li><a href="#/media/wsound">WSound</a></li>
        <li><a href="#/media/wimage">WImage</a></li>
        <li><a href="#/media/wvideo">WVideo</a></li>
        <li><a href="#/media/pdf-output">WPdfImage</a></li>
        <li><a href="#/media/pdf-output">WPdfRenderer</a></li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p><a href="#resources">Top</a></p>

  </message>

  <message id="media-PDF">
    <h2 id="pdf">PDF output</h2>
    <p>
      Wt provides two classes for rendering to PDF:
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="#media/pdf-images">WPdfImage</a> is a paint device for
          rendering to PDF
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="#media/pdf-renderer">WPdfRenderer</a> to render XHTML to a
          multi-page PDF.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <h3 id="media/pdf-images">PDF Images</h3>
    <p>
      The class ${doc-link WPdfImage} is a paint device for rendering
      to PDF. It supports two main use-cases:
      <ul>
        <li>as any other paint device, it can be used to create a PDF
        output of the painting (which could e.g. be a chart or your
        own painted widget), or</li>
        <li>it can be used to embed Wt-generated contents into a larger PDF
        document, e.g. to generate a report</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      A <tt>WPdfImage</tt> paint device is typically used in
      conjunction with a ${doc-link WPainter}, which provides a
      high-level unified painting API.
    </p>
    ${<if:cpp>}
      <p>
        The PDF is generated using
        <a href="http://libharu.org/">The Haru Free PDF Library</a>. This class
        is included in the library only if <tt>libharu</tt> was found during the
        build of the library.
      </p>
    ${</if:cpp>}
    ${<if:java>}
      <p>
        The PDF is generated using the <a
        href="http://pdfjet.com">PDFjet library</a>, and Wt can use
        either the open source or commercial version.
      </p>
    ${</if:java>}

    <p>The following example shows how to use a <tt>WPdfImage</tt> directly in
    conjunction with <tt>WPainter</tt>.</p>
    
    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PdfImage}
      ${src PdfImage}
    </fieldset>

    ${<if:cpp>}
      <p>Another common use-case is to paint the contents of a
      <tt>WPaintedWidget</tt>, such as a chart, to a PDF :
      </p>

      <fieldset class="example">
        ${src pdfImageWrite}
      </fieldset>
    ${</if:cpp>}

    <p>
      When you want to embed a PDF image into a larger document, you
      need to use its constructor which passes an existing PDF
      document and page for it to paint on.  This approach is used for
      example by the <a href="#media/pdf-renderer">WPdfRenderer</a> to
      render XHTML to multi-page PDF files.
    </p>
    <p>
      Font information is embedded in the PDF. Fonts supported are native
      PostScript fonts (Base-14) (only ASCII-7), or true type fonts
      (Unicode). See <tt>addFontCollection()</tt> for more information on how
      fonts are located and matched to ${doc-link WFont} descriptions.
    </p>
    <p>
      The paint device has the following limitations:
      <ul>
        <li>
          Images (cf. <tt>WPainter::drawImage()</tt>) can only be included
          from local files, and only JPG or PNG images can be embedded.
        </li>
        <li>
          Drop shadows are not supported.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p><a href="#pdf">Top</a></p>

    <h3 id="media/pdf-renderer">Rendering HTML to PDF</h3>
    <p>
      The class ${doc-link Render-WPdfRenderer} implements a XHTML to
      PDF renderer. It can be used to create mult-page reports,
      without the need for programming tedious layouting using a
      low-level drawing API.
    </p>
    <p>
      The rendering engine supports only a subset of XHTML. See the
      documentation of ${doc-link Render-WTextRenderer} for more information.
    </p>
    <p>
      Although the rendering class itself can render to any
      <tt>WPaintDevice</tt> (with font-metris), by far the most common
      use-case is to render to a PDF document using
      <tt>WPdfImage</tt>. Typically, you will want to adapt the pixel
      resolution By default it uses a pixel resolution of 72 DPI,
      which is a common default for printed documents, but differs
      from the default used by most browsers (which is 96 DPI and has
      nothing to do with the actual screen resolution). The resolution
      can be changed using <tt>setDpi()</tt> and has the effect of
      scaling down (or up) the rendering. This can be used in
      conjunction with <tt>setFontScale()</tt> to scale the font size
      differently than other content.
    </p>

    <fieldset class="example">
      <legend>Example</legend>
      ${PdfRenderer}
      ${src PdfRenderer}
    </fieldset>

    <p><a href="#pdf">Top</a></p>
  </message>
</messages>
