<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<messages>
  <message id="Wt.Auth.login-form-info">
    Hangman keeps track of the best players, and since that could be
    you, you might want to register. <br/>
    If you would rather not register for some reason, use the
    <b>guest/guest</b> account.
  </message>

  <message id="highscore.info">
    <p>
      For each game won, you gain 20 points, minus one point for each
      wrong letter guess. <br />

      For each game lost, you loose 10 points, so you better try hard
      to guess the word!
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="hangman.readyToPlay">
    <h2>Ready to play ?</h2>
  </message>

  <message id="hangman.dutchWords">
    Dutch words ({1} words)
  </message>

  <message id="hangman.englishWords">
    English words ({1} words)
  </message>

  <message id="hangman.newGame">New game</message>

  <message id="hangman.guessTheWord">
    <h2>Guess the word, {1}!</h2>
  </message>

  <message id="hangman.youHang">
    You hang... <br />The correct answer was: {1}
  </message>

  <message id="hangman.youWin">
    You win!
  </message>

  <!-- Emails -->

  <message id="Wt.Auth.confirmmail.subject">Email confirmation</message>

  <message id="Wt.Auth.confirmmail.body">
Hello {1},

Thank you for joining the Wt hangman example!

Please click here to confirm your registration or copy and paste the
following URL into your browser: (Note: be sure to copy the entire
URL, including any part of it which goes onto a second line.)

{3}

Good luck in the game!

The Wt team.
  </message>

  <message id="Wt.Auth.confirmmail.htmlbody">
    <h3>Hello {1},</h3>

    <p>Thank you for joining the Wt hangman example!</p>

    <p>Please <a href="{3}">click here to confirm</a> your
    registration or copy and paste the following URL into your
    browser: <i>(Note: be sure to copy the entire URL, including any
    part of it which goes onto a second line.)</i></p>
    
    <b>{3}</b>

    <p>Good luck in the game!</p>

    <p>The Wt team.</p>
  </message>

  <message id="Wt.Auth.lostpasswordmail.subject">Lost password instructions</message>

  <message id="Wt.Auth.lostpasswordmail.body">
Hello {1},

This mail has been sent to you, because someone (presumably you?)
indicated that he wishes to choose a new password, because the current
password escapes his mind.

If you requested this, then choose a new password by clicking on the
following link or copying the URL into your browser. If you didn't
request this, you can safely ignore and discard this email.
 
Please copy and paste the following URL into your browser: (Note: be
sure to copy the entire URL, including any part of it which goes onto
a second line.)
 
{3} 

Your truly,

The Wt team.
  </message>

  <message id="Wt.Auth.lostpasswordmail.htmlbody">
    <h3>Hello {1},</h3>

    <p>This mail has been sent to you, because someone (presumably
    you?) indicated that he wishes to choose a new password, because
    the current password escapes his mind.</p>

    <p>If you requested this, then choose a new password by clicking
    on the following link or copying the URL into your browser. If you
    didn't request this, you can safely ignore and discard this
    email.</p>
 
    <p>Please <a href="{3}">click here to choose a new password</a> or
    copy and paste the following URL into your browser: <i>(Note: be
    sure to copy the entire URL, including any part of it which goes
    onto a second line.)</i></p>
    
    <b>{3}</b>

    <p>Yours truly,</p>

    <p>The Wt team.</p>
  </message>

</messages>
