<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<messages>
  <message id="treeview-introduction">
    <h2>WTreeView example</h2>

    <p>This example illustrates the WTreeView widget. This widget is
    part of Wt's MVC widgets, and are an alternative to the WTree, and
    WTreeTable widgets which are not MVC.</p>

    <p>The widget supports very large models by loading only the
    visible region (with some margin) in the browser. This results in
    low memory consumption (on client and server) and fast load
    times.</p>

    <p>This example uses a WStandardItemModel to populate the tree
    table. As is demonstrated, various roles may be used to indicate
    text, icons, selectable items (through check boxes), and also URLs
    or internal paths.</p>

    <p>Many aspects of the tree view widget are not illustrated here,
    such as the various supported selection behaviors and modes, and
    reacting to item click events.</p>
  </message>

  <message id="drink-Beer">
    <h3>Drink: beer</h3>

    <p>
      Belgium is famous for its rich beer culture. <br />

      Belgians (like most other Europeans), will tell you that they
      have the largest variety of best beers in the world.
    </p>

    <p>
      Read about it on wikipedia: <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beer">Beer</a>.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="drink-Wine">
    <h3>Drink: wine</h3>

    <p>
      Not only because of their renowned chauvinism are French people
      so proud of their wine: they have plenty of good wines to brag
      about. <br />
    </p>

    <p>
      Read about it on wikipedia: <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wine">Wine</a>.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="drink-Bordeaux wine">
    <h3>Drink: wine (Bordeaux)</h3>

    <p>
      Bordeaux is a wine region in France.
    </p>

    <p>
      Read about it on wikipedia: <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bordeaux_wine">Bordeaux wine</a>.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="drink-Cava">
    <h3>Drink: cava</h3>

    <p>
      The French do not allow the Spanish to call Cava Champagne, but
      that is what it is.
    </p>

    <p>
      Read about it on wikipedia: <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cava">Cava</a>.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="drink-San Miguel">
    <h3>Drink: San Miguel</h3>

    <p>
      A Spanish beer.
    </p>

    <p>
      Read about it on wikipedia: <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahou_Brewery">San Miguel</a>.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="drink-Juice">
    <h3>Drink: fruit juice</h3>

    <p>
      It's got vitamins all over it and entirely healthy.
    </p>

    <p>
      Read about it on wikipedia: <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juice">Juice</a>.
    </p>
  </message>

  <message id="drink-Tea">
    <h3>Drink: tea</h3>

    <p>
      C'est la boisson du jour.
    </p>

    <p>
      Read about it on wikipedia: <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tea">Tea</a>.
    </p>
  </message>
</messages>
