<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<messages>
  <message id="template">
    <div id="top_wrapper">
      <div id="top_content">
	${languages}
	<div id="top_wt">
	  <a href="//www.emweb.be/">
	    <img src="/css/wt/emweb_powered.jpg" alt="Emweb" height="22" />
	  </a>
	</div>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div id="banner_wrapper">
      <div id="banner_content">
	<div id="banner_end">
	  <div id="banner">
	    <!-- <a href="#">Wt</a> -->
	  </div>
	</div>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div id="main_wrapper" class="home">
      <div id="main_content">
	<div id="main_menu">
	  ${menu}
	  ${sidebar}
	</div>
	${contents}

	<div class="clearall"></div>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div id="footer_wrapper">
      <div id="footer_content">
	<div id="footer_copyright"> 
	  <a href="//www.emweb.be/">
	    <img src="/css/wt/emweb_large.jpg" height="25" width="101"
		 alt="Emweb.be" title="emweb.be"/></a>
	  Solutions for web-based systems<br/>
	  <a href="//www.emweb.be/">www.emweb.be</a>
	</div>

	<div id="footer_menu"> 
	  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt">Home</a>
	  | <a href="//www.emweb.be/contact">Contact</a>

	</div>

	<div id="chat"></div>
	<script type="text/javascript">
	    /*<![CDATA[*/
	  setTimeout(function() {
	    loadScript("//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/examples/simplechat/chat.js?div=chat", null);
	  }, 0);
            /* ]]> */
	</script>

	<div class="clearall"></div>
      </div>
      <script type="text/javascript">
	    /*<![CDATA[*/
(function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i['GoogleAnalyticsObject']=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
(i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
})(window,document,'script','//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js','ga');

ga('create', 'UA-4345578-1', 'auto');
ga('send', 'pageview');
            /* ]]> */
      </script>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="wt">Wt, C++ Web Toolkit</message>

  <message id="introduction">Introduction</message>
  <message id="blog">Blog</message>
  <message id="features">Features</message>
  <message id="documentation">Documentation</message>
  <message id="examples">Examples</message>
  <message id="download">Download</message>
  <message id="community">Support</message>
  <message id="other-language">!C++</message>

  <message id="hello-world">Hello world</message>
  <message id="charts">Charts</message>
  <message id="wt-homepage">Wt homepage</message>
  <message id="treeview">Treeview</message>
  <message id="git">Git explorer</message>
  <message id="chat">Chat</message>
  <message id="mail-composer">Mail composer</message>
  <message id="hangman">Hangman</message>
  <message id="widget-gallery">Widget gallery</message>

  <message id="home.news">
    <h3><span>News</span></h3>
  </message>
  <message id="home.latest-news">
    <h4><span>Latest News</span></h4>
  </message>
  <message id="home.historical-news">
    <h4><span>Historical News</span></h4>
  </message>

  <message id="source-browser-link">
    <a href="{1}">Browse the source code</a>
  </message>

  <message id="src-title">
    <div>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.intro">

<h3><span>Wt: an introduction</span></h3>

<p>Wt (pronounced as <i>witty</i>) is a C++ library for developing
web applications.</p>

<p>The API is <b>widget-centric</b> and uses well-tested patterns of
desktop GUI development tailored to the web. To the developer, it
offers abstraction of many web-specific implementation details,
including client-server protocols (HTTP, Ajax, WebSockets), and frees
the developer from tedious JavaScript manipulations of HTML and
dealing with cross-browser issues. Instead, with Wt, you can focus on
actual functionality with a rich set of feature-complete widgets.</p>

<p>Unlike old-school page-based frameworks or current-day single-page
JavaScript "frameworks", Wt allows you to create stateful applications
that are at the same time highly interactive (using WebSockets and
Ajax for everything) but still support plain HTML browsers or web
crawlers using automatic <b>graceful degradation or progressive
enhancement</b>. Things that are natural and simple with Wt would
require an impractical amount of development effort otherwise:
switching widgets using animations, while retaining clean URLs and
browser navigation functions, or having a persistent chat widget open
throughout the entire application, that even works in legacy browsers
like Microsoft Internet Explorer 6.</p>

<p>The library comes with an application server that acts as a
stand-alone Http(s)/WebSocket server or integrates through FastCGI
with other web servers.</p>

<h4>Feature rich</h4>

<ul>
<li>Layout using <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/layout/html-templates">HTML
templates</a> or intelligent <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/layout/layout-managers">layout
managers</a> and themable look-and-feel, including support for <a
href="http://getbootstrap.com">Twitter Bootstrap</a> versions 2 or 3.</li>
<li>Create and maintain complexity by using and building reusable and
self-contained widgets.</li>
<li>Comes with a large set of feature-rich widgets that include <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/forms/">form
widgets</a>, <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/trees-tables/mvc-table-views">table</a> and <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/trees-tables/mvc-tree-views">tree
views</a>, <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/layout/dialogs">dialogs</a>, <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/navigation/popup-menu">popup
menu's</a>, etc...</li>
<li>Unified <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/graphics-charts">graphics</a>
APIs, 2D (SVG, HTML5 Canvas, VML, PNG, and PDF) &amp; 3D (client side
WebGL and server-side OpenGL).</li>
<li>Feature rich <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets/media/pdf-output">HTML
to PDF renderer</a> for dynamic report generation.</li>
<li>Elegant template-based C++ Database abstraction layer (Wt::Dbo)</li>
<li>Built-in security against common vulnerabiliets such as <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross-site_scripting">XSS(Cross-Site-Scripting)</a> or <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross-site_request_forgery">CSRF
(Cross-Site Request Forgery)</a></li>
</ul>

<h4>Typical use scenarios:</h4>

<ul>
  <li><b>High performance, complex</b> web applications which are
  fully personalized (and thus cannot benefit from caching), fully
  Ajax enabled and at the same time entirely accessible and Search
  Engine Optimized.</li>
  <li>Web-based GUIs for <b>embedded systems</b> benefit from the low
  footprint of a C++ web application server.</li>
  <li>Web-based GUIs that require <b>integration with (existing) C++
  libraries</b>, for example for scientific or engineering
  applications, or <b>existing C++ desktop applications</b>.</li>
</ul>
  </message>
  <message id="home.features">

<h3><span>Features</span></h3>

<h4>Core library</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Supports major browsers (Firefox/Gecko, Internet Explorer,
    Safari, Chrome, Konqueror, and Opera) but also plain HTML
    browsers and web crawlers.</li>
  <li>Develop and deploy on Unix/GNU Linux or Microsoft Windows
    (Visual Studio) environments.</li>
  <li>Equal behavior with or without support for JavaScript or Ajax,
    as far as possible, by using graceful degradation or progressive
    enhancement.</li>
  <li>Efficient rendering and (sub-) millisecond latency.</li>
  <li>Integrated Unicode support and pervasive localization.</li>
  <li>Support for browser history navigation (back/forward buttons and
    bookmarks), clean URLs with HTML5 History if available, and
    search engine optimization with a unified behavior for plain HTML
    or Ajax sessions.</li>
  <li>High performance, suitable for embedded (Linux) devices, or
    energy-, space- and budget-friendly (virtual private) server
    deployments.</li>
  <li>Based on event-driven async I/O: sessions are not
    tied to threads, and neither do open connections block threads.
    Instead, threads are used only to improve concurrent request
    handling (or for reentrant event loops).</li>
</ul>

<h4>Event handling</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Typesafe signal/slot API for responding to events.</li>
  <li>Listen for keyboard, mouse, focus, scroll or drag&amp;drop events,
    and get event details (such as mouse position, modifier buttons, or
    keyboard key).</li>
  <li>Automatic synchronization Automatically synchronizes form field data
    from browser to server and tracks server-side changes to be rendered
    in browser.</li>
  <li>Integrate with JavaScript libraries</li>
  <li>Timed events and server-initiated updates ("server push")</li>
  <li>Uses plain HTML CGI, Ajax or WebSockets</li>
</ul>

<h4>Native painting system</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Unified 2D painting API which uses the browsers native (vector)
    graphics support (inline VML, inline SVG, or HTML5 canvas), or
    renders to common image formats (PNG, GIF, ...) or vector formats
    (SVG, PDF).</li>
  <li>Unified GL-based 3D painting API which leverages WebGL in the browser
    or server-side OpenGL (fallback).</li>
</ul>

<h4>Built-in security</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Kernel-level memory protection protects against privacy issues
    arising from programming bugs, since sessions can be completely
    isolated from each other (in dedicated-process mode).</li>
  <li>Supports encryption and server authentication using Secure Sockets
    Layer (SSL) or Transport Layer Security (TLS) through HTTPS.</li>
  <li>Enables continuous use of HTTPS through low bandwidth
    requirements (fine-grained Ajax).</li>
  <li>Built-in Cross-Site Scripting (XSS) prevention. Rendered text is
    always filtered against potentially malicious code, making XSS
    attacks against Wt applications (close to) impossible.</li>
  <li>Not vulnerable to Cross-site Request Forgery (CSRF) because
    cookies for session tracking are optional, and even when used, they
    are never solely relied on for requests that trigger event handling
    code.</li>
  <li>Not vulnerable to breaking the application logic by skipping to
    a particular URL, since only those events exposed in the interface
    can be triggered.</li>
  <li>Session hijacking mitigation and risk prevention</li>
  <li>DoS mitigation</li>
  <li>A built-in authentication module implements best practices for
    authentication, and supports third party identity providers using
    OAuth 2.0, and (later) OpenID Connect</li>
</ul>

<h4>Object Relational Mapping library</h4>

Wt comes with Wt::Dbo, a self-contained library which implements
Object-Relational mapping, and thus a convenient way to interact with
SQL databases from C++. Although features like optimistic concurrency
control make this an ideal technology for a database driven web
application (and it provides good integration with Wt's MVC classes),
the library can also be used for other applications, and does not
depend on Wt.

The ORM library (see also <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/tutorial/dbo/tutorial.html">this
tutorial</a>) has the following features:

<ul>
  <li>No code generation, no macro hacks, no XML configuration, just
    modern C++!</li>
  <li>Uses a templated visitor pattern which requires a single
    template method to provide the mapping: DRY and as efficient as
    conceivable!</li>
  <li>You can indicate surrogate auto-incremental keys or map natural
    keys of any C++ type, which may also be composite (i.e. require more
    than one database field).</li>
  <li>Supports <a
    href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimistic_concurrency_control">
    optimistic concurrency control</a> using a version field.</li>
  <li>Maps Many-to-One and Many-to-Many relations to STL-compatible
    collections.</li>
  <li>Provides schema generation (aka DDL: data definition language)
    and CRUD operations (aka DML: data manipulation language).</li>
  <li>Prepared statements throughout.</li>
  <li>Each session tracks dirty objects and provides a first-level cache.</li>
  <li>Flexible querying which can query individual fields, objects, or
    tuples of any these (using Boost.Tuple).</li>
  <li>Use a single connection or share connection pools between
    multiple sessions from which connections are used only during an
    active transaction.</li>
  <li>Comes with Sqlite3, Firebird, MariaDB/MySQL and PostgreSQL
    backends, and an Oracle backend is also available on request.</li>
</ul>

<h4>Testing</h4>

With Wt, event handling code constructs and manipulates a widget tree,
which can easily be inspected by test code. Therefore, a <a href="
//webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1Test_1_1WTestEnvironment.html">test
environment</a> allows your application to be instantiated and events
to be simulated in absence of a browser, short-cutting the underlying
request/response cycle that would otherwise require a simulated browser.

<h4>Deployment</h4>

<p>
The library abstracts different deployment options as connectors
libraries, which connect Wt with the outer world. Switching deployment
option is a matter of (re)linking to one of these connector libraries!
</p>

<h5>a) Built-in httpd</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Simple, high-performance web application server (multi-threaded,
    asynchronous I/O) based on the C++ asio library.</li>
  <li>Supports the HTTP(S) and WebSocket(S) protocols.</li>
  <li>Supports response chunking and compression.</li>
  <li>Single process (convenient for development and debugging), and
    embeddable in an existing application.</li>
  <li>Supports deployment behind a ProxyPass'ing (and if needed,
    load-balancing) web server.</li>
  <li>Available for both UNIX and Win32 platforms.</li>
</ul>

<h5>b) FastCGI</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Integrates with most common web servers (apache, lighttpd).</li>
  <li>Different session-to-process mapping strategies.</li>
  <li>Hot deployment: new sessions use the new application version while 
    older sessions may continue with their application version.</li>
  <li>Available only for UNIX platforms.</li>
</ul>

<h5>c) ISAPI</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Integrates with Microsoft IIS server.</li>
  <li>Uses the ISAPI asynchronous API for maximum performance.</li>
  <li>Available for the Win32 platform.</li>
</ul>

  </message>
  <message id="home.examples">

<h3><span>Examples</span></h3>

<p>Explore some live examples of Wt below.</p>

<p>
  The source code of these (and many more) examples is included in the
  Wt source distribution. You may also browse through the source code
  of each example using the <a href="#/src">source code viewer</a>,
  following the link below each example.
</p>

<p>
  Cross-linked source code for these examples is also in
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/examples/html/modules.html" target="_blank">
  doxygen documentation (in a new window)</a>.
</p>

  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.hello">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Hello world!</h4>

<p>
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/examples/hello/hello.wt" class="run" target="_blank">
    <img src="/icons/green-play.png" style="vertical-align: top"/> Run example
  </a>
</p>

<p>This simple example illustrates most of the basic Wt concepts:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    How to make a minimal Wt application, using <b>WRun()</b> to start
    the web server, and a function to create a new <a
    href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WApplication.html"
    target="_blank">WApplication</a>, corresponding to a new session.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Creating widgets</b>, and adding them to <b>the widget tree</b>.
  </li>
  <li>
    Reacting to events using the <b>signal/slot</b> mechanism.
  </li>
  <li>
    Reading user input and updating widgets.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>For a thorough (although slightly out-dated) explanation of the
hello world example, see also the <a
href="http://www.codeguru.com/cpp/i-n/internet/browsercontrol/article.php/c15275/"
target="_blank">nice introduction to Wt</a> written by Victor Venkman.</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.wt">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Wt homepage</h4>
<p>We eat our own dog food: this website itself is a Wt example. </p>

<p>
  Not really the interactive application Wt was designed for, the
  homepage illustrates how Wt also makes excellent content-driven
  websites. To that extent, Wt supports pretty URLs all the same for
  both Ajax and plain HTML sessions (leveraging HTML5 History support
  if possible), useful for browser history navigation,
  bookmarks, and search engine optimization.
</p>

<p>
  Navigation is provided by a <a
  href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WMenu.html"
  target="_blank">WMenu</a> and <a
  href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTabWidget.html"
  target="_blank">WTabWidget</a>. These widgets share the same feature
  set. For Ajax sessions, they support <b>pre-loading</b> and <b>lazy
  loading</b> of the contents associated with each item. Pre-loaded
  contents does not increase the load time because the Wt rendering
  engine always optimizes the response time by only transmitting
  visual widgets or changes first. Everything invisible (such as the
  contents for other pre-loaded menu items) is transmitted in the
  background, after rendering the visible contents.
</p>

<p>
  Menu navigation is implemented using C++ stateless slots, and
  therefore results in <b>client-side</b> event handling
  code. Optionally, CSS3 animations can be used to animate the
  transition of contents managed by a <a
  href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WStackedWidget.html"
  target="_blank">WStackedWidget</a>.
</p>

<p>
  URLs are associated with each menu/tab entry, and in this way
  participate in browser navigation history and bookmarking. When the
  user browses through the history, the menu reacts
  to <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WApplication.html#a674fd6a2522d66d07908e8f3d82424a9"
  target="_blank">navigation events</a>. Similarly, when a user
  bookmarks a URL to revisit it later, or follows an external link to
  your application, the menu reacts to the initial internal
  path. All-together this generates a decentralized "routing
  framework" for pretty URLs that works equally well for Ajax as plain
  HTML sessions.
</p>

<p>
  The chat widget sitting at the bottom is actually part of the <a
  href="#/examples/chat">chat example</a>.
</p>

</div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.examples.treeview">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Treeview</h4>

<p>
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/examples/treeview-dragdrop/treeview-dragdrop.wt" class="run" target="_blank">
    <img src="/icons/green-play.png" style="vertical-align: top"/>  Run example
  </a>
</p>

This example illustrates some MVC functionality provided by builtin
Views (WTreeView, WTableView and PieChart) and models.

<ul>
  <li>
    The example uses <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTreeView.html"
    target="_blank">WTreeView</a>
    and <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTableView.html"
    target="_blank">WTableView</a> widgets for rendering a Model's
    data in a tree or a table.
  </li>
  <li>
    A <a
    href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WSortFilterProxyModel.html"
    target="_blank">WSortFilterProxyModel</a>
    implement sorting and filtering for another model.
  </li>
  <li>
    These item views have support for drag and drop of a selection of items.
  </li>
  <li>
    You can use nested layout managers (horizontal and
    vertical
    <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WBoxLayout.html" target="_blank">
      WBoxLayout</a>)
    for an automatic window-filling layout, with optional resize handles.
  </li>
  <li>
    Modal (and non-modal) <a
    href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WDialog.html"
    target="_blank">dialogs</a> can be used to prompt for input.
  </li>
  <li>
    You may show a context-sensitive
    <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WPopupMenu.html" target="_blank">
      WPopupMenu</a>.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.examples.chart">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Charts example</h4>

<p>
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/examples/charts/charts.wt" class="run" target="_blank">
    <img src="/icons/green-play.png" style="vertical-align: top"/>  Run example
  </a>
</p>

<p>This example demonstrates the <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/group__charts.html" target="_blank">Wt
charting widgets</a> that are implemented on top of Wt's cross-browser
painting API. This painting API uses built-in browser support for
generating high quality graphics. Depending on the browser,
inline VML, inline SVG, HTML5 canvas, or a PNG image is used to
render painted contents in a <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WPaintedWidget.html"
target="_blank">WPaintedWidget</a>.
</p>

<p>This example also demonstrates how a Model can be shared by several
Views, and pass modification events to each connected View. The <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTableView.html"
target="_blank">table view</a> and the chart implement a <i>View</i>
on the same <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WAbstractItemModel.html"
target="_blank">item model</a>.</p>
</div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.examples.git">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Git explorer</h4>

<p>
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/examples/gitmodel/gitview.wt" class="run" target="_blank">
    <img src="/icons/green-play.png" style="vertical-align: top"/>  Run example
  </a>
</p>

<p>
  This example serves as a demo for a custom model implementation which can
  be used by Wt's item View classes, such as
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTreeView.html" target="_blank">
    WTreeView</a>.
</p>
<p>
  A <a
  href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WStandardItemModel.html"
  target="_blank">WStandardItemModel</a> can be populated with data
  retrieved from for example a database. A draw-back is however that
  all data must be retrieved in advance and is kept in session
  memory. By reimplementing <a
  href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WAbstractItemModel.html"
  target="_blank">WAbstractItemModel</a>, you can however implement a
  model that reads (or computes) the data only when needed, and
  provides a trade-off between keeping data in memory or fetching it
  from the source.</p>

  <p>In this example, we implement a tree model that navigates a <a
  href="http://git-scm.com/">git repository</a>. The model lazy-stores
  folder nodes in memory, but reads all other data directly from
  git. Initially we thought the SHA-1 id's could be used, but folders
  with the same content in different places of the git repository have
  the same SHA-1 ID's while representing different <a
  href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WModelIndex.html"
  target="_blank">model indexes</a>.
</p>
</div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.examples.composer">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Mail composer</h4>

<p>
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/examples/composer/composer.wt" class="run" target="_blank">
    <img src="/icons/green-play.png" style="vertical-align: top"/>  Run example
  </a>
</p>

<p>
  This example implements a GMail-like mail composer and shows among
  other things how to upload files asynchronously, showing a
  cross-browser upload progress bar and with support for multiple
  files.
</p>

  <ul>
    <li>
      The <i>ContactSuggestions</i> class provides auto-completion of
      the addressees in the To: Cc: and Bcc: fields. The widget
      derives from <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WSuggestionPopup.html"
	     target="_blank">WSuggestionPopup</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      The <i>AttachmentEdit</i> widget uses a <a
      href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WFileUpload.html"
      target="_blank">WFileUpload</a> to asynchronously
      upload files. The upload <a
      href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WProgressBar.html"
      target="_blank">progress bar</a> will work even in IE6.
    </li>
    <li>
      The <i>Option</i> and <i>OptionList</i> classes show how
      stateless slots, a trick to handle events client-side but
      implement them still in C++, may be used even when the behaviour
      is not entirely stateless. In this case, the hiding of an Option
      affects neighboring visible options: an option needs a separator
      only if there is a neighbouring option. By <b>invalidating the
      stateless slot implementations</b> when state has changed, we
      can still use a stateless slot implementation and enjoy
      client-side event handling performance!
    </li>
  </ul>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.chat">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Simple Chat</h4>

<p>
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/examples/simplechat/simplechat.wt" class="run" target="_blank">
    <img src="/icons/green-play.png" style="vertical-align: top"/>  Run example
  </a> (or ventilate your thoughts down here)
</p>

<p>
  This example implements a simple chat client and server. Using
  <b>server-initiated updates</b>, you can easily push events from one
  user to other users. Server-initiated updates are implemented using
  Ajax long polling or HTML5 WebSockets.
</p>

<p>
  It also illustrates nice benefits of a class-based approach to web
  application development: you can easily instantiate the same widget
  class multiple times. The SimpleChatClient widget may be reused just
  as you reuse basic Wt widgets such as a push button.
</p>

<p>
  The chat application is also available as a <i>Widget</i> which can
  be embedded in another page (very much like how you integrate a
  google maps widget inside another application). In this case, we've
  embedded the chat also in this very homepage as follows:
</p>
  <pre>    &lt;div id="chat"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;script src="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/examples/simplechat/chat.js?div=chat"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</pre>
<p>
  This uses Cross-Origin Ajax/WebSocket requests (if the browser
  supports this, falling back to old tricks if not) to communicate
  from a HTML origin page to a server hosting the Widget possibly from
  a different domain.
</p>

<p>
  Interactive applications like these, which allow users to post HTML
  text to other users, are notorious for <b>cross-site-scripting (XSS)
  attacks</b>: a user enters malicious (javascript) code as part of
  his message. When another user renders this message, it may transmit
  unwanted private information retrieved from, for example, browser
  cookies. Wt prevents such attacks completely, and without any
  responsibility to the developer, since widgets such as WText ensure
  that what is displayed is only passive text, discarding anything
  that is not strictly text.
</p>
</div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.examples.hangman">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Hangman</h4>

<p>
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/examples/hangman-game/hangman.wt" class="run" target="_blank">
    <img src="/icons/green-play.png" style="vertical-align: top"/> Run example
  </a>
</p>

<p>
  This example implements a simple well-known game, including a user
  ranking system, which is persisted to a database using Wt::Dbo.
</p>
<p>
  Some of the things illustrated in this example:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Different approaches to layout: using an <a
    href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTemplate.html"
    target="_blank">HTML template</a>, a <a
    href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WBoxLayout.html"
    target="_blank">layout manager</a>, or by compositing basic
    widgets and CSS.
  </li>

  <li>
    Using hidden content to optimize the user experience by preloading
    contents, used in this game to preload the various images used to
    show the hanging man.
  </li>

  <li>
    Navigation is implemented using <a
    href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WAnchor.html"
    target="_blank">WAnchor</a> which reference an internal path.
    Action is taken by reacting to internal path changes.
  </li>

  <li>
    The example uses <a
    href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/group__auth.html">the
    authentication module (Wt::Auth)</a> to authenticate users using a
    username/password, or using Google's beta OAuth 2.0 service.
  </li>

  <li>
    A database which contains user information is accessed and updated
    using <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/tutorial/dbo/tutorial.html">Wt::Dbo</a>.
  </li>
</ul>

<!--<p>For a thorough explanation of the hangman example, see also the ARTICLE</p>-->
</div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.examples.widgetgallery">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Widget gallery</h4>

<p>
  <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/widgets" class="run" target="_blank">
    <img src="/icons/green-play.png" style="vertical-align: top"/>  Go to widget gallery
  </a>
</p>

<p>
 This example demonstrates most widgets provided by Wt, in addition to
 other aspects such as event handling and layout classes. Useful as an
 executable reference to widgets and features provided by the library.
</p>

</div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.download">
    <h3><span>Download</span></h3>
  </message>
  <message id="home.download.license">
<h4>License and Pricing</h4>

<p>Wt may be used using either an Open Source or a Commercial License.</p>

<p>If you wish to use the library using the <b>GNU General Public
License (GPL)</b>, you may build a web application with Wt and deploy
it, but per the terms of the GPL, you are obliged to make the source
code available to anyone who you give the application to install the
application on its own server. This also applies to redistribution of
the Wt library, in original or modified form.</p>

<p><b>The Commercial License</b> has no such limitations: you may
redistribute applications developed with Wt without needing to
redistribute the source code. The license is a royalty-free, perpetual
license for one developer to use the API of Wt (respectively Wt::Dbo)
for application development, using the latest version of Wt or any
version released during one year.
</p>

<table class="versions">
  <tr class="trh">
    <th></th>
    <th class="product">Dbo</th>
    <th class="product">Wt + Dbo</th>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r0">
    <th>Widget library</th>
    <td></td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r1">
    <th>Application server</th>
    <td></td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r0">
    <th>HTTP + WebSockets server</th>
    <td></td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r1">
    <th>Charting Module</th>
    <td></td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r0">
    <th>XHTML Rendering Module</th>
    <td></td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r1">
    <th>C++ ORM</th>
    <td>+</td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r0">
    <th class="indent">Sqlite3 driver</th>
    <td>+</td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r1">
    <th class="indent">PostgreSQL driver</th>
    <td>+</td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r0">
    <th class="indent">Firebird driver</th>
    <td>+</td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r1">
    <th class="indent">MariaDB/MySQL driver</th>
    <td>+</td>
    <td>+</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r0">
    <th class="indent">Oracle driver</th>
    <td colspan="2"><a href="mailto:sales@emweb.be">Contact us</a></td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="separate r1">
    <th>License</th>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r0">
    <th class="indent">
      GNU General Public License
    </th>
    <td>free</td>
    <td>free</td>
  </tr>
  <tr class="r1">
    <th class="indent multiline">
      Commercial License
    </th>
    <td class="multiline">
      <div><span class="price">&euro;175</span> <span class="cart" /></div>
      <div><a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/license/WtDbo%20License%20Agreement.pdf" class="smallprint">(license text)</a></div>
    </td>
    <td class="multiline">
      <div><span class="price">&euro;599</span> <span class="cart" /></div>
      <div><a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/license/Wt%20License%20Agreement.pdf" class="smallprint">(license text)</a></div>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>

There is also an Oracle driver for Wt::Dbo, which is sold separately and
can be used only in conjunction with a Commercial License for Wt::Dbo.

  </message>
  
  <message id="home.download.packages">
    <h4><span>Available packages</span></h4>
  </message>
  <message id="home.download.version"><b>Version</b></message>
  <message id="home.download.date"><b>Date</b></message>
  <message id="home.download.description"><b>Description</b></message>

  <message id="home.download.other">

<p>
  If you are looking to use Wt using <b>MSVC on Windows platforms</b>,
  then you can save yourself some hassle to build Wt with its optional
  dependencies from source, and download one of the <a
  href="https://github.com/kdeforche/wt/releases">binary builds
  instead</a> (<a
  href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/witty/files/wt/">old releases</a>)
  which allow you to quickly experiment with the examples
  that ship with Wt.
</p>

<p>
  Similarly, if you are on <b>Ubuntu</b>, you can install a reasonably
  recent version of Wt from official packages. The wiki contains more
  details on <a
  href="http://redmine.emweb.be/projects/wt/wiki/Installing_Wt_on_Ubuntu">installing
  Wt on Ubuntu</a>, including instructions on how to build Wt from
  source or getting packages for the most recent Wt releases.
</p>

<div class="fragment">
  <pre class="fragment">
$ sudo apt-get install witty witty-dev witty-doc witty-dbg witty-examples</pre>
</div>

<p>
  The last package (<tt>witty-examples</tt>) installs the examples
  in <tt>/usr/lib/Wt/examples</tt>. You can run each of them like this:
</p>

<div class="fragment">
  <pre class="fragment">$ /usr/lib/Wt/examples/hello/hello</pre>
</div>

<p>Older releases are still available at
<a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/witty/files/wt/">sourceforge.net</a>.
</p>

<h4>The Wt installer: winst</h4>

If you are curious about Wt and would like to try it out but your OS
or distribution does not provide an up-to-date package, then this may
be just what you need. This package will download and build Wt and its
dependencies in a <b>UNIX(-like) environment</b>, and provides also
a script to run the examples.

<p>
This requires <tt>CMake</tt> and <tt>GNU make</tt> and will try to
download software using <tt>wget</tt>.
</p>

<p>
Download the package
(<a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/packages/winst-0.4.tar.gz">winst-0.4.tar.gz</a>)
or get the latest git version:
<div class="fragment">
  <pre class="fragment">$ git clone git://github.com/kdeforche/winst.git</pre>
</div>
</p>

<h4>System requirements</h4>

For building and installing the latest version of Wt, you need at
least the following two packages:
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.cmake.org/">CMake</a> cross-platform make configure
    utility.<br />

    CMake &gt;= 2.6 is preferred (although by the act of a miracle,
    2.4 still works).
  </li>
  <li>
    The indispensable <a href="http://www.boost.org/"> boost C++
    library</a>: boost-1.41 or later. Older boost versions (as old as 1.36)
    may also be used, but some functionality will be missing
    (JSON parsing and a better SQL query parsing for Wt::Dbo). <br />

    The following boost libraries (which are not headers only) are
    needed: <tt>boost_date_time</tt>, <tt>boost_regex</tt>,
    <tt>boost_program_options</tt>, <tt>boost_signals</tt>,
    <tt>boost_random</tt>, <tt>boost_system</tt>, and optionally (but
    highly recommended) <tt>boost_thread</tt>.
  </li>
</ul>

The following packages are optional, and availability enables additional
features in Wt:
<ul>

  <li><a href="http://www.openssl.org/">OpenSSL</a>: if available,
    then the HTTPS protocol will be supported by the web client
    (<a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1Http_1_1Client.html">Http::Client</a>) and web server (wthttp connector)
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/libharu/libharu/wiki">libharu</a>: if
    available, a
    <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WPdfImage.html">WPdfImage</a>
    paint device will be included, which provides rendering support for PDF
    documents. For more complete support for TrueType fonts and Unicode, you'll
    want <a href="https://github.com/libharu/libharu">the latest git version</a>
    and probably also libpango (see further) for accurate font/glyph
    selection.
  </li>
  <li><a href="http://www.graphicsmagick.org/">GraphicsMagick</a>: if
    available,
    a <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WRasterImage.html">WRasterImage</a>
    paint device will be included, which outputs to raster images like PNG
    or GIF.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.pango.org/">pango</a> (LGPL): if available,
    text rendering for WPdfImage and WRasterImage will be assisted by
    this library for TrueType font selection, taking into
    consideration both the font face and unicode coverage.</li>
  <li>
    <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/">PostgreSQL</a>, <a
    href="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a>/<a
    href="http://mariadb.org/">MariaDB</a>, and <a
    href="http://firebirdsql.org">Firebird</a>: if available,
    connectors for these databases for the ORM library (<a
    href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/tutorial/dbo/tutorial.html">
    Wt::Dbo</a>) will be built (alongside the Sqlite3 connector which
    is distributed with Wt).
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The other requirements depend on the connector support you would
like. The connector is what makes your Wt application communicate with
the browser:</p>

<h5>For FastCGI (Unix only):</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Apache 1 or 2, or another web server which supports the FastCGI
  protocol.</li>
  <li>
    <a href="http://www.fastcgi.com/#TheDevKit">FastCGI development kit</a>
    : fcgi-2.4.0
  </li>

   <li>
     When using apache:
     Apache <a href="http://www.fastcgi.com/dist/mod_fastcgi-2.4.6.tar.gz">mod_fastcgi</a>:
     mod_fastcgi-2.4.x.<br />Alternatively you may
     use <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/download.cgi#mod_fcgid">mod_fcgid</a>:
     mod_fcgid-2.3.5.
  </li> 
</ul>

<h5>For the built-in http deamon, wthttpd:</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Optionally, libz (for compression-over-HTTP) and openssl (for
    HTTPS support).
  </li>
</ul>

<h5>For ISAPI (Win32 only):</h5>

<ul>
  <li>The ISAPI connector only works for deploying Wt applications withing a
    Microsoft IIS server.</li>
</ul>

Follow the <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/InstallationUnix.html">Installation
instructions</a> to build Wt and run the examples, or see if your
platform is listed in the <a
href="http://redmine.webtoolkit.eu/projects/wt/wiki/Wt_Installation">platform specific
installation instructions</a>.

<h4>Git repository</h4>

<a href="https://github.com/kdeforche/wt"><img style="display: block; width: 80px; float: right" src="https://github.com/github/media/blob/master/octocats/octocat.png?raw=true"></img></a>
<p>If you want to keep track of the latest changes, or participate in
Wt development, you may want to work from
the <a href="https://github.com/kdeforche/wt">github
repository</a>.</p>

<p>
Alternatively checkout the repository using:
<div class="fragment">
  <pre class="fragment">$ git clone git://github.com/kdeforche/wt.git</pre>
</div>
</p>
  </message>

  <message id="home.community">
<h3><span>Support</span></h3>

<h4>Support and Training</h4>

<p>
  You can get <a href="//www.emweb.be/services">support and
  training</a> directly from the library authors, with a
  guaranteed three-day response time.
</p>

<p>
  Community help is available in the <a
  href="http://redmine.webtoolkit.eu/projects/wt/boards">public
  forums</a>. Until September 2009, there was only a <a
  href="mailto:witty-interest@lists.sourceforge.net">mailing list</a>
  (<a
  href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/witty-interest">how
  to join</a>), and the old dogs haven't left yet. You may search or
  browse the mailing list archives using the <a
  href="http://gmane.org/info.php?group=gmane.comp.web.witty.general">Gmane
  gateway</a> (kudos to Pau Garcia i Quiles for setting this up).
</p>

<p>
  To get up to speed with Wt and/or Wt::Dbo, you may also obtain <a
  href="//www.emweb.be/services">training</a> directly from
  the library authors.
</p>

<h4>Authors</h4>

<p>
The software was originally developed by <a
href="mailto:koen@emweb.be">Koen Deforche</a>, and is currently
maintained by <a href="//www.emweb.be/">Emweb bvba</a>.</p>

<p>We are greateful to these projects from which we borrowed code:</p>
<ul>
<li>The built-in httpd is based on an example of the <a
href="http://asio.sourceforge.net/">asio C++
library</a>, developed by Christopher M. Kohlhoff. <a
href="http://www.boost.org/LICENSE_1_0.txt">Boost Software License</a></li>
<li>The <a href="http://rapidxml.sourceforge.net/">RapidXML</a>
library by Marcin Kalicinski.  <a
href="http://www.boost.org/LICENSE_1_0.txt">Boost Software License</a></li>
<li>The authentication module
contains <a href="http://www.openwall.com/crypt/">bcrypt</a>
and <a href="http://www.openwall.com/passwdqc/">passwdqc</a> by Solar
Designer. <a href="http://www.openwall.com/crypt/">Public
domain.</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
Other independent contributors include: Richard Ulrich, Gaetano
Mendola, Thomas Suckow, Hilary Cheng, Dmitriy Igrishin, Daniel Derr,
Omer Katz, and Lukasz Matuszewski, and many others (see the Changelog).
</p>

<h4>Wiki</h4>

<p>
There is a community-run <a
href="http://redmine.webtoolkit.eu/projects/wt/wiki">Wt Wiki</a> with useful
information, including installation notes for several Linux
distributions.
</p>

<h4>Contributions</h4>

<p>Development of Wt is sponsored by the following companies and
organisations:</p>

<p>
<table>
  <tr>
    <td class="sponsor-logo"><a href="//www.emweb.be/">
      Emweb bvba</a>
    </td>
    <td class="sponsor-role">
      Creators, official maintainers, and support
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td class="sponsor-logo">
      <a href="http://www.eurofer.be/">
      Eurofer</a>
    </td>
    <td class="sponsor-role">
      Sponsored the development of the charting library, WTreeView and
      hierachical item models.
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
</p>

<p>User contributions are welcomed, ranging from simple patches to
widgets, widget sets, and core improvements.</p>

<p>However, because Wt is dual-licensed under an Open Source and
commercial license, and to legally protect the code base of Wt as a
whole by one entity without having to worry about the copyrights for
different pieces, we require a copyright assignment from contributors
to <a href="//www.emweb.be/">Emweb</a> before
accepting the contribution.</p>

<h4>Translations</h4>

The Chinese translation of the homepage was provided by Zhimin Song.

<h4>Sourceforge</h4>

<a href="http://sourceforge.net"><img src="https://sflogo.sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=153710&amp;type=1" style="vertical-align:middle" width="88" height="31" border="0" alt="SourceForge.net Logo" /></a>
The Wt project is hosted at sourceforge <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/witty/">here</a>.
  </message>
  <message id="home.other-language">

<h3><span>!C++ ?</span></h3>

<p>You like the library functionality, but do not grock C++ for your
project?</p>

<p>Do not despair. Wt exists in a native variant or through bindings
in other languages:

<ul class="languages">
<li>
<div>
<img class="java-language-icon" src="/icons/java-logo.png" alt="Java"></img>

You can use <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/jwt">JWt</a>, a native <b>Java</b> version of Wt
developed and maintained together with the C++ version. It has, with
few exceptions, the same features as Wt, but runs natively in the JVM
and can be deployed into any Servlet container.
</div>

<br style="clear: both" />

</li>
<li>
<div>
<img class="language-icon" src="/icons/ruby-logo-R.png" alt="Ruby"></img>

Richard Dale is
maintaining <a href="http://github.com/rdale/wtruby/tree/master">WtRuby</a>,
<b>Ruby</b> bindings to Wt, using the same framework used for generating Ruby
bindings to Qt and KDE.
</div>


<br style="clear: both" />

</li>

<li>
<div>
<img class="language-icon" src="/icons/clojure-logo.png" alt="Clojure"></img>

Leveraging the JVM's support for other languages, such
as <b>Clojure</b>, a LISP variant, Ralph Moritz is experimenting
with <a href="http://lispetc.posterous.com/hello-jwt-from-clojure">using
JWt from within Clojure</a>, documenting his experience in his blog
and eventually developing a small support library.
</div>

<br style="clear: both" />

</li>

<li>
<div>
<img class="language-icon" src="/icons/jython-logo.png" alt="Jython"></img>

Albert Cervera i Areny is experimenting to use JWt from <b>Jython</b>,
another language running on the JVM. He documents how to create and run 
the "Hello World!" program in Jython in <a href="http://www.nan-tic.com/en/from-pyqt-to-jythonjwt-setting-up-the-environment">this blog post</a>.
</div>

<br style="clear: both" />

</li>

</ul>
</p>

  </message>
  <message id="home.documentation">
 
<h3><span>Documentation</span></h3>

<h4>Build and install</h4>

<p>
Generic installation instructions (UNIX)
are <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/InstallationUnix.html">here</a>, which
are also included in the source package (INSTALL or INSTALL.html).</p>
<p>
In addition, the <a href="http://redmine.webtoolkit.eu/projects/wt/wiki">Wt
Wiki</a> has a section dedicated
to <a href="http://redmine.webtoolkit.eu/projects/wt/wiki/Wt_Installation">platform
specific installation notes</a>.
</p>

<h4>Introduction and tutorials</h4>

<ul>
<li>Learn about the benefits of Wt compared to traditional web
application frameworks using our <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/doc/Wt-WhitePaper.pdf">white
paper</a>.</li>

<li>The <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/tutorial/wt.html">online
tutorial</a> (<a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/tutorial/wt.pdf">download
PDF</a>) brings you up to speed on developing web applications using
Wt (revised December 2011).</li>

<li>The ORM framework (Wt::Dbo) is covered in a separate <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/tutorial/dbo.html">online
tutorial</a> (<a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/tutorial/dbo.pdf">download
PDF</a>) (revised July 2011).</li>

<li>Dr Dobbs Journal has a good <a href="http://www.ddj.com/cpp/206401952">
introductary article on Wt</a> (February 2008).</li>

<li>The reference manual contains a <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/overview.html">library
overview</a> which is recommended reading with information about
configuration and deployment options.</li>

<li>Victor Venkman wrote a
<a href="http://www.codeguru.com/cpp/i-n/internet/browsercontrol/article.php/c15275/">nice introduction to Wt</a>, with a closer examination of
the <a href="#/examples/">hello world example</a>.</li>

</ul>

<h4>Reference manual</h4>

<p>The <a
href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/reference/html/index.html"
target="_blank"> reference manual</a> has been generated from the
source code using doxygen.</p>

<h4>Annotated examples</h4>

<p>Source-level documentation has also been generated for the examples
and can be viewed <a href="//www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/doc/examples/html/modules.html"
target="_blank">here (in a new window)</a>.</p>

<h4>Wiki</h4>

<p>
There is a community-run <a href="http://redmine.webtoolkit.eu/projects/wt/wiki">Wt Wiki</a> with useful information such as a FAQ and
tips and tricks.
</p>

  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code for Wt examples</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for all examples included in 
	<a href="#/">Wt</a>.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.">Wt examples</message>

  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.hello">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code of the <i>Hello world</i> example</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for Wt's 
	<a href="#/examples/">Hello world</a> example.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.hello">Example: Hello world</message>

  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.hangman">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code of the <i>Hangman</i> example</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for Wt's 
	<a href="#/examples/">Hangman</a> example.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.hangman">Example: Hangman</message>

  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.charts">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code of the <i>Charts</i> example</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for Wt's 
	<a href="#/examples/charts">Charts</a> example.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.charts">Example: Charts</message>

  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.treeview-dragdrop">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code of the <i>Treeview</i> example</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for Wt's <a href="#/examples/treeview">
	  Treeview</a> example.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.treeview-dragdrop">Example: Treeview</message>

  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.composer">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code of the <i>Mail composer</i> example</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for Wt's 
	<a href="#/examples/composer">Mail composer</a> example.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.composer">Example: Mail composer</message>
  
  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.wt-homepage">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code of the <i>Wt homepage</i> example</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for Wt's 
	<a href="#/examples/wt-homepage">Homepage</a> example.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.wt-homepage">Example: Wt Homepage</message>

  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.gitmodel">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code of the <i>Git explorer</i> example</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for Wt's 
	<a href="#/examples/gitmodel">Git explorer</a> example.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.gitmodel">Example: Git explorer</message>

  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.simplechat">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code of the <i>Chat</i> example</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for Wt's 
	<a href="#/examples/simplechat">Chat</a> example.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.simplechat">Example: Chat</message>

  <message id="srcview.title.CPP.widgetgallery">
    <div class="srcviewtitle">
      <h2>Source code of the <i>Widget gallery</i> example</h2>

      <p>
	Browse below the source code for Wt's 
	<a href="#/examples/widgetgallery">Widget gallery</a> example.
      </p>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="srcview.title.widgetgallery">Example: Widget gallery</message>

</messages>
