<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<messages>
  <message id="top_wt">
      <a href="http://www.emweb.be/">
	<img src="/images/emweb_powered.jpg" alt="Emweb" height="22" />
      </a> 
  </message>

  <message id="banner_wrapper">
    <div id="banner_content">
      <div id="banner_end"> <div id="banner"><a href="#">Wt</a></div> </div>
    </div>
  </message>

  <message id="footer_wrapper">
    <div id="footer_content">
      <div id="footer_copyright"> 
	<a href="http://www.emweb.be/">
	  <img src="/images/emweb_large.jpg" height="25" width="101"
	       alt="Emweb.be" title="emweb.be"/></a>
	Solutions for web-based systems<br/>
	<a href="http://www.emweb.be/">www.emweb.be</a>
      </div>

      <div id="footer_menu"> 
	<a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/">Home</a>
	| <a href="http://www.emweb.be/?page=contact">Contact</a>
      </div>
      <div class="clearall"></div>
    </div>
    <script src="http://www.google-analytics.com/ga.js" type="text/javascript">
    </script>
    <script type="text/javascript">
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker('UA-4345578-1');
      pageTracker._initData();
      pageTracker._trackPageview();
    </script>
  </message>

  <message id="wt">Wt, C++ Web Toolkit</message>

  <message id="introduction">Introduction</message>
  <message id="news">News</message>
  <message id="features">Features</message>
  <message id="documentation">Documentation</message>
  <message id="examples">Examples</message>
  <message id="download">Download</message>
  <message id="community">Community</message>

  <message id="hello-world">Hello world</message>
  <message id="charts">Charts</message>
  <message id="wt-homepage">Wt homepage</message>
  <message id="treeview">Treeview</message>
  <message id="git">Git explorer</message>
  <message id="chat">Chat</message>
  <message id="mail-composer">Mail composer</message>
  <message id="widget-gallery">Widget gallery</message>

  <message id="home.news">
    <h3><span>News</span></h3>
  </message>
  <message id="home.latest-news">
    <h4><span>Latest News</span></h4>
  </message>
  <message id="home.historical-news">
    <h4><span>Historical News</span></h4>
  </message>

  <message id="home.intro">

<h3><span>Wt: an introduction</span></h3>

<p>Wt (pronounced 'witty') is a C++ library and application server for
developing and deploying web applications. It is not a 'framework',
which enforces a way of programming, but a library.</p>

<p>The API is widget-centric, and inspired by existing C++ Graphical
User Interface (GUI) APIs. To the developer, it offers complete
abstraction of any web-specific implementation details, including
event handling and graphics support.</p>

<p>Page-based frameworks (such as based on PHP or JSP/JSF (+ servlets
+ struts)) for developing web application do not make abstraction of
the peculiarities of the underlying technologies (HTML/XHTML,
JavaScript, CSS, AJAX, Forms, DHTML, SVG/VML/Canvas). As a
consequence, a developer must gain familiarity with all of these
(evolving) technologies. Moreover, when choosing to use a technology
(such the currently popular AJAX), the developer is responsible for
graceful degradation when AJAX or JavaScript are not available or
disabled. The structure of the application follows mostly the
page-centric paradigm of early day HTML. This means that when using
advanced AJAX techniques, as a developer you will need to design and
maintain manually your client-server communication.</p>

<p>Generating HTML code or filling HTML templates is prone to security
problems such as XSS (Cross-Site-Scripting), by unwillingly allowing
JavaScript to be inserted in the page. But this cannot be avoided by
template frameworks, because as a developer you need to be able to
insert self-written JavaScript to improve your web application.</p>

<p>In contrast, a web application developed with Wt is written in only
one compiled language (C++), from which the library generates the
necessary HTML/XHTML, Javascript, CGI, SVG/VML/Canvas and AJAX
code. The responsibility of writing secure and browser-portable web
applications is handled by Wt. For example, if available, Wt will
maximally use JavaScript and AJAX, but applications developed using Wt
will also function correctly when AJAX is not available, or when
JavaScript is disabled, reverting to a plain HTML/CGI mechanism for
communication between browser and server.</p>

<h4>Typical use scenarios:</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Web-based GUIs for <b>web-enabled embedded systems</b> benefit
  from the low footprint of a C++ web application server.</li>
  <li>Web-based GUIs that require <b>integration with (existing) C++
  libraries</b>, for example for scientific or engineering
  applications.</li>
  <li>Creating a port of <b>existing C++ desktop applications</b> to
  the web.</li>
</ul>

<h4>Some benefits of using Wt</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Develop web applications like you develop C++ desktop
  applications.</li>
  <li>Provides plain widgets, which work regardless of JavaScript
  availability (but benefit from JavaScript availability), and Wt::Ext
  widgets which are more polished, or provide advanced functionality,
  but require JavaScript and a modern browser. As far as possible,
  these widgets share the same API.</li>
  <li>Use the built-in httpd for easy development and deployment, or
  use the FastCGI connector to deploy as a FastCGI application.</li>
  <li>A single specification for both client- and server-side
  validation and event handling (when using stateless slot
  implementations)</li>
  <li>Generates standards compliant HTML or XHTML code.</li>
  <li>Portable, anti-aliased graphics (uses inline VML, inline SVG or
  the HTML 5 canvas).</li>
  <li>No XSS security risks since Wt has complete control over the
  presentation layer and proactively filters out <i>active</i> tags
  and attributes. No exposure of business logic, which stays at the
  server.</li>
  <li>Ultra-fast load time and low bandwidth usage, which are
  affected only by screen complexity, not application size.</li>
</ul>

  </message>
  <message id="home.features">

<h3><span>Features</span></h3>

<h4>Core library</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Supports all major browsers (Firefox/Gecko, Internet Explorer,
    Safari, Konqueror, and Opera) but also browsers that do not support
    JavaScript (tested with Links and Lynx).</li>
  <li>Develop and deploy on Unix/GNU Linux (gcc) or Microsoft Windows
    (Visual Studio).</li>
  <li>Equal behavior with or without support for JavaScript or AJAX,
    as far as possible.</li>
  <li>Integrated Unicode support (UTF8/UTF16).</li>
  <li>Incremental rendering of changes to the web page (when AJAX
    is available).</li>
  <li>Two-phased rendering of changes to the web page, with first
    visible, and in the background invisible changes (when AJAX is
    available). When AJAX is not available, only visible contents is
    rendered.</li>
  <li>Configurable session tracking options that include URL rewriting
    and cookies.</li>
  <li>Supports timed events and built-in support for server-initiated
  updates ("server push")</li>
  <li>Support for browser history navigation (back/forward buttons and
    bookmarks) through a flexible internal path API.</li>
  <li>High performance, allowing deployment on low-end embedded
    devices, or energy-, space- and budget-friendly deployment of
    Internet or extranet web sites.</li>
  <li>Completely based on async I/O: sessions are not tied to threads,
    and neither do delayed responses (e.g. for server push) block
    threads. Instead, threads are needed only to improve concurrent
    request handling or for reentrant event loops.</li>
</ul>

<h4>Event handling</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Listen for keyboard, mouse and focus events, and get event
    details (such as mouse position, modifier buttons, or keyboard
    key).</li>
  <li>Uses a template-based signal/slot system for event handling.</li>
  <li>By default, server-side event handling, in C++.</li>
  <li>Dynamic C++-to-JavaScript translation, by specifying
    <i>stateless slot</i> implementations. A single C++ slot implementation
    provides both client-side and server-side event handling: visual changes
    at client-side and application state at server side.</li>
  <li>Possibility to hook in custom JavaScript (e.g. for client-side only event
    handling), and <i>emit</i> C++ signals from this custom JavaScript.</li>
  <li>Easy Drag&amp;Drop API.</li> 
</ul>

<h4>Native painting system</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Unified painting API which uses the browsers native (vector)
    graphics support (inline VML, inline SVG, or HTML 5 canvas).</li>
  <li>Supports arbitrary painter paths, clipping, text, images,
    transformations, and stroke and fill styling.</li>
  <li>Use the painting API in conjunction with a WPaintedWidget, or directly
    using the SVGImage paint device.</li>
</ul>

<h4>GUI components</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Basic widgets (buttons, HTML anchors, checkboxes and radio
    buttons, combo boxes, containers, file upload control, images,
    labels, line edits, buttons, etc..</li>
  <li>Form widgets have built-in support for client-side and
    server-side validation using WValidator classes.</li>
  <li>Composite widgets (that are built on top of basic widgets, and
    use only the Wt public API): calendars, sliders, trees and tree
    tables, menus, in-place edits, virtual images, panels.</li>
  <li>Modal windows (dialog and message boxes)</li>
  <li>Built-in internationalization using messages resource bundles.</li>
  <li>CSS either inline, or using internal or external style sheets.</li>
  <li>Ext Wt widgets that internally
    use <a href="http://extjs.com/">Ext JS 2.0.1</a> JavaScript
    widgets. A large subset of the ExtJS widgets have been wrapped as
    C++ widgets.
  </li>
  <li>Flexible charting widgets (cartesian charts and pie charts)
    based on the native painting API, and Wt's MVC infrastructure.</li>
</ul>

<h4>Built-in security</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Kernel-level memory protection protects against privacy issues
    arising from programming bugs, since sessions can be completely
    isolated from each other (in dedicated-process mode).</li>
  <li>Supports encryption and server authentication using Secure Sockets
    Layer (SSL) or Transport Layer Security (TLS) through HTTPS.</li>
  <li>Enables continuous use of HTTPS through low bandwidth
    requirements (fine-grained AJAX).</li>
  <li>Built-in Cross-Site Scripting (XSS) prevention. Rendered text is
    always filtered against potentially malicious code, making XSS
    attacks against Wt applications (close to) impossible.</li>
  <li>Not vulnerable to Cross-site Request Forgery (CSRF) because
    cookies for session tracking are optional, and even when used, they
    are never solely relied on for requests that trigger event handling
    code.</li>
</ul>

<h4>Deployment</h4>

<h5>a) FastCGI</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Integrates with most common web servers (apache, lighttpd).</li>
  <li>Different session-to-process mapping strategies.</li>
  <li>Hot deployment: new sessions use the new application version while 
    older sessions may continue with their application version.</li>
  <li>Simultaneous handling of requests within and in between sessions
    (using multi-threading)</li>
  <li>Debug using gdb or valgrind.</li>
  <li>Available only for UNIX platforms.</li>
</ul>

<h5>b) Built-in httpd</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Simple, high-performance web application server (multi-threaded,
    asynchronous I/O) based on the C++ asio library.</li>
  <li>Supports both HTTP and HTTPS using the OpenSSL library.</li>
  <li>Supports response chunking and compression</li>
  <li>Single process (convenient for development and debugging).</li>
  <li>Available for both UNIX and Win32 platforms.</li>
  <li>Supports deployment behind a ProxyPass'ing (and if needed,
    load-balancing) web server.</li>
</ul>

  </message>
  <message id="home.examples">

<h3><span>Examples</span></h3>

<p>Explore some live examples of Wt below.</p>

<p>
  The source code of these examples is included in the Wt source
  distribution. You may also browse through the source code of each
  example in the tree widget.
</p>

<p>
  Cross-linked source code for these examples is also in
  <a href="/wt/doc/examples/html/modules.html" target="_blank">
  doxygen documentation (in a new window)</a>.
</p>

  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.hello">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Hello world!</h4>

<p>The most ubiquitous of all examples:
<a href="/wt/examples/hello/hello.wt" target="_blank">Hello world</a>.</p>

<p>This simple example illustrates basic Wt concepts:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    How to bootstrap a new Wt application using <b>WRun()</b>, and a
    function to create a new <a
    href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WApplication.html" target="_blank">
      WApplication</a>,
    corresponding to a new session.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Creating widgets</b>, and adding it to <b>the widget tree</b>.
  </li>
  <li>
    Reacting to events using the <b>signal/slot</b> mechanism.
  </li>
  <li>
    Reading widget state (such as line edit text) and updating widgets.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>For a thorough explanation of the hello world example, see also the
<a href="http://www.codeguru.com/cpp/i-n/internet/browsercontrol/article.php/c15275/" target="_blank">nice introduction to Wt</a> written by Victor
Venkman.</p>

<p>Browse the source code:</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.wt">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Wt homepage</h4>
<p>We eat our own dog food: this website itself is a Wt application. </p>

<p>
  Not a very interactive application (and certainly not the
  recommended use-case for using Wt), the wt-homepage illustrates use
  of
  the <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WMenu.html" target="_blank">WMenu</a>
  and <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTabWidget.html" target="_blank">WTabWidget</a>
  widgets, and also uses several features to increase scalability (by
  completely minimizing server-side memory usage).
</p>

<p>
  In addition, the homepage also uses several features of the WMenu
  widget: a main menu, which is a plain vertical WMenu instantiation,
  and the examples tab widget, which uses a WTabWidget which is itself
  implemented as a horizontal WMenu (with a specific style).
</p>

<p>
  The menu widget supports <b>pre-loading</b> versus <b>lazy
  loading</b> the contents associated with each item. This can
  be <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WMenu.html#d7840197cc0caf0430792b9f4a0df60d" target="_blank">specified</a>
  for each item separately. Note that pre-loading does not increase
  the load time. This is because the Wt render engine optimizes the
  response time by only transmitting visual widgets or changes
  first. Everything invisible (such as the contents for other
  pre-loaded menu items) is transmitted in the background, after
  rendering the visible contents. Automatically.
</p>

<p>
  Menu navigation is implemented using C++ stateless slots, and
  therefore results in <b>client-side</b> event handling code.
</p>
<p>
  The homepage needs to be search engine friendly and therefore it
  uses the <b>internal path</b> features of WMenu, which participate
  the browser history and allow bookmarking or referring to a
  particular application state. When the user browses through the
  history, the application reacts to these changes by
  listening
  to the <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WApplication.html#41c9bda19b28526e47e70b1b6045e7cf" target="_blank">the
  internalPathChanged signal</a> from the WApplication
  object. Similarly, when a user bookmarks a URL, and later comes
  back, this signal is emitted just after a new application is
  started.
</p>

<p>
  Although Wt is lightweight in CPU time (at the server), it does
  require to keep some widget state at the server. This is not
  necessarily a problem, provided enough memory (and swap
  space). Since the Wt homepage is deployed on a VPS, we still were
  careful to minimize server state, by using
  the <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WViewWidget.html" target="_blank">WViewWidget</a> where possible.
</p>

<p>Browse the source code:</p>

</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.treeview">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Treeview</h4>
<p>
  <a href="/wt/examples/treeview-dragdrop/treeview-dragdrop.wt" target="_blank">
  This example</a> demonstrates the following features:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Using a <a
    href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTreeView" target="_blank">WTreeView</a>
    for rendering a model in a tree or a table. WTreeView displays
    tree-tables (i.e. a tree in the first column with a number of
    additional columns), and so a tree and table are two degenerate
    cases.
  </li>
  <li>
    The use of <a
    href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WSortFilterProxyModel"
    target="_blank">WSortFilterProxyModel</a>
    to implement sorting and filtering of another model.
  </li>
  <li>
    How to implement drag and drop from a selection of items.
  </li>
  <li>
    Using nested layout managers (horizontal and
    vertical
    <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WBoxLayout" target="_blank">
      WBoxLayout</a>)
    for an automatic window-filling layout.
  </li>
  <li>
    Since WTreeView does not yet support inline editing, how to use a
    modal <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WDialog" target="_blank">
      WDialog</a> to present a simple form, using a
    <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WGridLayout" target="_blank">
      WGridLayout</a>
    for layout.
  </li>
  <li>
    How to show a context-sensitive
    <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WPopupMenu" target="_blank">
      WPopupMenu</a>.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>Browse the source code:</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.chart">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Charts example</h4>

<p><a href="/wt/examples/charts/charts.wt" target="_blank">This
example</a> demonstrates the
<a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/namespaceWt_1_1Chart.html" target="_blank">
  Wt charting widgets</a> that are implemented on top of Wt's
cross-browser painting API. This painting API, uses built-in browser
support for generating high quality graphics (instead of the more
common approach of rendering raster images on the server
side). Depending on the browser, inline VML, inline SVG, or the HTML 5
canvas is used to render painted contents in
a <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WPaintedWidget.html"
     target="_blank">WPaintedWidget</a>.
</p>

<p>This example demonstrates Wt's MVC infrastructure. Both
the <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1Ext_1_1TableView.html"
target="_blank">table view</a> and the charts implement Views on a
single <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WAbstractItemModel.html"
target="_blank">model</a>. In this way, all changes in the model are
automatically reflected in updated views. The model may contain
strings, numbers or <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WDate.html"
target="_blank">dates</a>. You can see this in action by editing the
data using the table view.</p>

<p>The example also shows how one may easily use multiple input
widgets, react to input changes, and set and read their contents, and
use <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WComboBox.html"
target="_blank">WComboBox</a> in conjunction with MVC models.  Behind
the scenes, the library makes sure that data is synchronized between
browser and server.</p>

<p>Browse the source code:</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.git">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Git explorer</h4>
<p>
  <a href="/wt/examples/gitmodel/gitview.wt" target="_blank">
  This example</a> shows how to implement a custom model for Wt's
  MVC-based view classes, such as
  <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTreeView.html" target="_blank">
    WTreeView</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Wt provides a <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WStandardItemModel"
		   target="_blank">WStandardItemModel</a> which can be
  populated with data retrieved from for example a database. A draw-back is
  however that all data is stored in memory and must be retrieved in advance.
  By reimplementing
  <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WAbstractItemModel"
     target="_blank">WAbstractItemModel</a>, you can implement a model
  that retrieves data only when needed, and provides a trade-off between loading
  data in memory or keeping it elsewhere.
</p>
<p>Browse the source code:</p>
</div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.examples.style">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Style example</h4>

<p>
  HTML/CSS is especially convenient for adding style to your web page or
  web application, and Wt supports both inline and stylesheets for applying
  style to your application.
</p>
<p>
  In <a href="/wt/examples/style/styleexample.wt" target="_blank">this example
  </a> we show how to create a widget class that has rounded
  corners, <i>RoundedWidget</i>. Since rounded corners are not part of
  CSS 2, the current accepted solution is to use some CSS tricks with
  images. In this example, we <b>compute the corner images on the
  fly</b> (with the specified colors and radius), using the graphics
  library gd. Using the widget is completely straight forward (as also
  demonstrated around the menus in the wt homepage itself), and the
  contents is an ordinary
  <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WContainerWidget.html"
     target="_blank">WContainerWidget</a>
  into which widgets may be added.
</p>

<p>
  This examples shows how to use
  a <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WMemoryResource.html"
  target="_blank">WMemoryResource</a>, which is an implementation of
  the abstract
  class <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WResource.html"
  target="_blank">WResource</a>. A WResource may be the target of a
  browser request, and may thus represent any kind of file. In
  particular,
  a <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WImage.html"
  target="_blank">WImage</a> may be defined using an image resource,
  as in this example. A WMemoryResource streams the response from a
  byte array in memory. Similarly,
  a <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WFileResource.html"
  target="_blank">WFileResource</a> streams the response from a
  temporary file. If you wish to compute data on the fly, instead of
  precomputing and storing it in memory or in a file, you can
  re-implement WResource. This is illustrated in the mandelbrot
  example, which computes the mandelbrot images on the fly.
</p>

<p>Browse the source code:</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.composer">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Mail composer</h4>

<p>
  <a href="/wt/examples/composer/composer.wt" target="_blank">This
  example</a> implements a GMail-like mail composer and shows among
  other things how you can easily upload files asynchronously.
</p>

<p>
  Some notes about this example:
</p>

  <ul>
    <li>
      Like the Wt homepage, it uses only <b>style sheets</b> and style
      classes for accurate control over the look.
    </li>
    <li>
      The <i>ContactSuggestions</i> class provides auto-completion of
      the addressees in the To: Cc: and Bcc: fields. The widget
      derives from
      the <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WSuggestionPopup.html"
	     target="_blank">WSuggestionPopup</a>
      class, which uses a number of
      <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1JSlot.html"
	 target="_blank">JSlot</a>
      objects. These are slots for which the client-side JavaScript
      event handling code is specified in custom JavaScript (in
      contrast to stateless slots, for which client-side JavaScript is
      "learned" through invocation). In this way, the sorting through
      available contacts for suitable suggestions is done entirely
      client-side. Note that the contacts for this suggestion box are
      automatically transferred in the background, simply because they
      are invisible.
    </li>
    <li>
      The <i>AttachmentEdit</i> widget also demonstrates the use of
      <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WFileUpload.html"
	 target="_blank">WFileUpload</a>
      which allows for <b>asynchronous transfer of files</b>, in this
      case for uploading the attachments while editing the message.
    </li>
    <li>
      The <i>Option</i> and <i>OptionList</i> classes show how
      stateless slots may be used even when the behaviour is not
      entirely stateless. In this case, the hiding of an Option
      affects neighboring visible options to set the separator
      correctly. By <b>invalidating the stateless slot
      implementations</b> when state has changed, we can still
      get away with a stateless slot implementation, and thus
      client-side event handling performance!
    </li>
  </ul>

<p>Browse the source code:</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.dragdrop">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Drag &amp; Drop</h4>

<p>
  <a href="/wt/examples/dragdrop/dragdrop.wt" target="_blank">This example</a>
  demonstrates the usage of the Drag and drop API. Drag and drop is only
  available when JavaScript is available or enabled, so you should
  always provide an alternative if you wish to support other browsers.
</p>

<p>
  Add drag &amp; drop functionality to your application in three steps:
</p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      Specify that a
      <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WInteractWidget.html"
      target="_blank">WInteractWidget</a> is draggable (using
      <b>WInteractWidget::setDraggable()</b>). You must chose a mime
      type, and properties that specify how the dragging must be
      rendered.
    </li>
    <li>
      A drop site declares itself to accept drops of a particular mime
      type
      (see <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WWidget.html#a38"
      target="_blank">WWidget::acceptDrops()</a>. Visual feed-back of
      a drop site may be specified by changing the style when the
      mouse hovers on top of it with a compatible mime type.
    </li>
    <li>
      Finally, a drop-site re-implements <b>WWidget::dropEvent(WDropEvent)</b>
      which is called when something was dropped, and provides details on the
      mime type and the sender.</li>
  </ul>

<p>Browse the source code:</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.chat">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Simple Chat</h4>

<p>
  <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu:1410/simplechat.wt" target="_blank">
  This example</a> implements a simple chat client and server for a
  multi-user chat application. It illustrates how one can easily let
  multiple users interact, for example using <b>server-initiated
  updates</b> to push information from one user to other users.
</p>

<p>
  It also illustrates nice benefits of a class-based approach to web
  application development: you can easily instantiate the same widget
  class multiple times. The SimpleChatClient widget may be intantiated
  as easily as you use basic Wt widgets such as a push button.
</p>

<p>
  Interactive applications like these, which allow users to post HTML
  text to other users, are notorious for <b>cross-site-scripting (XSS)
  attacks</b>: a user enters malicious (javascript) code as part of
  his message. When another user renders this message, it may transmit
  unwanted private information retrieved from, for example, browser
  cookies. Wt prevents such attacks completely, and without any
  responsibility to the developer, since widgets such as WText ensure
  that what is displayed is only passive text, discarding anything
  that is not strictly text.
</p>

<p>Browse the source code:</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.fileexplorer">
<div>
<h4 class="example">File explorer</h4>

<p>
  You can <a href="/wt/examples/filetreetable/filetreetable.wt"
  target="_blank">browse the Wt source code tree</a> in an example
  demonstrating the use
  of <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTreeTable.html"
  target="_blank">WTreeTable</a>.
</p>
<p>
  WTreeTable organizes its data
  using <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTreeTableNode.html"
  target="_blank">WTreeTableNode</a> objects, which derive
  from <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WTreeNode.html"
  target="_blank">WTreeNode</a>. All these widgets inherit
  from <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WCompositeWidget.html"
  target="_blank">WCompositeWidget</a>, and therefore use only the
  public Wt API, and are all plain C++ (and only few lines of that).
</p>
<p>
  FileTreeTableNode re-implements WTreeNode::populate() to retrieve the
  contents of a directory only when needed. In addition, we use the
  LazyLoading policy of WTreeNode to only load nodes when they are
  viewed, unlike for the tree lists like the one just below for which
  we use a NextLevelLoading policy.
</p>
<p>
  This examples also demonstrates selection support in a tree
  (table). In this example, we configured extended selection, but only
  allow files to be selected (not directories).
</p>

<p>Browse the source code:</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.calendar">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Calendar</h4>

<p>
  An example of a self-contained composite widget, is
  the <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WCalendar.html"
  target="_blank">WCalendar</a> widget (330 lines of C++).
</p>

<p>
 Here we demonstrate the use of this widget, once using
 the <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/classWt_1_1WDatePicker.html"
 target="_blank">WDatePicker</a> for assisting in inputting a date
 into a text box, and two direct instantiations (see
 the <a href="/wt/doc/examples/html/Home_8C-source.html#l00397"
 target="_blank"> Home::calendarExample()</a> method for the code).
</p>
</div>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.calendar.datepicker">
    <p>A field for editing a date in conjunction with a WDatePicker:</p>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.calendar.enter-birth-date">
    Please enter your birth date:
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.calendar.plain">
    <p>A plain calendar:</p>
  </message>
  <message id="home.examples.calendar.multi">
    <p>A calendar with multiple selection:</p>
  </message>

  <message id="home.examples.widgetgallery">
<div>
<h4 class="example">Widget gallery</h4>

<p>
 <a href="/widgets" target="_blank">This example</a> demonstrates
 most widgets provided by Wt, in addition to other aspects such as
 event handling and layout classes. Useful as an executable reference
 to widgets and features provided by the library.
</p>

</div>
  </message>

  <message id="home.download">
    <h3><span>Download</span></h3>
  </message>
  <message id="home.download.license">
<h4>License</h4>

<p>Wt may be used using either the GPL or a Commercial License.</p>

<p>If you wish to use the library using the <b>GNU General Public
License (GPL)</b>, you may build a web application with Wt, and deploy
it to your own intranet or Internet web server, for any purpose,
without the requirement to make the source code freely available.
</p>

<p>Note that if you are passing on your web application in binary form,
be it selling or giving away for free, then you must include the source
code, as per terms of the GPL. This also applies to redistribution of
the Wt library, in original or modified form.</p>

<p><b>The Commercial License</b> has no such limitations. Please visit
our <a href="http://www.emweb.be/?page=license-wt">Licensing
information</a> page for license terms, pricing and ordering.</p>

<p>You may also obtain <a
href="http://www.emweb.be/?page=services">support and training</a>
options, directly from the library authors.</p>
  </message>
  <message id="home.download.requirements">
<h4>System requirements</h4>

For building and installing the latest version of Wt, you need at
least the following two packages:
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.cmake.org/">CMake cross-platform make configure
    utility</a>.

    <p>CMake 2.4 or 2.6 are preferred.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    The indispensable <a href="http://www.boost.org/">
    boost C++ library</a>: boost-1.35 or later.

    <p>Wt requires the following boost libraries: boost_date_time,
    boost_regex, boost_program_options, boost_signals, boost_system,
    and optionally (but highly recommended) boost_thread.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The other requirements depend on the connector support you would
like. The connector is what makes your Wt application communicate with
the browser:</p>

<h5>For FastCGI (Unix only):</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Apache 1 or 2, or another web server which supports the FastCGI
  protocol.</li>
  <li>
    <a href="http://www.fastcgi.com/#TheDevKit">FastCGI development kit</a>
    : fcgi-2.4.0
  </li>

   <li>
     When using apache:
     Apache <a href="http://www.fastcgi.com/dist/mod_fastcgi-2.4.2.tar.gz">mod_fastcgi</a>:
     mod_fastcgi-2.4.2.<br />Alternatively you may
     use <a href="http://fastcgi.coremail.cn/">mod_fcgid</a>:
     mod_fcgid-1.07.
  </li> 
</ul>

<h5>For the built-in httpd (wthttpd):</h5>

<ul>
  <li>The built-in httpd requires the
    <a href="http://asio.sourceforge.net/">asio C++ library</a>,
    which is included in boost.
  </li>
  <li>Optionally, libz (for compression-over-HTTP) and openssl (for
    HTTPS support).
  </li>
</ul>

Follow the <a
href="/wt/doc/reference/html/Installation.html">Installation
instructions</a> to build Wt and run the examples, or see if your
platform is listed in the <a
href="/wt/wiki/index.php/Wt_Installation">platform specific
installation instructions</a>.
  </message>
  <message id="home.download.cvs">
<h4>CVS respository</h4>

<p>If you want to keep track of the latest changes, or participate in
Wt development, you may want to connect to the source repository. Wt's
source repository can only be accessed using anonymous CVS.</p>

<p>
To checkout wt using CVS, do:
<div class="fragment">
  <pre class="fragment">$ cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@cvs.webtoolkit.eu/opt/cvs login
  (just press 'Enter' at the password prompt)
$ cvs -z3 -d :pserver:anonymous@cvs.webtoolkit.eu/opt/cvs co wt</pre>
</div>
</p>
  </message>
  <message id="home.download.packages">
    <h4><span>Available packages</span></h4>
  </message>
  <message id="home.download.version"><b>Version</b></message>
  <message id="home.download.date"><b>Date</b></message>
  <message id="home.download.description"><b>Description</b></message>

  <message id="home.community">
<h3><span>Community</span></h3>

<h4>Authors</h4>

<p>
The software was originally developed by <a
href="mailto:koen@emweb.be">Koen Deforche</a>, and is currently
maintained by <a href="http://www.emweb.be/">Emweb bvba</a>.</p>

<p>Wt includes code borrowed from other projects:</p>
<ul>
<li>The built-in httpd is based on an example of the <a
href="http://asio.sourceforge.net/">asio C++
library</a>, developed by Christopher M. Kohlhoff (<a
href="http://www.boost.org/LICENSE_1_0.txt">Boost Software License</a>).</li>
<li>Thread pool implementation from Philipp Henkel (<a
href="http://threadpool.sourceforge.net/">threadpool</a>; <a
href="http://www.boost.org/LICENSE_1_0.txt">Boost Software License</a>).</li>
<li>The <a href='http://www.minixml.org/'>Mini-XML
2.4</a> library by Michael Sweet (<a
href="http://www.minixml.org/documentation.php/license.html">Mini-XML license
  </a>, which is LGPL with some exceptions)</li>
</ul>

<h4>Wiki</h4>

<p>
There is a
community-run <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/wiki/">Wt Wiki</a>
with useful information, including installation notes for several
Linux distributions.
</p>

<h4>Support</h4>

<p>You can obtain <a href="http://www.emweb.be/?page=services">support
and training</a> options directly from the library authors.</p>

<p>In addition, there is an active <a
href="mailto:witty-interest@lists.sourceforge.net">the
mailinglist</a>, where you are welcome to get community help (<a
href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/witty-interest">info to
join the mailinglist</a>).</p>

<p>You may search or browse the mailing list archives using
the <a href="http://gmane.org/info.php?group=gmane.comp.web.witty.general">Gmane
gateway</a> (kudos to Pau Garcia i Quiles for setting this up).</p>

<h4>Sponsors</h4>

<p>Development of Wt is sponsored by the following companies and
organisations:</p>

<p>
<table>
  <tr>
    <td class="sponsor-logo"><a href="http://www.emweb.be/">
      Emweb bvba</a>
    </td>
    <td class="sponsor-role">
      Creators, official maintainers, and support
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td class="sponsor-logo">
      <a href="http://www.eurofer.be/">
      Eurofer</a>
    </td>
    <td class="sponsor-role">
      Sponsored the development of the charting library
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
</p>

<h4>Contributions</h4>

<p>User contributions are welcomed, ranging from simple patches to
widgets, widget sets, and core improvements.</p>

<p>However, because Wt is dual-licensed under an Open Source and
commercial license, and to legally protect the code base of Wt as a
whole by one entity without having to worry about the copyrights for
different pieces, we require a copyright assignment from contributors
to <a href="http://www.emweb.be/">Emweb</a> before
accepting the contribution.</p>

<h4>Translations</h4>

The Chinese translation of the homepage was provided by Zhimin Song.

<h4>Sourceforge</h4>

<a href="http://sourceforge.net"><img src="http://sflogo.sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=153710&amp;type=1" style="vertical-align:middle" width="88" height="31" border="0" alt="SourceForge.net Logo" /></a>
The Wt project is hosted at sourceforge <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/witty/">here</a>.
  </message>

  <message id="home.documentation">
 
<h3><span>Documentation</span></h3>

<h4>Build and install</h4>

<p>
Generic installation instructions (UNIX)
are <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/Installation.html">here</a>, which
is also included in the source package (INSTALL or INSTALL.html).</p>
<p>
In addition, the <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/wiki/">Wt
Wiki</a> has a section dedicated
to <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/wiki/index.php/Wt_Installation">platform
specific installation notes</a>.
</p>

<h4>Introduction and tutorials</h4>

<ul>
<li>Dr Dobbs Journal has a good <a href="http://www.ddj.com/cpp/206401952">
introductary article on Wt</a> (February 2008).</li>

<li>Software Developers Journal has a (slighly outdated) tutorial
(April 2006). The tutorial uses the Hangman example code (see also in
the examples section!). You can view a copy of the article <a
href="/wt/doc/tutorial/wt-sdj.xhtml">on-line</a> or grab a
<a href="/wt/doc/tutorial/wt-sdj.pdf">PDF copy</a>.</li>

<li>Victor Venkman wrote a
<a href="http://www.codeguru.com/cpp/i-n/internet/browsercontrol/article.php/c15275/">nice introduction to Wt</a>, with a close examination of
the <a href="/wt/examples">hello world example</a>.</li>

</ul>

<h4>Reference manual</h4>

<p>There is a a <a href="/wt/doc/reference/html/index.html"
target="_blank"> reference manual (in a new window)</a>, generated
from the source code using doxygen. This also contains a small
tutorial on the tree list example, focusing in particular on the
stateless slot implementation mechanism, which is a more advanced
feature of Wt to allow optimisation of event handling to client side
code.</p>

<h4>Annotated examples</h4>

<p>Source-level documentation has also been generated for the examples
and can be viewed <a href="/wt/doc/examples/html/modules.html"
target="_blank">here (in a new window)</a>.</p>

<h4>Wiki</h4>

<p>
There is a community-run <a href="http://www.webtoolkit.eu/wt/wiki/">Wt Wiki</a> with useful information such as a FAQ and
tips and tricks.
</p>

  </message>
</messages>
